the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home the
the
the in
the norm
are the in discussing the
continuous-time and discrete-time
Fourier transforms we
developed a number of important
properties
to particularly sitting significant ones
as I mention
at the time are the modulation property
and the convolution property
starting with the next lecture the one
after this one
will be developing and exploiting some
other consequences
the modulation property in today's
lecture though I'd like to
review and expand on the notion of
filtering
which as I had mentioned flows more less
directly from
the convolution property to begin let me
just quickly review
what the convolution property is both
for continuous-time
and for discrete-time the convolution
property tells us
that the 48 transform
all the convolution up to time functions
is the product up to 48 transforms
now what this means
in terms love linear time-invariant
filters
since we know that the in the time
domain the output of a linear
time-invariant filter is the convolution
love the input and the impulse response
it says essentially then in the
frequency domain
that the forty a transformer the output
is the product
of the 48 transform of the impulse
response
namely the frequency response and the
Fourier transform
love the input so the output is
described through that product
now recall also
bad in developing the four EA transform
I interpreted
the Fourier transform as the complex
amplitude
over decomposition of the signal interns
have a set of complex exponentials
and the frequency response for the
convolution property
in effect tells us what the amplitudes
how to modify the amplitudes
avi to those complex exponentials as
they go through the system
now this led to the notion of filtering
where the basic concept was that since
we can modify
the airport to %uh each of the
exponential
complex exponential components
separately weekend for example
retain some love them and totally
eliminate others
and this is the basic notion of
filtering so
we have as you recall first evolved the
notion
in continuous-time all an ideal filter
for example I L a straight year an ideal
low-pass filter where we pass exactly
frequency comp phone it's in one band
and reject
totally frequency comp ponents in
another band
the van being passed of course referred
to as the passband
and the ban rejected as the stopping I
illustrated here low pass filter we can
of course
reject the low frequencies and retain
the high frequencies and that then
corresponds to
ideal high pass filter or we can just
retain frequencies within a band
and so I show below what is referred to
commonly as
a bandpass filter now
this is what the ideal filters look like
for continuous-time for discrete-time we
have exactly
the same situation namely we have
an ideal discrete-time low-pass filter
which
passes exactly frequencies which are the
low frequencies
low frequencies of course being around
zero and because the periodicity also
around 2pi
we show also an ideal
high pass filter and a high pass filter
as i indicated last time passes
frequencies around pie
and finally below that I show an ideal
bandpass filter a an ideal bandpass
filter passing frequencies
someplace in the range between 0 and pie
and recall also bat the basic difference
between
continuous-time and discrete-time for
these filters is that
the discrete-time versions are of course
periodic
in frequency now let's look at
these ideal filters and in particular
the idea low-pass filter
in the time domain we have
the frequency response 0 the idea
low-pass filter
and shown below it is the impulse
response so here is the frequency
response
and below it the impulse response
love the ideal low-pass filter
and this of course is a sin x over X
for with impulse response and recognize
also
or recall that since this frequency
response
is real value
the impulse response in other words the
inverse transform
is an even function of time and
notice also since I want to refer back
to this
that the impulse response to an ideal
Lopez filter
in fact is non causal that follows from
Long other things from the fact that
it's an even function
but keep in mind in fact that sin x over
its function
goes off to infinity in both directions
so
the impulse response to the idea
low-pass filter
is symmetric and continues to have tales
of the plus and minus infinity
now the situation is basically the same
in the discrete-time case
let's look at the frequency response and
associated impulse response
for an ideal discrete-time low-pass
filter
so once again here is the
frequency response love the idea
low-pass filter
and below it I show the impulse response
again its a sin x over x-type impulse
response
and again we recognize
that sits in the frequency domain this
frequency response
is real bad that means as a consequence
of the properties love the forty a
transforming inverse Fourier transform
that the impulse response is an even
function
in the time domain and also incidently
the sin x over expulsion goes off to
infinity
again in both directions
now we talked about i do. filters
in this discussion and ideal filters are
in fact ideal in a certain sense what
they do ideally
is they pass a certain band of
frequencies exactly
and they reject a band of frequencies
exactly
on the other hand there are many
filtering problems in which
generally we don't have a sharp
distinction between the frequencies we
want to
passed in the frequencies you wanna 12
reject
one example if this that's elaborated on
in the tax is
the design of an automotive suspension
system which in fact
is the design all a low-pass filter
and basically what you want to do in a
case like that
is filter out or attenuate
very rapid Road variations and keep
the lower variations in of course
elevation of the highway
or or road and what you can see
intuitively is dead and there isn't
really a very sharp
distinction a sharp cutoff between what
you would like to recall
the low frequencies and what you would
call the high frequencies
now also somewhat related to this is the
fact dead
the as we've seen in the time domain is
ideal filters have
very particular kind of character for
example let's look back
at the ideal low-pass filter and
we saw this the impulse response
the impulse response is what we've shown
here let's now look
at the step response love the
discrete-time
ideal low-pass filter and noticed the
fact that it has a tail that oscillates
and when this step its in fact it has
oscillatory behavior
now exactly the same situation occurs
in continuous-time let's look at the
step response love the continuous-time
ideal ok pass filter and
what we see is that when a step its
then in fact we get and isolation
and very often that isolation
is something this undesirable for
example if you're designing
an automotive suspension system and you
hit a curve which is
step input in fact you probably would
not like
to have the automobile oscillating sort
sort dying down in in isolation
now is another very important point
which again
we can see there in continuous-time and
discrete-time
which is that even if we wanted to have
an ideal filter the ideal filter has
another problem
if we want to attempt to implemented in
real time
what's the problem the problem is
that since the impulse responses even
and in fact
has details that go of the plus and
minus infinity
its non causal so if in fact
we want to build a filter and the filter
is restricted operate in real time
than in fact we can't build
an ideal filter so
what that says is that in practice
although i do. filters
are nice to think about and perhaps
relate to practical problems
more typically what we consider
are non-ideal filters and
in the discrete-time case non-ideal
filter
then would have a characteristic
somewhat
like i've indicated here where instead o
a very rapid transition from passband to
stop and
there would be more gradual transition
with a passband cutoff frequency and
a stop and cutoff frequency
and perhaps also instead of having
exactly
flat characteristic in the stop band and
in the past and
we would allow a certain amount a ripple
we also have exactly the same situation
in continuous-time we're here will just
simply change your frequency axis
to a continuous frequency axis instead
of the discrete frequency axes
again we would think in terms of I'm
allowable passband ripple
a transition from stop and from passband
to stop and
with a passband cutoff frequency and a
stop and
cutoff frequency so
kind of the notion here is dead again i
do. filters are ideal in some respects
not ideal in other respects and for many
practical problems we may not want them
and even if we did want them
we may not be able to get them perhaps
because at this issue of causality
even if causality is not an issue what
happens
in filter design and implementation in
fact
is dead the sharper you attempt to make
the cut off
the more expensive in some sense the
filter becomes
either in terms of comp phone-ins in
continuous-time
or in terms of computation in
discrete-time
and so their are these whole variety of
issues
that really make it important to
understand the notion love non-ideal
filters now just two
illustrate as an example let me remind
you
love one kinda bad example love what in
fact is a non-ideal
low-pass filter and we have look
previously
at The Associated differential equation
let me now in fact related to a circuit
and in particular an RC circuit
where the output could either be across
the capacitor
or the output can be across the resistor
so
effect we have two systems here we have
a system
which is the system function from the
voltage source input to the capacitor
output
the system from the both source input
to the resistor output and in fact
just up like your cause both its law to
this we can relate those in a very
straightforward way
it's very straight forward to verify
that
the system from input to resist their
output
is simply the identity system with
the capacitor output subtracted from
now we can write the differential
equation
for either the system's and as we talked
about last time
in the last several lectures solve that
equation using
the exploiting the properties at a4e a
transform
and in fact we if we look at the
differential equation
relating the capacitor output to
the voltage source input we recognize
that this is an example
that in effect we saw previously and so
just working our way down applying the
48 transport to the differential
equation
and generating the system function by
taking the ratio of the capacitor
voltage
or its Fourier transform to the Fourier
transform the source
we then have the system function
Associated
with the system for which the output is
the capacitor voltage
or if we solve instead for the system
function
associated with the resistor output
we can simply subtract h1 from unity
and the system function that we get in
that case is the system function
that I show here so we have
now to system functions one for the
capacitor output
the other for the resistor output and
one the first corresponding to the
capacitor output
in fact if we plotted on a linear ramp
up to scale
looks like this and as you can see and
as we saw last time
is an approximation to a low pass filter
it is in fact and non-ideal ok pass
filter
whereas the resistor output is
an approximation to a high pass filter
or in effect and non-ideal high pass
filter
so in one case just comparing the two we
have
a low-pass filter as the capacitor
output associate with the capacitor
output
and a high pass filter Associated with
the
resistor out let's just quickly
look at that example now looking on a
boat reply
instead o on the linear scale that we
showed before
and recall incidently a and
be aware incident leave the fact that
week and of course cascade
several filters if this type and approve
the characteristics
so I have shown at the top
a bodie plot or the
capacitors system functions associated
with the capacitor output it's flat out
to a frequency corresponding 21
over the time constant RC
and then it falls off at 10 DB
per decade a decade being a factor 10
or if instead we looked at the system
function associated with the resistor
output that corresponds to a
10 dB per decade increase in frequency
up to approximately the reciprocal at
the time constant and
then approaching a flat characteristic
after that
and if we consider either one of these
looking back again at the low-pass
filter if we were to cascade several
filters
with this frequency response then
because we have things plotted on a boat
reply
the body plot for the Cascade would
simply be summing these and so
if we castigated for example two stages
is that a role of at 10 dB per decade it
would
role of at 20 DB for decades
now filters that this type RC filters
perhaps several of them in cascade are
in fact very prevalent
and in fact in a in a an environment
like this where where in fact doing
recording
we see there there are
filters a fact I there show up very
commonly both in the audio
and the video poker portion or the
signal processing this Associated
with making this set of tapes in fact
are let's take a look in the control
room
and what I'll be able to show you in the
control room
is the audio portion love
the processing that's done and the kinds
of filters very much of the type we just
talked about
their associated with signal processing
this stunning
in preparing the audio the tapes so
let's just take a walk into the control
room and see what we see
well this is the control room issues for
camera switching its
use for computer editing and also audio
control
you can see the monitors and these are
used for the
camera switching and and this is the
computer editing
console that use for online and offline
but I really want to demonstrate though
in a context to the lecture is the audio
control panel
which contains among other things a
variety of filters for high frequency
low frequencies cetera basically
equalization
filters and what we have in the way of
filtering is
first of all a was referred to as a
graphic equalizer
which consists of a set a bandpass
filters which are described
little more carefully in a minute and
then also
and audio Control Panel which is down
here
and which contains separate equalizer
circuits for each
over a whole set of channels and also
lotsa controls on them
well let me begin in the demonstration
by
demonstrating a little bit of what the
graphic equalizer does
okay well what we have is a set a
bandpass filters
and what's indicated appear the center
frequencies as the filters
and then a slider switch reach 18 Lexus
attenuator amplify
and this is a DP scale so essentially
if you look across this banker filters
with the output olaf for the equalizer
just being the summer the outputs from
you to these filters interestingly the
position the slider switches as you move
across here
in effect shows you what the frequency
response to the equalizer is
so you can change the overall shaping
I'll
the filter by moving the switches up and
down all right now the equalizer is
outlets
put the equaliser into the circuit and
now I I put in this filtering
characteristic
and what I'd like to demonstrate is
filtering
with this when we do things that are a
little more dramatic than what would
normally be done in a typical audio
recordings setting
and to do this let's add to my voice to
music too
make it more interesting a not the my
voice is an interesting as it is
but in any case let's bring some music
up
and now what all do is
set the low frequencies flat and let me
take out the high frequencies
above eight hundred cycle and
so now we have affectively is the
low-pass filter it
and now the low-pass filter let me know
bring the high is backup
and so on bringing up those bandpass
filters
and now let me cut-out the lows
and you'll hear the lows disappearing
and in effect
keeping the highest affectively
Crispin's
the sound my voice music
and finally let me go back 20db
equalization I need to the filters
and what also to now is
take the equalizer out at the circuit
totally
now let's take a look at the audio
Master Control Panel
and this panel has of course
for each channel and for example channel
that we're working on
a volume control I can turn the volume
down
and I can turn the volume up and
it also has a set for this particular
equalizer circuit
it has a set love 3 bandpass filters
and not switch lettuce either
put in up to 12 the be gain
or 12 DB attenuation in each of the
bands
and also a selector switch the lights is
select the center the band
so let me Jess a again demonstrate a
little bit with this and
let's get a closeup of this panel so
what we have is i indicated
is 3 bandpass filters and these knobs
that I'm pointing to hear
are controls that allow us to reach the
filters to put in
up to 12 dB gain or 12 dB attenuation
there are also with the to the filters a
selector switch
that lets us adjust the center frequency
the filter basically it's a
to position switch they're also as you
can see is
a button dead Lexus either put the
equalization in or out
currently the equalization is out but
put the equalization in
we won't be here any effect from that
because the game controls are all set at
0db
and I want to illustrate shortly the
effective these but before I do let me
draw your attention
to one other filter which is
this white switch and this this which
is a high pass filter that essentially
cuts out frequencies below about a
hundred cycle so what it means is that
but put this which in everything is more
or less flat above a hundred cycles
and what that's used for basically is to
eliminate
perhaps 60 cycle noise if that's present
or some
low-frequency home or whatever well we
won't
really demonstrate anything with that
let so now with the equalization and
demonstrate the effect I'll
boosting or attenuating the low and high
frequencies
and again I think for to demonstrate
this it's
it illustrates the point the best if a
if we have a little background music so
maestro if you can bring that up
and so now I'm gonna do is first
whose the low frequencies and that's
what this
potentiometer knob will do so now I'll
increasing the low-frequency game
and in fact all the way up to 12 the be
when I have the novel
was liza going here and so that has a
very basic
sounding back
make it even base you're fighting
my sees and
attenuating knows by
well
okay well leads words some the
high-frequency
back in
in now let's turn the low-frequency
game offers back down
20 and now we're back to flat
equalization
and now I can turn the low-frequency
game down
so dead attenuate the low frequencies by
as much as 12 the
that's where we are now in service
force much first
to enhance the highs even more hike in
addition coming out who's the highs
by his
okay well let's turn down the music now
and
and go back to no equalization by
setting these knives 20 dB in fact we
can take the equalizer out
well thats a quick look at some
real-world filters
now let's the stop having so much fun
and
let's go back to the lecture okay well
thats a little behind the scenes look
but I'd
like to do now is turn our attention to
discrete-time filters and
as i've mentioned in previous lectures
their are
basically two classes
love discrete-time filters or discrete
time difference equations
one class is referred to
as a nonrecourse ive or moving average
filter and the basic idea
with the moving average filter is
something that perhaps your
some what familiar with intuitively
think I've the notion
I love taking that data sequence and
let's suppose that what we wanted to do
was apply a some smoothing to the data
sequence
we could for example think taking
adjacent points
averaging them together and then moving
that average
along the data sequence what you can
kinda see intuitively
is that that would have apply some
smoothing so in fact
the difference equation let's say for a
three-point moving average
would be the difference equation that I
indicate here
just simply taking a data point
and the two data points adjacent to it
and forming an average over those three
so if we thought if the kinda processing
involved
if performing an output sequence value
we would take three adjacent points an
average though
that would give us the output at The
Associated time
and then to compute the next output
point we were just simply slide this
by a one-point average these together
and that would give us the next output
point and we would continue along
just simply sliding in averaging
to form the output data sequence now
that's an example love what's commonly
referred to as a three-point moving
average
in fact we can generalize that notion
in a number of ways one-way generalizing
the notion over moving average from the
three-point moving average which I
summarize again here is to think or
extending that
to a larger number of points and in fact
applying waits to that as i indicate
here
so that in addition to just summing up
the points and dividing by the number of
points on
we can in fact apply individual weights
to the points
so that its what is often referred to as
awaiting
with moving average and I show
below one possible kind of curve
that might result where these would-be
essentially the weights Associated with
this waited
moving average and in fact its easy to
verify
that this indeed corresponds to the
impulse response
the filter well just two
cement this notion let me show you an
example or two
here is an example all a
five-point moving average a five-point
moving average
would have an impulse response dead
just consists of a rectangle Lovelinks 5
and if this is convolved with the data
sequence that would corresponding
correspond to taking five adjacent
points and in effect averaging them
we've looked previously at the quarry a
transformer this rectangular sequence
and the forty a transformer that in fact
is all the form of a sign an axe over
sin x kar and as you can see
that is so approximation to
a low-pass filter and so this again is
a the impulse response and frequency
response
all a non-ideal low-pass filter
now there are a variety of both
algorithms that in fact tell you how to
choose the weights
associated with the waiting weighted
moving average
to in some sense design better
approximations
and without going into the details love
any of those algorithms
let me just show the results of choosing
the weights
for the design over 250 first 251 points
moving average filter where the weights
are chosen using an optimum algorithm to
generate a sharp a cut-off
as can possibly be generated and so what
I show here
is the frequency response
that the resulting filter on a
logarithmic ample to scale
in a linear frequency scale noticed that
on this scale the pass band is very flat
although here is an expanded you all
that and in fact it
has was referred to as an equal ripple
characteristic
and then here's the transition band and
here we have to stop and
which in fact is down somewhat more than
80 dB
and again has what's referred to as an
equal ripple characterised
now the notion of a moving average
for filtering is something dead is very
commonly
use I a head shown last time actually
the result
some filtering on a particular data
sequence the Dow Jones Industrial
Average
and very often in
looking at various kinds a stock market
publications
what you will see is this the Dow Jones
average
shown in its raw form as a data sequence
and then very typically
you you'll see also: the result all
moving average where the moving average
might
be on the order love days or it might be
on the order
months the whole notion being to take
some other random high frequency
fluctuations
out at the average and show the
low-frequency
or trends over
some period of time so let's
in fact go back to the Dow Jones average
and
let me now show you what the result of
filtering
with a moving average filter would look
like
on the Seder same Dow Jones Industrial
Average sequence that I showed last time
so once again we have the Dow Jones
average from 1927 to roughly 1932
at the top we see the impulse response
for the moving average
again I remind you on an expanded time
scale
and was shown here is the moving average
with just one point
so the output on the bottom trace is
just simply identical to the input now
let's increase the link to the moving
average 22 points and we see that
there's a small amount of smoothing
three points and just a little more
smoothing pickets inserted
now a four-point moving average
and next the five-point moving average
and a six-point moving average next we
see that the smoothing increases
now let's increase the link to the
moving average filter much more rapidly
and watch how the output is
more and more smooth in relation to the
input
again i emphasize that the timescale
for the impulse response is
significantly expanded in relationship
to the timescale for both the input in
the output
and once again through the magic of
filtering we've been able to eliminate
the 1929 stock market crash
alright so we've seen moving average
filters
and or what are sometimes referred to as
non workers is filters and
they are as I stressed very important
class
discreet I filters another
very important class of discrete-time
filters are
what are referred to as rehearses
filters
workers the filters are filters that for
which the difference equation
has feedback from the output back
into the input in other words the output
depends not only on the input but also
on previous values if the output
so for example as i stress previously
a rikers a difference equation has
the general form that I indicate year
a linear combination love waited outputs
on the left hand side and linear
combination
waited inputs on the right hand side and
as we talked about we can solve this
equation
for the current output why I have an
interns a
of current and past inputs and passed
out
what's for example just two
interpret this focus on the
interpretation of this is a filter
let's looking at a first-order
difference equation which
we've talked about and generated the
solution to previously
so the first-order a first 30 difference
equation
would be as i indicated here
and imposing causality on this
so that we assume that we are running
this is a recursion forward in time
we can solve this for why I have an
intern's affects it man
and why I have and -1 waited
by the factor a and I simply indicate
the block diagram for this but what we
want to examine now
for this first order recursion is the
frequency response and see its
interpretation
as a filter well in fact again
the mathematics for this we've gone
through in the last lecture
and so interpreting the first-order
difference equation as a system
we can what what we're attempting to
generate is the frequency response
which is the forty a transformer the
impulse response
and from the difference equation we can
of course all
for either one of those by using the
properties exploiting the properties in
for EA transform applying to 48
transport to the difference equation
we will end up with the forty a
transformer the output
equal to the Fourier transform the input
times this factor which
we know from the convolution property in
fact
is the frequency response
of the system so this is the frequency
response
and of course the inverse Fourier
transform a bad
which I E indicate below
is the system impulse response
so we have the frequency response
obtained by
applying to free a transformed to the
difference equation the impulse response
and as we did last time we can
look at that interns love
a frequency response characteristic
and recall that depending on whether
the factor A is positive or negative we
need to get
a low-pass filter or a high pass filter
and if in fact we look at the frequency
response
for the factor a being positive then we
see that this is an approximation
to a low-pass filter who wears below it
I showed the frequency response
for a negative & mare the
this corresponds to a way high pass
filter because we're attenuating
low frequencies and retaining
the high frequencies in and
recall also that we illustrated
this this characteristic as a low-pass
high-pass filter for the recursion
for the first-order recursion by by
looking at
how it work as a filter in both cases
when the input was the Dow Jones average
and indeed we saw that
it generated both low-pass and high-pass
filtering
in in the appropriate cases so for
discrete-time
we have the two classes moving average
and
a cursive filters and
and there are a variety of issues
discussed in the text about why
in certain contexts one might want to
use one or the other basically what
happens
is dead for the moving average filter
for a given set a filter specifications
there are many more multiplications
required in for a cursive filter by
there are in certain contexts some very
important compensating benefits
the moving average filter
now this concludes pretty much
what I A want to say in detail
about filtering the concept filtering in
this set of lectures
this is only a very quick glimpse into
a very important and very rich topic and
one of course that
can be studied on its own in
considerable amount of detail
as the lectures go online what will find
is that the basic concept to filtering
both
ideal and non-ideal filtering will will
be a very important part love what we do
and in in particular
beginning with the next lecture will
turn to
a discussion of modulation exploiting
the property modulation as it relates to
some practical problems
and what will find when we do that is
that
a very important part of that discussion
and in fact the very important part
love the use of modulation also
just naturally incorporates the concept
and properties filtering thank you