the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home in
the
in
the No
the in the last several lectures we
talked about
a generalization love the
continuous-time
Fourier transform and a very similar
strategy also applies to discrete-time
and that's what we want to begin to deal
with in today's lecture
so what we want to talk about is
generalizing the four EA transform
and what this will lead to in
discrete-time is a notion referred to as
the sea transport
now just as in continuous-time
in discrete-time the 48 transform
corresponded to a representation
love a sequence as a linear combination
love complex exponentials and
so this was the synthesis equation and
of course there is the corresponding
analysis equation
and as you recall and as is
the same for continuous-time the reason
that we pick complex exponentials was
because of the fact that their I can
functions of linear time-invariant
systems
in other words if you have a complex
exponential
into a linear time-invariant system the
output is a complex exponential
and the change in complex amplitude
is which corresponds to the frequency
response
in fact is what led to the definition of
the 48 transform
in particular it is the Fourier
transform
up the impulse response well
that said have notions is more or less
identical to
the way we motivated the look lost
transform
in the continuous-time case in the 48
transforming the continuous-time case
and just as in continuous-time there
it are a set signals more general
then the complex exponentials which
are also I can functions have linear
time-invariant systems
in particular and discrete-time if
we had instead love an exponential
you to the Chi Omega and we had a more
general
complex number Z bad
the signals E to the end is also
and I can function up a linear
time-invariant system
for any particular Z so
and we can see that by substituting that
it to the convolution some
and recognizing again very strongly
paralleling the
continuous-time argument head we can
rewrite this factor as Z to the N
the to the minus K and
because it the fact that it's a someone
and are some on K
and his term doesn't depend on K we can
take that term out
and the conclusion is that if we have
Z to the end as an input that
the output is love the same form times
a factor which depends on C
but of course doesn't depend on k cuz
that is
some doubt as we form the summation so
in fact
this some Asian corresponds to a complex
number
which will do no as agency
where Z will represent a more general
complex number
namely see is are
you to the jail maker are being the
magnitude of this complex number
and Omega of course being the angle so
for linear time-invariant system a more
general
complex exponential sequence up this
form
generates an output a complex
exponential sequence
have the same form with a change in
amplitude
which were representing as a gypsy
recognizing the fact that it's going to
be a function of what that complex
number is
and this amplitude factor is given by
this some Asian
and it is this some Asian which
is defined as busy transform
all the sequence H event
now let me stress that and I'll continue
to stress this is the lecture goes on
that much of what we've said is
directly parallel to what we said in the
continuous-time case
and what we simply done is to expand
from complex exponentials with a purely
imaginary exponent
complex exponential time functions are
sequences
that form into one's that have more
general
complex exponential factors
now we have a mapping here
from the impulse response to
the Tampa to or the Aiken value
associated with that input and this
mapping
is what is referred to as busy transport
so a gypsy is in fact
busy transform of the impulse response
and if we consider applying this mapping
as we did in continuous-time in a
similar argument
applying this mapping to a
sequence whether or not it corresponds
to the impulse response to the linear
time-invariant system
that leads then to busy transform
love a general sequence XFN
busy transform being defined by
this relationship and again
rotationally will often represent
a time for action and it's the transform
through shorthand notation
just indicating that accepts the
is this the transform love accident
alright so we've kind of motivated the
development
in a manner exactly identical to what we
had done with the a-plus transform
kinda the idea that if you look at the
eigen value associated
in with the linear time-invariant system
that essentially generates a mapping
between
the sequence impulse system impulse
response
and a function of Z and
that corresponds to busy transform here
at corresponded to applause transform
in a continuous-time case that same
argument
is also the argument the kinda argument
that we use
to lead us into before EA transform
originally an once again what you would
expect
is dead busy transform has a very close
an important relationship to the Fourier
transform
and indeed that relationship turned down
to be more or less identical to
the relationship between the applause
transform
in the 48 transforming continuous-time
well let's look at the relationship
for civil what we recognize is
they if we compare
the for EA transform expression
for a sequence and busy transform
expression for the same sequence
dead they involve essentially the same
operations
and in fact Cincy is of the form are
e2 the jail maker if we want
this some to look like this some
then that would mean that we would
choosy
equal to either the jail maker said
another way
busy transform onesie is a to the J
Omega
is going to reduce to before EA
transform
so we have relationship like the one
again we had between the law applies
transforming the forty a transforming
continuous-time
namely dead for certain set values
of the complex variable the transform
busy transform reduces
to the Fourier transform so if we have
ecstasy
busy transform and we look at that
for see equal to either the jail maker
and sequel to you to jail maker is
similar to saying that we're looking at
that for the magnitude of Z
equal to 1 were specifically choosing
are equal to one which is the magnitude
see then this is equal to
the four EA transform love the sequence
so busy transform frazee
equal to either J Omega is the Fourier
transform
and so this then corresponds to
X love Omega namely the Fourier
transform
well we now have ourselves in a similar
situation
again to what we had when we talked
about the applause transform
namely a notational
awkwardness or inconvenience which we
can resolve by simply
re defining some of our notation
in particular the awkwardness relates to
the fact that
whereas we've been writing or 48
transforms this way
as external make a if
we were to express XZ and look at it
it's equal to either the jail maker
we end up with the independent variable
be2 the jail maker
rather than Omega well in fact
the 48 transform is a functional Omega
it's also a function to be the jail
maker
and now we can see is dead given
the fact that we want to generalize the
four the the
for EA transformed to dizzy transform
it's convenient now
to use as notation for the four th
transform exit Z was equal to you DJ
Omega
namely are Fourier transforms will now
be written as i've indicated here
so just summarizing that our new
notation
is dead the independent variable
on the Fourier transform is now
going to be expressed as EJ Omega rather
than
as omega its a
minor notational change but I recognize
the fact that
its somewhat confusing initially and
takes a few minutes to sit down and just
get it straightened out it's very
similar to what we did with the
apostrophe in swarm
but let me draw your attention to the
fact that
in the applause transform the
independent variable that we ended up
with
in talking about the 48 transform
is different then what we're ending up
with here
in particular before we head J Omega
now we have the to the jail make
and the reason for that is simply that
the whereas in continuous time we were
talking about functions are the four
you to the st. now we're talking about
sequences the form Z to the end
alright so in we have one relationship
between the four EA transform and dizzy
transform namely
the fact that for the magnitude is equal
to 1
busy transform reduces to the Fourier
transform
now in the applause transform we also
had another important relationship an
observation
which was the fact that the
applause transform was
the Fourier transform love x50
modified and how is a modified it was
modified
by multiplying by a decaying
growing exponentially depending on what
the real part a veces
well we have a very similar situation
with dizzy transform
in particular in addition to the fact
that busy transform for a sequel the DJ
Omega
reduces to the four EA transform we'll
see
that this is a transform for other
values as the
is the Fourier transform love
the sequence with an exponential
weighting and let's see where that comes
from
here we have the expression general
expression for the transform
and recognizing that see is a complex
number which were expressing in polar
form
as are you to the jail maker
substituting that in this summation now
becomes
exit Van are you to jail make it to the
minus an
we can factor out these two turns are to
the minus and
and into the minus J Omega and and
combining the art a minus in with
excessive and
and the in the minus J Omega en
being treated separately what we end up
with
is the summation that I have here
well what this says is that the z
transform which is this
at sea equal to re: to jail maker
is in fact the four EA transform
allo what
it's the Fourier transform our love
xom.n
multiplied by art to the -10
so that is the expression
that we have here and in continuous-time
we had the applause transform is the
Fourier transform
love X 50 you to the minus Sigma T
here we have the Fourier transform
effective and art to the -10
now something to just reflect on for a
minute
is the bit because it tends to cause
little better problem with the algebra
later on if
your attention is drawn to it is that
we're talking about multiplying
excessive and
times are to the minus n the question is
for are greater than one
bizarre to -10 increase exponentially as
N increases
it is a decrease we're talking about are
to the minus and
if the matter if are is greater than one
of the magnitude of ours greater than
one for example
if it's equal to 2 are the minus and is
a half to the N
and so in fact that decreases
exponentially or more generally
the larger re: is the faster are to the
-10
DK's with increasing in
okay well let's just look at
some examples love the the transform
and examples that I picked again
are examples directly out of the text
and so
the details of the algebra you can
look at more leisurely as you sit with
the textbook
let's consider first the ball an
exponential sequence x7
equals a to the N times unit step so
zero for negative time
and an exponential for positive time
in and the Fourier transform as we've
seen in
earlier lectures is won over one minus a
it to the minus jail maker but
this doesn't always converge in
particular for convergence of the
Fourier transform
we would require absolute some ability
up the original sequence
and that in turn requires that the
magnitude have a
be less than 1 so the Fourier transform
is this
provided that the magnitude have a is
less than one
and what is the Fourier transform if the
magnitude a vase not less than 1
well the answer is that in that case it
doesn't converge
right now let's look at the Z transform
busy transform
is the some from minus infinity plus
infinity
Aug a to the N see the -10
times a unit staff the unit step will
change the lower limit 20
so some from zero to infinity and this
is all the form
eight times
Z to the -1 to the N
so we're summing from zero to infinity
eight times even minus 12 the N
that some is one over one minus AZ the
-1
but in order for that song to converge
we require that the magnitude have a
time see the -1 be less than 1
now this is busy transform is the
Fourier transform
love the sequence a to the N
times are to the -10 and
this statement about busy transforming
converging
see transform converging is exactly
identical to the statement
that what we're requiring is there the
magnet too
%uh a times art to the -1
be less than 1 where
this represents the exponential factor
that we have are that
in effect is applied to the sequence so
that
the 48 transform becomes the transform
and
so if we put this condition we can
interpret this condition
in exactly the same way day we interpret
the condition
on convergence of the 48 transform
right so from this six
from what we've worked out here then
well we have
is the see transform or
a to the N times you have an is
won over one minus AZ the -1
that works for any bad you have a
provided that we pick the value Z
correctly
in particular we have to pick the center
values UVC
so that what so that the magnitude obey
time 0 -1 is less than one
or equivalently so that the magnitude of
the
is greater than the magnitude a so
Associated with busy transform
of this sequence is this algebraic
expression
and this set of values on C for which
data algebraic expression is valid
and just as with the apostrophe its form
this range values is referred to as
the region of convergence love busy
transform
now again
as we saw with the apostrophe s form
it's important
to recognize dead in specifying
or having worked out the
d trance 4ever sequence it's not just
the algebraic expression
but also the region of convergence
that's required
to uniquely specified
to emphasize that further here is
example ten-point to from the text
and if you work that went through what
you find is that algebraically
busy transform love this sequence
is 101 minus AZ the -1
identical algebraically to what we had
up here
but now with a region of convergence
which is the magnitude of the less than
the magnitude have a
in contrast to this example
where the regional convergence was the
magnitude of the
greater than the magnitude day
alright so again requires not just the
algebraic expression
but also requires specification
the region of convergence and
also as with the applause transform
it's convenient in looking at
the z transform to
represented in the complex plane
in this case the complex plane referred
to as the
seaplane whereas in continuous time we
talked about the applause transform it
was the S point
Z of course because he is the complex
variable interns in which were
representing the sea transport
so we will be representing
the z transform interns of
representations in the complex plane
real part an imaginary part
but I've also identified a circle here
and you could wonder well what's the
significance
the circle recall
dead in the discussion that we just came
from
when we talked about the relationship
between is a transforming the 48
transform
busy transform reduces to the Fourier
when the magnitude of Z's equal to 1
the magnitude is equal to 1 in the
complex plane is a circle
and that circle in fact is a circle love
radius
1 and so its on this contour
in the seaplane that busy transform
reduces to the 48 transform and we'll
see some additional significance to that
as we go along just again emphasize the
relationship since
and differences with continuous-time
with the a-plus transform is the
behavior in the ass playing on the J
Omega axis
dead corresponds to
the Fourier transform here its the
behavior on the unit circle
with busy transform corresponds to the
Fourier transform
now we'll be talking as we did with a
plus transform
we'll be talking very often about
transforms which are rational at and
rational transfers as we kiss
was we'll see represent systems
which are characterized by linear cut
the coefficient difference equations
and so 4
the rational transfer for the rational
see transforms
will again find it convenient to use a
representation
interns opposes zeros and dizzy play so
let's
in look at are example as we worked it
out
previously example ten-point 1 and
with this sequence
busy transformers one divided by one
minus AZ the -1
and we happen to have written it as a
function of Z to the -1
clearly we can rewrite this by
multiplying
numerator and denominator by Z and this
would equivalent leave NBC divided by
see minus a
and so if we were to represent this
through a poll 0 plot we would have 0 at
the arch in corresponding this factor
and a poll at Z equals a
corresponding to the denominator factor
and
so the poll 0 pattern for this
is then a poll it's equal to a
and 0 at the origin
now let me just comment quickly about
the fact that we wrote
that we've written this as one over one
minus AZ the -1
and it seems kinda strange because
perhaps we should have multiplied
through by C
%uh let me just indicate dead
as you'll see as you work examples it's
very typical for busy transform
to come out as a function %uh Zeta -1
and so very typically you'll get to
recognize
dead things will be expressed in terms
of factors involving
terms like one minus AZ the -1 rather
than
factors are the foreign C-minus a
alright well
here is the one example that we heard
referred to
and if we consider another example
the other example which was example
10.22
consists love
a an algebraic expression as i indicate
here
but its region %uh validity is the
magnitude is the less than the magnitude
have a
and that corresponds to the same poll 0
apply but a region of convergence
which is inside this circle
whereas in the previous case
with the poll 0 plot we had a region of
convergence
which was for the magnitude at sea
greater than the magnitude have a
so these two examples this one and the
other one
have exactly the same poll 0 pattern and
their distinguished by
their regional convergence now
notice incidently that in this
particular case
the region of convergence includes the
unit circle provided that
the magnitude have a is less than one
and so in fact
that would say dead the sequence
has 48 transform that converges namely
with the magnitude see
equal to 1 whereas in this example
the regional convergence does not
include the unit circle
and so in fact we cannot look at Exit
see for the magnitude is equal to 1
and so this example with the magnitude
have a less than 1
does not have a Fourier transform the
convergence
well assuming that the bank to give a is
less than one
and the Fourier transform converges we
can in fact
look at the Fourier transform by
observing what happens as we go around
the unit circle
we've seen as for the a-plus transform
interns observing what happened as we
move along the jail make axis
and here again we can use
the vectors
as we trace out the unit circle
and in particular what we would be
looking at in this case
is the ratio of the zero vector
to the polls actor for example if we
were looking at the magnitude busy
transform
the magnitude is a transform with the
the ratio the like that this factor
to the like that this specter
and to observe the Fourier transform we
would observe
how those vectors change in length
as we move around the unit circle
and as we move around the unit circle
what we were trace out
interns the ratio the lights are those
vectors is
the for EA transform
okay well let's focus
on that also in the context
love a slightly different the
transforming dizzy transform here
as we'll see in later lecture is this
the transform associated with the
second-order
difference equation it's a it has a
denominator factor which has
which has two poles associated with it
and so here if we assumed
that the forty a transformer The
Associated sequence
converge then again we would look
at the behavior this as we moved around
the unit circle
and the ratio the links at the
appropriate vectors
would describe 4s the frequency response
I'm sorry the Fourier transform so
the Fourier transform magnitude would
consist the
the ratio the lengths
above the zero vectors divided by the
links to the poll vectors
and one thing that we observe is dead
as we move in frequency Omega in the
vicinity
love this poll this poll fact there in
fact
reaches a minimum length that would mean
there'd its reciprocal would be maximum
and then as we sweep past the lysate
these two vectors would increase the
zero vector is a course
would retain the same way no matter
where we were
on the unit circle so in fact if we look
at the Fourier transform associated with
this poll 0 pattern
if this was for example the the
for EA the represented the the
see transform or the impulse response
the linear time-invariant system the
corresponding frequency response
would be what I plotted out below and so
it would peak and in fact where it would
peak
is in the vicinity above the frequency
location of the poll
as I indicate up here
so as we sweep past is this poll
then in fact this 48 transform
peaks well
this notion love looking at the
frequency response as we move around the
unit circle
is a very important notion and it's
important to recognize that is the unit
circle that we're talking about here
whereas before
we were talking about the jail major
axis
and to emphasize this further
let me just show this example and in
fact
the previous example with the
computer display so that we can see the
frequency response
as it sweeps out as we go around the
unit circle
so here we have the poll 0 pattern
for the second-order example and to
generate the Fourier transform
we want to look at the behavior of the
polling 0 vectors as we move around the
unit circle
so first let's display the vectors
and here we have them displayed to
the point corresponding to zero
frequency
and the magnitude of the Fourier
transform
will be as we discussed the magnet to
the like that this 0 factors divided by
the magnitude of the like that the poll
vectors
shown below will be the for EA transform
and we have the Fourier transform
displayed
hear from 0 to 2pi rather than
from mine despite supply as it was
displayed in the transparency
because the periodicity the Fourier
transform
both those are acquittal
now we're sweeping away from I'll make
equal 0
and the lengths on the pole vectors have
changed
and that of course generates a change in
the 48 transform and
as we continue the process further
if we increase frequency
as we sweep closer to the location at
the pole
the polls actor decreases in length
dramatically
and net generates a residence in the 48
transform
very similar to what we saw in
continuous-time
now as we continue to sweep
further what will happen is that
that poll factor will begin to increase
in like that again
and so in fact the magnitude of the
Fourier transform
will decrease and we see that here
as we sweep toward or making equal to
pie
now notice in this process that the
like that the zero vector is has stayed
the same
because the fact that this 0 the zeros
are at the origin and no matter where we
are in the unit circle the like that
those factors is unity
so they don't influence in this example
the magnitude but they would of course
influence the face
now we want to continue sweeping from
make people to pie
around to 2pi and because the symmetry
in the Fourier transform
what we will see in the magnitude is
identical to what we would see
if we swept from a geek with the pie
back
clockwise who are making equal 0
in particular now as we're increasing
frequency
notice that the link love the poll
vector associated with the lower half
plane poll is decreasing
and so in fact that corresponds to
to generating a residence as
we sweep past that polo cation as we are
here
and then finally that poll factor
increases in Lang
as we begin to approach will make people
to 2pi
or equivalent Lee as we approach Omega
equal to 0
no finally let's also look at
the for EA transform associated with
the first order example that we
discussed earlier in the lecture
and so what we wanted look at is the
four EA transform as the poll
n0 vectors change once again
the Fourier transform will be displayed
on a scale from 0 to 2pi
frequency scale from 0 to 2pi rather
than mine despite a pie
and we want to observe the poll n0
vectors as we sweep around the unit
circle
we display first the poll n0 vectors
at Omega equal to 0 and
as the frequency increases
the polls vector increases in length
zero vector since the zeros at the
origin
will have constantly no matter where we
are on the unit circle although it would
affect the phase which we are not
displaying here
and so the principal affect the only
affect really in the magnitude
is due to the poll vector as the
frequency
continues to increase the poll vector
increases in length monotonically
in fact and so that means that the
magnitude
above the 48 transform will decrease
monotonically
until we get past Omega equal to pie
here we are now at Omega equal to pie
and when we continue sweeping past
this frequency around to 2pi then
we will see basically the same curve
swept out
in reverse sense because the symmetry
again if the 48 transform magnitude
sweeping from
hi tu Pai is going to be equivalent
with regard to the magnitude too
sweeping from pie
back to zero and so now
the poll vector begins to decrease in
length and
correspondingly the magnitude of the
Fourier transform
will increase and
that will continue until we get around
to make people to 2pi
which is equivalent of course will make
people 0
and obviously if we continue to sweep
around again we would simply
trace out other periods associated with
the forty a transport
well that hopefully gives you care some
feel for
for the notion I love %uh sweeping
around the unit circle and of course you
can see that
dead because the circle is periodic
as we go around and around of course
what would get is a periodic for EA
transform which is
the way for EA transforms are supposed
to be now
the just is
with the Laplace transform the
region of convergence that the transform
as we've seen in this example and
is a very important part the
specification
above busy transform and we can
in talking about sequences near
transforms either
specify the regional convergence
implicitly or we can't specify
explicitly
we can for example say what it is says
let's say the magnitude easy being
greater than the magnitude a
or we can recognize that the region of
convergence
has certain constraints associated with
certain properties love the time
function and
in particular there are
some important properties love the
region of convergence
which allow us given
bed we know certain characteristics at
the time function
to then identify the region of
convergence
by looking at the poll 0 pad for example
we recognize that the region of
convergence
does not contain any polls because the
fact that at polls
busy transform in fact blows up
and of course can converge at that point
furthermore
the region of convergence consists love
a ring
in the seaplane centered about the
origin
recall there with a plus transform
the regional convergence consisted of
strips in
the S plane with the sea transform the
region of convergence consist suffering
basically because if the fact that the
regional convergence
is dependent on the magnitude of Z
whereas
with a plus transform the region of
convergence was dependent on the real
party vez
the fact that is the magnitude of the
says
in effect dead all values see that have
the same magnitude
lie on a circle and so the regional
convergence you would expect
to be a concentric ring
in the seaplane furthermore as we've
already talked about and exploited
actually convergence %uh the Fourier
transform
is equivalent to the statement that the
region of convergence
includes the unit circle in the play now
in we can also associate the region of
convergence with issues
about whether the sequence is a finite
duration
alright cited or left-sided in and
let's let me sir quickly indicate again
what this I love the argument is if
we have a finite duration sequence so
that
the sequence is absolutely solvable and
therefore has a Fourier transform that
converges
then because of the fact dead it 0
outside some interval
I can multiply it by an exponentially
decaying sequence or by an exponentially
growing sequence
and since I'm only doing is over a
finite interval
no matter how I choose that exponential
will end up
with an absolutely some herbal product
so
if accident is a finite duration that in
fact the region of convergence
is the entire seaplane possibly
with the exception of the origin or
insanity on the other hand
if the sequence is a right-sided
sequence
then we have to be careful that we don't
multiply by an exponential that grows
too fast
for positive time or equivalent Lee in
we have to might have to choose the
exponential so that
it DK sufficiently fast for positive
time
as a consequence if that for a
right-sided sequence
if we have a value which is in the
region of convergence
as long as I multiply by exponentials
that DK faster than that for positive
time
then also have
convergence in other words all finite
values Z
to which the magnitude it sees greater
than this so that the exponentials die
of even faster
will also be in the region of
convergence
if we combine that statement with the
fact that there are no polls
in the region of convergence then we end
up with a statement similar to what we
had with the applause transform
here the statement is dead if the
sequences right-sided
then the regional convergence
has to be outside the outermost poll
essentially because it has to be outside
someplace and can include any polls
finally if we have
a left-sided sequence
van the if we have a value which is in
the region convergence
all values for which the magnitude see
is less than that
will also be in the region of
convergence or if ecstasy is rational
then the region of convergence must be
inside the innermost poll
and finally if we have a two-sided
sequence
then this kind of a balance between
the exponential factor that we use and
so in that case
then the region of convergence will be
ring
in the seaplane and a essentially will
extend outward to a poll
an inward to a poll so if we had
an algebraic expression let's say as
in we have here
in then
we can associate with that a region of
convergence outside this poll
and that would correspond to a
right-sided sequence
or we can associate it with it a region
of convergence
which is inside
the innermost poll and that would
correspond to a left-sided sequence
and the third and only other possibility
is a region of convergence which
lies between these two poles and
that would then correspond to a
two-sided sequence
noticed incidentally because that way
right place these polls
that this is the only one for which the
regional convergence includes the unit
circle
in other words it's the only one for
which the Fourier transform convergence
okay now we move through that fairly
quickly and
a I've emphasize the fact that it
parallels very closely what we did
with the a-plus transform what I'd like
to do
is just conclude with a discussion of
how we get the time function back again
when we have busy transform including
its regional convergence
well we can first the ball develop a
more less formal expression
and the algebra for this is going
through in the text and you went through
something similar
to this with the applause transform in
the video course manual so I won't carry
through the details
but basically well we can use to develop
a formal expression is the fact
that dizzy transform is the Fourier
transform
the sequence exponentially weighted so
we can apply the inverse
transformed to that and
that gives is not active and protective
an exponentially weighted
and if we track that through then what
we'll end up with
is an expression after we've taken care
of
few the app's lines and deltas will end
up with an expression
that expresses formally
the sequence XFN interns
love busy transform where
this in fact is a cock to her in a goal
in the complex plane
and so there's a formal expression just
as there's a formal expression for the
apostrophe its form
but in fact the more typical procedure
is
to use essentially transform pairs that
we know
together with the idea of using a
partial fraction expansion
so if we had a sequence if we had a see
transformers I indicate here
and if we expanded out
in a partial fraction expansion
then weekend recognize as
we did in a similar style with the lip
gloss transform
we can recognize dead each term
together with the identified region of
convergence
corresponds to an exponential factor
and so this term together with the fact
that we know that the magnitude of C
must be greater than to allows us
to recognize this as similar to
the example ten-point 1 and in
particular than
the sequence associated with that is
what I indicate here
and for the second term the sequence is
what I indicate here so
what we're simply doing is using the
fact that
we've worked out big the example going
one direction before
and now we use that together with the
partial fraction expansion
to get the individual sequences back
again
and then at them together is one other
method which I'll just point to
which eg is also elaborated on a little
more in the text
but it's kind of the idea I love
developing the inverse
Z transformed by recognizing dead
this the transformer formula
in fact is a power series
so if we take exigency
and expanded into power series
then we can pick of the values affect
the van
by identifying the individual
coefficients
in this expansion
okay and so by simply doing long
division for example
we can also get the inverse transform
and that by the way is very useful
particularly
if we want to get the inverse see
transform
for z transform expression which is not
rational
right now we move through this fairly
quickly on the other hand I stress
dead it's very similar to what we went
through for the applause transform
except
for a very important difference
the principal difference really being
that with a plus transform it was the J
Omega axis and the S plane
that we focused attention on when we're
thinking about the Fourier transform
here the unit circle in the seaplane
plays an important role
well we'll see when we continue this in
the next lecture is dead
there are properties are busy transform
just as they were properties of us
transform
and those properties allow us
to develop and exploit
busy transform in the context love
systems describable by when your
constant coefficient difference
equations
so in the next lecture will focus on
some properties busy transform and then
we'll see
how to use those properties to help us
in getting further insight and working
with system
describe a wall by difference equations
thank you