the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU Horan
the
the in
the new
the the
during the course we've developed a
number
love very powerful and useful tools and
we've seen how
these can be used in designing and
analyzing systems for example for
filtering for modulation et cetera
I'd like to conclude this
series of lectures with an introduction
to one more
important topic namely the
analysis love feedback systems and
what are the principal reasons that we
have left
this discussion to the last part of the
cores is so that we can exploit
some of the ideas that we've just
developed in
summer the previous lectures namely the
tools afforded us by
applause NZ transforms now
as I had indicated in one of the
very first lectures a common example
a feedback system is the problem love
let's say
balancing a broom or in the case if that
lecture balancing
my son's force on in the palm of your
hand
and kinda the idea there is dead
what that relies on in order to
make that a stable system is feedback in
that particular case visual feedback
that specific problem the one about
saying something let's say in the palm
of your hand
is an example love a problem which is
commonly referred to as
inverted pendulum and it's one that we
will actually be analyzing
in a fair manner detailed not in this
lecture but in the next lecture
but let me just kinda vindicate what so
the issues
are let me describe this into context
not over balancing a broom on your hand
but
let's say that we have a mechanical
system which consists of a card
and the card can move let's say in one
dimension
and it has mounted on it
a bar a ride with the weight on the top
and it pivots around the base so that
essentially represents the
inverted pendulum so that system can be
more or less depicted as i've indicated
here and this is the cart
that can move along the x-axis and
here we have a pivot point a ride await
at the top
and then of course there's several
forces acting on this and
their is an acceleration that can be
applied to the cart:
and that will be thought a as the
external input
and then on the pendulum itself on the
wait
there is the force of gravity and
then typically said if external
disturbances that might
represent for example air currents or
wind or whatever
dead will attempt to
Dez to destabilize the system
specifically
to have the pendulum fall down now
if we look at this system in more or
less
a straightforward way what we have then
are the system dynamics and
several inputs one of which is the
external disturbances
and the second is the acceleration which
is
the external acceleration is supplied
and the app for the system can be
thought I love
as the angular displacement love the
pendulum which
if we want a balanced we would like that
angular displacement to be equal to 0
now if we know exactly what the system
dynamics are
and if we knew exactly what the external
disturbances are
invented principal we could design and
acceleration namely an input
dead would exactly generate
0 output in other words the angle would
be equal to 0 but as you can imagine
just is its basically impossible to
balance a broom
in the palm of your hand with your eyes
close
what is very hard to ascertain in
advance or what the various
dynamics and disturbances are and so
more typically
what you with a kid doing is measuring
the output angle and
then using that measurement to somehow
influence the applied acceleration or
fours
and that then is an example other
feedback system
so we would major the output angle
and generate
an input acceleration which is
some function love what that output
angle is
and if we choose the feedback dynamics
correctly
then in fact we can drive this output 20
this is one example love a system
which is inherently unstable because if
we left it to its own
devices the pendulum with simply fall
down and essentially by applying
feedback
what we're trying to do is stabilize
this inherently unstable system
and we'll talk a little bit more about
that specific application feedback
shortly another common example a
feedback
is in positioning our tracking systems
and I aid indicate one here
which corresponds to the problem love
positioning
a telescope which is mounted on a
rotating platform
so in a system that tape for example
I indicate here the rotating platform in
the telescope
it's driven by a motor and again
we could imagine in principle the
possibility love
driving this to the desired angle
by choosing an appropriate applied input
voltage
and as long as we know such things as
what the disturbances are that influence
the telescope mount and what the
characteristics that the motor are
in principle we could in fact
carry this out in a form which is
referred to as open loop
namely we can choose an appropriate
input voltage
to drive a motor to set
the platform ankle at the desired
angular position
however again there are enough unknowns
in a problem like that
so that one is motivated to employ
feedback namely to make a measurement
up the output angle and use that in a
feedback loop
to influence the press the drive for the
motor
so that the motor so that the telescope
platform is positioned appropriately
so if we look at this in a feedback
context we would then
take the measured output angle
and the measured output angle
would be fed back and compared
with the desired angle and
the difference between those which
essentially is the error between the
platform positioning and the desired
position
would be put perhaps through an
appropriate gainer attenuation
and used as the exhortation to the motor
so in the mechanical or physical system
that would correspond to measuring the
angle let's say
with the potentiometer so here we're
measuring
the angle and we have an output which is
proportional
to that measured angle and then we would
use
feedback comparing
the measured angle to some
proportionality factor multiplying the
desired angle
so here we have the desired angle
again through some type a potentiometer
the two are compared I do the comparator
we basically have an indication of what
the difference
is and that represents an error between
the desired in the true Engel
and then that is used through perhaps an
amplifier
to control the motor and in that case
of course when the air goes to zero that
means that the actual angle on the
desired angle
are equal and in fact in that case also
with this system
the input to the motor is likewise equal
to 0
now and as i've illustrated here
it tends to be in the context or a
continuous-time
or analog system and in fact another
very common
way of doing positioning or tracking is
to instead implement the feedback
using a discrete I'm a digital system
and so in that case we would basically
take the
position output as its measures
sample at a sexually
convert that to additional discrete-time
signal and then that is used in
conjunction
with the desired angle
which both foreign ports to this
processor
and the output a bad is converted let's
say back to
and a an analog a continuous-time
voltage and used to drive the motor
now you could ask why would you go to
a digital or discrete time measurement
rather than doing it
the way a I showed on the previous
overlay which seemed relatively
straightforward
and the reason principally is dead in
the context of a digital implementation
the feedback process often
you can implement a better controlled
an offense also more sophisticated
algorithm for the feedback dynamic so
that you can take a cab perhaps not only
the angle itself but also love the rate
of change a bang going in fact
the rate of change in the rate of change
in angle and
so the system Isis shown air then
is basically has a discrete-time
or digital feedback loop around a
continuous-time system
now open this is an example 0
in fact the more general way in which
discrete-time feedback is used with
continuous systems and
let me indicate in general what such
what the character a block diagram such
a system might be
typically if we abstract away from the
telescope Positioning System
we might have a more general
continuous-time system
and around which we want to apply some
feedback which we could do with a
continuous-time system
or with the discrete-time system by
first
converting the signals to discrete-time
signals
then processing that with a
discrete-time system
and then through inappropriate
interpolation algorithm
we would then convert that back to
a continuous-time signal and
the difference between the input signal
and this continues to signal which is
fed back
then forms the exhortation to the system
that
essentially we're trying to control and
in
many systems that this type the
advantage
is that this system can be implemented
in a very reproducible way either with a
digital computer computer
or with microprocessor and although
we're not going to go into this in any
detail
in this lecture there is some discussion
this in the text
essentially if we make certain
assumptions about
this particular feedback system we can
move the continues to discrete-time
converter
up to this point and to this point and
we can move
the interpolating system outside
the summer and what happens in that case
is that we end up with what
looks like an inherently discrete-time
feedback system so in fact we take those
steps
then what we'll end up with for a
feedback system
is a system that essentially
can be analyzed as a discrete-time
system
here we have what is in the forward path
and is basically the continuous-time
system
with the interpolator at one end and it
continues to discrete-time converter at
the other end
and then we have whatever system it was
in the feedback loop
discrete-time that shows up in this
feedback loop well show this
mainly to emphasize the fact although
there are some steps there that we
obviously left out
I show that mainly to emphasize the fact
that feedback arises
not just in the context of
continuous-time systems
but also the analysis love discrete-time
feedback systems becomes important
perhaps because
we have used discrete-time feedback
around a continuous-time system
but also perhaps because the feedback
system
is inherently discrete-time in lobby and
just illustrate
one or indicate one example in which
that might arise this is an example
in which which is also
discussed in so in more detail in the
text
but basically population studies for
example
represent examples all discrete-time
feedback systems
where let's say that we have some type
of model
for population growth and since people
come
in imager amounts that represents
essentially
the the I the output over any population
model
essentially are inherently represents a
sequence namely its index
on an integer variable
and typically models for population
growth
are unstable systems you can kind
imagine that because
if you take simple models the population
and what happens is that
the in any generation the
number all people or
animals or whatever it is that this is
modeling
grows essentially exponentially I love
with
the size the previous generation now
where does the feedback come in
well the feedback typically comes in in
in
incorporating in the overall model
various retarding factors for example
as the population increases the food
supply becomes more limited
and that a sexually as a feedback
process
dead acts to
retard the population growth and so
an overall model are somewhat simplified
for a for a population system
is the open-loop model in the absence of
retarding factors
and then very often the retarding
factors
can be described as being related
to the size of the population and those
essentially act to reduce
the overall input to the population
model
and so population studies are
one very common example love
discrete-time feedback systems
well what would a look at and understand
are the basic properties love
feedback systems and to do that
let's look at the basic block diagrams
and equations
for feedback systems either
continuous-time and discrete-time
let's begin with
the continuous-time case
and now what we've done is simply
abstract out
any of the applications to a fairly
general system
in which we have a system HVS
in what's referred to as the forward
path
and a system GIS in the feedback path
and the the
input to the system HVS is the
difference between the input to the
overall system
and the output out the feedback loop
and I draw your attention to the fact
that
what we illustrate here and what we're
analyzing is negative feedback
namely this out this output is attracted
from the input and thats done
more for reasons have convention than
for any other reasons
its typical to do that an appropriate
certainly
in some feedback systems but not all and
the output of the answer is commonly
referred to as the error signal
indicating that is the difference
between the signal fed back
and the input to the overall system
now if we want to analyze the feedback
system
we would do that essentially by writing
the appropriate equations
and its best done and generating
the equivalent system function for the
overall system
it's best on in the frequency or poss
transform domain
rather than a in the time domain and let
me just indicate
what the steps are that are involved in
there are few steps have algebra that
I that I'll leave in your hands but
basically if we look at
this feedback system we can label of
course is the output is why ft
we can label they look lost transform
the output is why evas
and we also have YS as the input here
because this is the system function the
apostrophe s former varsity is simply
the applause transformer this and for
which is why our best times Govs
so here we have why evas times
Govs at the air
the input here is excessive ass
and so the law applies transform of the
error signal
is simply exit ass
minus our best which is why I've SG a
vast so this is minus why evas
GFS thats
the love postures for the error signal
the apostrophe its form
all the output if this system is simply
this expression times HFS
so that's what we have here but what we
have here we already called why evas
so in fact we can simply say dead
these two expressions have to be equal
and so we've essentially done the
analysis
saying that those two expressions are
equal lets us
solve for y más over Xmas which is the
overall system function
and if we do that what we end up with
for the overall system function
is the algebraic expression that I
indicate here
its HFS divided by one-plus
GFS HFS said another way
its the system function in the open-loop
forward path
divided by one-plus what's referred to
as the loop gain
GFS times HFS let's just look back up at
the block diagram
GFS times HFS is
simply the gain around the entire loop
from this point around to this point
so the overall system function is the
gain in the forward path
divided by one-plus the loop gain which
is
HFS times GFS now
none of the equations that we wrote head
relied specifically on this being
continuous time we just did some algebra
and we use the system function property
of the system's
at so pretty obviously the same kinda
algebraic procedure would work in
discrete-time
and so in fact if we carried out a
discrete-time analysis
rather than a continuous-time analysis
we would simply
and up with exactly the same
system and exactly the same
a question for the
overall system function the only
difference being that
here things are functional see whereas
if I just flipped back
the other overlay we simply have
previously everything as a function of
tea and a frequency-domain
s in the discrete-time case
we've simply replaced in the time domain
the independent variable by
and and in the frequency domain
the independent variable by C
so what we see is that
the we have a basic feedback equation
and that feedback equation is exactly
the same for continuous-time and
discrete-time
although we have to be careful about
what implications we draw
depending on whether we're talking about
continuous-time
for discrete-time
now to illustrate
the importance a feedback let's look at
a number love common applications
and also as we talk about these
applications will see
is dead while these applications
and context in which feedback is used
are
extremely useful and powerful they
fallout in a an almost straightforward
way
from is very simple feedback equation
that we've just arrived well
the examples that I want to just talk
about
are for civil the
use the feedback in amplifier design and
we're not going to
design ample fires in detail but what
I'd like to illustrate
is the basic principle behind why
feedback
is useful in designing amplifiers in
particular
how it plays a role in compensating
for a9 constant frequency response
that's so that's one context that will
talk about
a second that I'll indicate is the use
the feedback
for implementing infers systems
and a third which we indicated it
in the case the inverted pendulum is
important
context in which feedback is used is in
stabilizing unstable systems
and what we want to see is wire how
the a feedback system where the basic
feedback equation
in fact letters to each of these various
things
well let's begin with amplifier design
and let's suppose that we've
built somehow without feedback
and ample fire that is terrific in terms
of its game
but has the problem dead whereas we
might like the ample fire to have
a very flat frequency response in fact
the frequency response to the sample
fire
is 9 constant and what we'd like to do
is compensate for that well it turns out
interestingly
dead if we embed the amplifier in a
feedback loop
where in a feedback path we incorporate
an attenuator
then in fact we can compensate for that
nine constant frequency response
well let's see how that works out for
the feedback equation
we have the basic feedback equation we
derive that we want to look at frequency
response
so we look specifically at the Fourier
transform and of course
the frequency response to be overall
system is
the frequency response to the out at the
Fourier transform the output divided by
the input using the feedback equation
that we just arrived
that has in the numerator the frequency
response in the forward path divided by
one plus
the loop gain which is hijo may get
times K
and this is the key because here
if we choose K times HJ Omega
to be very large much larger than 1
then what happens is that these two
cancel out hijo may get times hijo
Hojo Maki here and in the denominator
will cancel out
as long as this term dominates and in
that case
under that assumption the overall system
function is approximately
one over K
well if K is constant
as a function of frequency then we
somehow magically have ended up
with an amplifier that has a flat
frequency response
well it seems like we're getting
something for nothing and actually
were not there's a price that we pay for
that because
notice the fact dead in order to get
gain out at the overall system
K must be less than one so this has the
correspond to an attenuator
and we also require that
K which is less than one times the game
up the original amplifier
that that product be greater than one
and the implication of this without
tracking it in detail right now the
implication it in this
is dead whereas we flattened the
frequency response
we have in fact been paid a price for
that the price we paid is that
the game is somewhat reduced from the
gain
that we had before the feedback because
k times H
must be much larger than 1 but the
gayness
is proportional to one over K now one
last point to make
related to that when Caswell why is it
any easier
to make a flat with frequency then
to build a flat an amplifier with the
flat frequency response
the reason is that the gain in the
feedback path
is an attenuator not an amplifier and
generally attenuation with a flat
frequency response is much easier to get
then gainers for example a resistor
which
attenuates with generally have a flatter
frequency response at a very high gain
amplifier
part so p.m. that's one common example
feedback that and feedback in fact is is
very often used in
high-quality ample fire systems another
very common example
in which feedback is used is in
implementing inverse systems
now what I mean by that is suppose that
we have a system which indicate here P
evas
input and output and what we would like
to do
is implemented a system which is the
infers that this system
namely has a a-plus transformer system
function
which is one over pls in for example
we may have measure a particular system
and what we would like to design is a
compensator for it
and the question is by putting this in a
feedback loop
can we in fact implement
the inverse that this system the answer
to that is yes
and the feedback system in that case is
as i indicate here
so here what we choose to do
is to put the system whose inverse we're
trying to generate
in a feedback loop and
in this case a high-gain in the forward
path
now for this situation k is again a
constant but in fact that the high-gain
constant
and now if we look at the feedback
equation then
what we see is equation if this form
and notice that if K ties PFS
is large compared with one
then this term dominates the gain in the
forward path cancels out
and what we're left with is a system
function
which is just one over
PFS an a sister this type
is used in a whole variety of contexts
one very common one
is in building what a call like a
rhythmic devices are like rhythmic
amplifiers
ones in which the input output
characteristic is like a rhythmic
it's common to do that with a diode
that has an exponential characteristic
and
using that with feedback as feedback
around a high gain operational amplifier
and by the way
the logarithmic amplifier is nonlinear
what I said here's linear
or the analysis here was linear but that
example in fact
suggests something which is true which
is that
that same basic idea in fact can be used
often in the context of nonlinear
feedback and nonlinear feedback systems
alright well as a final example
what I'd like to analyze is the context
in which
we would consider stabilizing
unstable systems and
I had indicated that one context in
which that arises and
a which we will be analyzing the next
lecture
is the inverted pendulum and
in that situation or in a situation
where
we're attempting to stabilize an
unstable system
we have now in the forward path
a system which is unstable
and in the feedback pair
we put inappropriate system
so that the overall system in fact is
stable
now how can stability at high rise
outta having and initially unstable
system
well again if we look at the basic
feedback equation
the overall system function is the
system function for the forward path
divided by a one plus the loop gain GFS
times HFS
and for stability
what we want to examine are the roots
have one plus GFS times HFS
and in particular the polls are
zeros up that factor
and as long as we choose GFS so that
the polls love this term
I'm sorry so that the zeros at this term
are in the left after the S plane
then what we'll end up with is stability
so
stability is dependent not just on HFS
for the closed-loop system
but on one plus GFS times hrs
and in this kind of notion
is used in lots of situations
I indicated the inverted pendulum
another very common example
is in some very high performance
aircraft
where the basic aircraft system
is an unstable system but in fact
it's stabilized by putting the right
kinda
feedback dynamics around it and those
feedback dynamics might in fact
involve the pilot is well
now 4
the system that we just talked about in
the stability was
described in terms of a continuous-time
system
and the stability condition that we end
up with of course relates
to the zeros love this the nominator
term
and we require for stability dead the
real parts
love The Associated roots bien the left
after the S point
exactly the same kind analysis in terms
of stability
apply is in discrete-time that is
in discrete-time as we saw previously
the basic discreet I feedback system is
exactly the same except that the
independent variable
is now an integer variable rather than a
continuous variable
the feedback equation is exactly the
same
so to analyze stability of the feedback
system
we would want to look at this zeros love
one-plus
GFZ times agency so again it's those
zeros
that affect stability and the principal
difference
between the continuous-time and
discrete-time cases
is the fact that the stability condition
in discrete-time is different than it is
in continuous time namely
in continuous-time we care for stability
about polls of the overall system
being in the left and left after the
espy to the right half vs plane
in discrete-time what we care about is
whether the polls are inside or outside
the unit circle
so in the discrete-time case
what we wait impose for stability is
that the zeros
have a magnet to which is less than one
so the basic analysis is the same but
the details at the stability condition
of course it different
now wet just indicated
is that feedback can be used
to stabilize unstable system
and as you can imagine is the other side
of the coin
namely if you start with
a stable system and put feedback around
it
if you're not careful what can happen in
fact is that you can destabilize the
system
so is always the potential hazard unless
it's something you want to have happen
dead feedback around what used to be a
stable system
now generates a system which is on
stable and their
are lots of examples at that one very
common example
is in audio systems and this is probably
an example that your
somewhat familiar with basically
an audio system if you have the speaker
and microphone in any kind of proximity
to each other
is in fact the feedback system well
first of all the audio input
to the microphone consists of
the external audio inputs
which and the external audio inputs
might for example
I be my voice that might be the room
noise
and in fact as well as trade shortly if
I'm not careful
might in fact be the output from speaker
which represents feedback
that audio of course drives
after appropriate amplification drives
a speaker and
if in fact the speaker
is let's say has any proximity to
the microphone then there can be a
certain amount of the output to the
speaker
that feeds back around
and is fed back into
the microphone now
if the system function associated with
the feedback to indicate here as a
constant
times into my SS times capital T
the in the minus s times capital T
represents the fact
that their is in general some delay
between the time delay between the
speaker output
and the input that it generates to the
microphone
the reason for that the lay of course
being dead
there may be some distance between the
speaker and microphone
and the constant k to that I have in the
feedback path
represents the fact that between the
speaker in the microphone
there may be some attenuation so
if I have for example speakers I happen
to have here
and I were too
have that speaker putting out
what in fact I'm putting into the
microphone or the app for the microphone
than what we have is a feedback path and
the feedback path is from the microphone
through the speaker I did the speaker
back into the microphone
and the feedback path is from here
to the microphone and the
characteristics or frequency response
our system function
is associated with the characteristics a
propagation a transmission
if I we move closer to the speaker and I
by the way don't have the speaker on
right now and I'm sure you all
understand why
a in if I move closer then
the constant k2 gets what
gets larger and if I move further away
the constant k to get small
Bardwell let's look at and analysis if
this and see what it is or why it is
that in fact we
getting instability in terms or that any
stability is predicted by the basic
feedback equation
now notice first of all they were
talking about positive feedback here
and just simply substituting the
appropriate
system functions into our basic feedback
equation
we have an equation that says that the
overall system function
is given by the forward gain which is
the gain of the amplifier
between the microphone and speaker
divided by
one minus because in the minus because
we have positive feedback
the overall loop gain which is k1 k2
either minus s capital T and these two
games k1 and k2
are are assumed to be positive and
and generally are positive so in order
for us to a
well if if you want to look at the polls
at the system
then we want to look at this zeros this
the nominator
and the zeros is this the nominator
occur at values %uh vests
such that you to the minus s capital T
is equal to 1 over K one times k2
and acquittal early that says that
the the polls love the closed-loop
system
occur at one over capital T in capital T
is related to the time delay one over
capital T
times the lock to the basie fk1 times k2
well for stability we want
these polls to all be in the left after
the S plane
and what that means then is that for
stability
well we require is dead k1 times k2
be less than 1 in other words we require
that the overall loop gain
the less the magnitude lou came P less
than 1
if it's not then what we generate is
instability
and just to illustrate that let's turn
the speaker on
and what will demonstrate is feedback
right now the system is stable are and
I'm being careful to keep my distance
from the speaker
as I get closer k2
will increase and as k2 increases
eventually the polls will move into the
right here for the S plane
or they'll try to what will happen is
that the system will start oscillating
going to nonlinear distortion
so as I get closer you can hear that
we get feedback we get isolation and you
I guess neither you nor I can take too
much bad food
the unseeded what's happening if we can
just turn the speaker of now
and you can see that what's happening is
that as
k2 increases the polls are moving
on to the jail make axis the system
starts docile aid
their own actually moving to the right
half plane because
there are nonlinear nonlinearities that
inherently control system
okay so what we've seen
in the lecture at today's lecture
is the basic analysis equation and
a few of the applications and one
application
that or one both application hazard that
we've talked about
and is the application in which we
may destabilize unstable systems or if
we're not careful
destabilize stable systems as i've
indicated several
times during the lecture one common
example
love unstable system which feedback can
use be used to stabilize
is the inverted pendulum which I refer
to several times
and in the next lecture what I'd like to
do is
focus in on a more detailed analysis at
this
and what we'll see in fact is dead
the feedback dynamics the former the
feedback dynamics
are important with regard to whether you
can it can stabilize the system
interestingly enough for this particular
system as we'll see in the next lecture
if you simply try to measure the angle
and feed that back that in fact you can
stabilize the system
water requires is not only the angle
but some information about the rate of
change angle
but will see that in much more detail in
the next lecture
thank you