the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home in
the
the in
the new the
last time we introduce the La Paz
transform
as a generalization the Fourier
transform and just as a reminder
the lacrosse transform expression as we
developed it
is this integral very much
similar to the Fourier transform
integral
except with more general complex
variable and in fact we
developed and talked about the
relationship between the apostrophe is
forming a 48 transform
in particular the apostrophe s form
where the Posterous for variable ass
purely imaginary in fact reduces
to the 48 transform or
more generally with the process for
variable as a complex number
the a-plus transform is
the Fourier transform love the
corresponding time
function with an exponential weighting
and
also as you should recall the
exponential weighting introduce the
notion that
the repost transform may converge for
some bad use
Sigma and perhaps not for other values
Sigma
so associated with the look lost
transform
was what we refer to as the region of
convergence
now just says
with the Fourier transform there are a
number of properties
the applause transform that are
extremely useful
in describing and analyzing signals and
systems
for example one other properties
that we in fact took advantage out in
our discussion last time
was the limit linearity property which
says
in essence that they'll a-plus transform
love the linear combination
up to time functions is the same
linear combination love the associated
with boss transforms
also there is a very important and
useful property which tells us
how the derivative overtime function
or rather the applause transformer the
derivative
is related to the low-priced transform
in particular
the a-plus transformer the derivative is
the apostrophe is for affective T
multiplied by ass and as you can see by
just sending a sequel to jail maker
in fact this reduces to the
corresponding Fourier transform property
and
a third property that in fact will make
frequent you so
is referred to as the convolution
property
again a generalization of the
convolution property for 48 transforms
here the convolution property says that
the applause transform the convolution a
two-time functions
is the product love The Associated
the floss transforms now
its important at some point
to think carefully about the region of
convergence
as we discuss these properties and let
me just
draw your attention to the fact dead in
discussing properties fully and in
detail
one has to pay attention not just to
how the algebraic expression changes
but also what the consequences are for
the region of convergence
and thats discuss in somewhat more
detail in the text and I won't do that
here
now the convolution property
leads to of course a very important and
useful
mechanism for dealing with linear
time-invariant systems
very much as the 48 transformed did in
particular
the convolution property tells us that
if we have a linear time-invariant
system
the output in the time domain of course
is the convolution
of the input and the impulse response
in the applause transform domain the
a-plus transformer the output
is the love plus transformer the impulse
response
times the low-priced transformer the
input
and again this of course is a
generalization
love the corresponding property for 48
transports
in the case I'll the 48 transform
the Fourier transform the appalls
response we refer to as the frequency
response
in the more general case with applause
transforms
it's typical to refer to the apostrophe
its former the impulse response
as the system function
now the
in talking about the system function
the issue some issues love the region of
convergence and for that matter location
opposes the system function
are closely tied in and related
to issues of whether the system is
stable and causal
and in fact there's some useful
statements that can be made
that play an important role throughout
the further discussion
for example we know from previous
discussions
that the there's a condition for
stability of a system which is absolute
integrability of the impulse response
and that in fact is the same condition
for convergence of the Fourier transform
of the impulse response
what that says really is that
if a system is stable then the region of
convergence
of the system function must include the
che Omega axis which of course is where
the applause transform reduces to the
Fourier transform
so that relates the regional convergence
and stability
also you recall from last time
that we talked about the regional
convergence associated with
right-sided time functions in particular
for right-sided time function the reach
of convergence
must be to the right the rightmost poll
well if in fact we have a system that's
causal
then the that causality
imposes the condition that the impulse
response be right sided
its own fact for causality we would have
a regional convergence
associated with the system function
which is to the right to the right most
poll
now interestingly in very important is
the consequence if you put those two
statements together
in particular your lead to the
conclusion
that for stable causal system
all the polls must be in the left half
up the ass play what's the reason
the reason of course is that if the
system is stable in causal
the regional convergence must be to the
right of the rightmost poll
it must include DJ Omega axes obviously
then
all the polls must be in the left after
the S
and again that's an issue that is
discussed
somewhat more carefully and in more
detail in the text
now the properties that we're talking
about here
are not the only properties there are
many others
but these properties in particular
provide
the mechanism as they did with Fourier
transforms
for turning linear constant coefficient
differential equations into algebraic
equations
and correspondingly lead to a mechanism
for dealing with solving when your
constant coefficient differential
equations
and I'd like to illustrate that by
looking
at both first-order and second-order
differential equations
let's begin first evolve with the
first-order
differential equation and in so what
we're talking about
is a first order system
what I mean by that is a system that's
characterize by a first-order
differential equation
and if we apply to this equation the
differentiation property then
the derivative the prosperous for the
derivative
is s times the apostrophe s former the
time function
the linearity property allows us to
combine these two gether
and so consequently applying the law
applies transformed to this equation
leads us to this algebraic equation and
following that through
leads us to the statement that the
a-plus trance for the output
is one over est plus a times the
applause transformer the input
we know from the convolution property
that in fact this full price transform
is the system function
times X evas and so one over est plus a
a
is the system function or equivalently
the applause transform of the impulse
response
so we can determine the impulse response
by taking the inverse Laplace transform
all HFS given by one over est plus a
well we can do that using the inspection
method which is one way that we have
doing inverse Laplace transforms the
question is then what time
function has a plus transform which is
one over est plus a
the problem that we run into in fact is
that there are two answers to that
one over est plus 80 is the applause
transform
are an exponential for positive time
but one over est plus a is also the
apostrophe s for
Aug an exponential for negative time
which one of these do we end up picking
well recall that the difference between
the
is was in their region of convergence
and in fact
in this case this corresponded to a
region of convergence
which was the real part a vast greater
than minus a
in this case this was the corresponding
applause transform
provided at the real party bass is
less than mine is a so we have to decide
which region of convergence that we pick
and it's not the differential equation
that will tell us that
its something else that has to give us
that information
what could it be well what it might be
is the additional
information that the system is either
stable or causal
so for example if the system was causal
we would know that the regional
convergence is to the right of the poll
and that would correspond and to this
being the impulse response
whereas with a negative
I'm sorry with a positive if we knew
that the system let's say was not causal
then we would associate with that this
region convergence
and we know that we would know then that
this is the impulse response
so a very important point is that
what we see is that the when your car is
the coefficient differential equation
gives us the algebraic
expression for the system function
but does not tell us about the region of
convergence we get the region of
convergence
from some auxiliary information what is
that information
well it might for example the knowledge
that
the system is perhaps table
which tells us that the regional
convergence includes the jail making
axis
or perhaps causal which tells us that
the region of convergence
is to the right to the right most poll
so it's the auxiliary information
specifies 4s the region of convergence
very important point the differential
equation by itself is not completely
specify
the system it only essentially tells us
what the algebraic expression is for the
system function
alright that's a first order example
let's now look at
a second-order system and the
differential equation that I picked
in this case I've parameterized in a
certain way which will see will be
useful
in particular it's the second order
differential equation and I've chosen
just for simplicity to not include
a derivatives on the right hand side
although we could have
in fact if we did that would insert
zeros into the system function
as well as the polls inserted by the
left hand side
we can determine the system function in
exactly the same way namely apply the
applause transformed to this equation
that would convert this differential
equation to
an algebraic equation and now on we
solve
this algebraic equation for why a bass
in terms of x a badass it will come out
in the former why evas
equal to H a vast times X a badass
and H invest in that case we would get
simply by dividing out by this
polynomial an ass and so the system
function and
is the expression that I have here
so this is the form for second-order
system
where there are two pole since this is
the second order polynomial
there are no zeros Associated
in with the fact that I had no
derivative up the input on the right
hand side of the equation
well let's look at this example
namely the second-order system a little
more detail
and what we want to look at is the
location at the polls and some issues
such as for example the frequency
response
so here again I have the algebraic
expression for the system function
in and as i indicated this is the second
order polynomial
which means that we can factor it into
two routes
and so c1 and c2 represent the polls
have the system function
and in particular in relation to the two
parameters
say to and Omega Sapan if we look at
what these routes are than what we get
are the to expressions that I have below
and notice incidently dead if data is
less than 1 than what's under the square
root
is negative and so this in fact
corresponds to an imaginary
part an imaginary term for Zeta less
than 1
and so the two routes then have
a real part which is given by -8 Omega
Sapan
and an imaginary part if I were to
rewrite this
and then expressed in terms or Jr
skirted -1
in looking below will have a real part
which is -8 Omega Sapan an imaginary
part which is omega Sapan
times this square root thats reseda
less than 1 and for Zeta greater than
one
the two routes of course will be real
part so let's examine this for the case
where
data is less than 1 and
what that corresponds to then are to
polls in the complex
plane and they have
a real part and an imaginary part
and you can exploit this is somewhat
more detail on your own
but essentially what happens is that as
you keep the parameter
Omega stuff and fixed and very
data these polls trace out
a circle and for example
with say to equal to 0 the polls
are on the jail may access at Omega
Sapan
for as as say to
because once as a day
increases and gets closer to one
these the polls converge toward the real
axis
and any particular for
say to greater than one what we end up
with
are to polls on the real axis
well actually the case that we want to
look at
a little more carefully is when the
polls are complex
and what this becomes is a second-order
system which has we'll see
as the discussion goes on as an impulse
response which
oscillates with time correspondingly a
frequency response
that has a residence well let's examine
the frequency response little more
carefully
and 1 I'm assuming in the discussion is
that first of all
the polls are in the left half plane
corresponding
to they don't make this a ban being
positive
and so this is minus that is negative
and furthermore I'm assuming that the
polls are complex
and in that case the algebraic
expression
for the system function is omega cement
squared in the numerator and two poles
in the denominator which a complex
conjugates
now what we want to look at is
the frequency response the system
and that corresponds to looking at
the 4e a transformer the impulse
response
which is the a-plus transform on the
jail making access
so we want to examine what HSC is as we
move
along the jail make axes and notice that
to do that
in this algebraic expression
we want to set s equal to jail maker and
then
evaluate for example we want to look at
the magnet to the frequency response
evaluate the magnet to of the complex
number
well there's a very convenient way of
doing that geometrically
by recognizing dead in the complex plane
this complex number minus back complex
number represents a vector
and essentially to look at the magnitude
of this complex number
corresponds to taking omega Steuben
squared and dividing it
by the product all the links of these
factors
so let's look for example at the vector
ass minus C-one
where s is on the Chi Omega axis
and doing that here is
the vector C-one
and here is the vector ass which is jail
make if we're looking let's say at this
bad you frequency
and this specter than is the vector
which he is J Omega minus C-one
so in fact it's the link that this
vector
that we want to observed as we change
Omega namely as we move along the Chi
Omega axis
you want to take this specter and this
specter
take the lights at those factors
multiply them together
divide that it will make its offense
where'd and that will give us
the frequency response that's little
heart
to see at a frequency response will work
out just looking at one point although
notice that as we move along the jail
make axes
as we get closer to this poll this
vector in fact gets shorter
at so we might expect that
the frequency response as a moving along
the Chi Omega axis in the vicinity is
that poll
would start to pee well I think that all
of this
is much better seen dynamically on the
computer display
so let's go to the computer display and
what we look at
is a second-order system the frequency
response a bit as we move
along jail make acts
so here we see the poll pair in the
complex plane
and to generate the frequency response
we want to look at the behavior of the
poll vectors as we move vertically
along the chair make axis so we'll
show the poll vectors and let's begin
at Omega equal 0 so here we have the
poll vectors from the polls to the point
Omega equal to 0 and as we move
vertically along the jail make axis will
see how the those poll vectors
change in length the magnitude of the
frequency response is the reciprocal
the product are the lights are those
factors
shown below is the frequency response
where we've begun just that'll make
equal to 0
and as we move vertically
along the jail make axis and the poll
vector last change
that will then influence what the
frequency response looks like we've
started here too move a little bit
away from Omega equal to 0 and
notice that in the upper half plane the
poll vector has gotten shorter
the poll vector for the pole in the
lower half plane has gotten longer
and now as omega increases further
that process will continue and in
particular
the poll vector associated with the poll
in the upper half plane
will be as short as in the vicinity
are in a freak at a frequency in the
vicinity of that poll
and so for that frequency than the
frequency response will P
and we see that here
from this point as the frequency
increases
corresponding to moving further
vertically along the chair maker axes
both poll vectors will increase in
laying
and that means then dead the magnet to
the frequency response will decrease for
this specific example
the magnitude of the frequency response
will
asymptotically go to zero
so what we see here is there the
frequency response has a resonance
and as we see geometrically from the way
defectors behave their residence in
frequency
is very clearly associated with the
position at the polls
and so in fact illustrate that further
and
dramatize it as long as we're focused on
it let's now
look at the frequency response for the
second order example
as we change the pole positions and
first what we'll do
is let the polls move vertically
parallel to the Chi Omega axes and see
how the frequency
response changes and then we'll have the
polls move
horizontally parallel to the relaxes and
see how the frequency response changes
to display the behavior the frequency
response is the polls move we've
change the vertical scale on
the frequency response somewhat and
now what we want to do is move the polls
first parallel to the jail make axis and
then
parallel to the real axis here we see
the
effect moving the polls parallel to the
jail may axis
and what we observe is that in fact the
frequency
location the residence shifts basically
tracking
the location at the pole
if we now move the poll back
down closer to the real axis then
this residents will shift back toward
its original location
and so let's now see that
and here we are back at the frequency
that we started at
now will move the polls even closer to
the real axis
the frequency location at the residence
will continue to shift toward lower
frequencies
and also in the process incidently
the height ove the resonant peak will
increase
because of course the lengths love
the poll factors are getting shorter
and so we see now the residence shifting
down toward lower and lower frequency
and finally what
will now do is move the polls back to
their
original position and the resonant peak
will
of course shift back up and
correspondingly
the height or amplitude the residence
will decrease and now we're back at the
frequency response that
we head generated previously next we'd
like to look at the behavior as the
polls
move parallel to the real axis first
closer to the J Omega axis and then
further away
as they move closer to the jail make
access
the residence sharpens because of the
fact
that the poll factor get shorter and
responds
or changes in like more quickly as we
move past it
moving along the jail make axis so
here we see the effect a move in the
polls closer to the jail make axis
the residence has gotten narrower in
frequency
and higher in amplitude associated with
the fact that the poll vector get
shorter
next
as we move back to the original location
the residents will broaden once again
and the airport to
will decrease
and then if we continue to move the
polls even further away
from the real axis the residents will
broaden
even further and the ample to the peak
will
become even smaller and finally
let's now just move the polls back to
their original position and we'll see
the Reds residence narrow again and
become higher
and so what we see then is that for
a second-order system the behavior above
the residents basically is associated
with the Polo cations the frequency the
residence associated with the vertical
position in the polls
and the sharpness at the residence
Associated with the real party polls in
other words there
position closer or further away from the
J Omega axis okay so
for complex polls then into the second
order
system what we see is that we get
a resident kind of behavior and
in particular then that resident
behavior
tens to peak or get pic year
as the value of data gets smaller
and here just to remind you what you saw
here is the frequency response with
one particular choices values well this
is normalized to make a span is one one
particular choice for Zeta
family .4 here is
what we have with say to smaller
and finally here is example
where say that has gotten even smaller
than that and what that corresponds to
is the polls moving closer to the jail
make axes
the corresponding frequency response
getting PQ
now in the
time-domain what happens is that
we have of course these complex roots
which I indicated previously where
this represents the imaginary part
because data is less than one
and in the time domain we will have
a form for the behavior which is a
e2 the C-one TV plus a conjugate
eat so the C-one conjugate
see and so
in fact as the polls get closer to the
jail make axis cars fine to use a to
getting smaller
as the polls get closer to
the chair maker axis in the frequency
domain
the residences get sharper in the time
the real part all the polls has gotten
smaller
and that means in fact that in the time
domain
behavior will be more oscillatory and
less than
and so just looking at that again
here is in the time domain
what happens first IPL with
and the parameter say to equal to
.4 and isolates an exponentially
dies out year
is the second-order system
where data is now point to is that a
point for
and finally the second-order system
wears a to is .1
and what we see as say to get smaller
and smaller
is dead the oscillations are basically
the same but
the exponential damping becomes
less and less right now
this is a somewhat more detailed look at
second-order systems
and second or two systems and for that
matter first order systems are
systems that are important in their own
right but
they also are important as basic
building blocks
for more general in particular for
higher-order systems
and the way in which that stone
typically
is by combining first- and second-order
systems together
in such a way that they implement
higher-order systems
and two very common connections are
connections which are cascade
connections
and connections which are parallel
connections in a cascade connection
we would think love combining this
system
systems individual systems together as i
indicated herein series
and of course from the convolution
property the overall system function
is the product of the individual system
functions
so for example if these were all
second-order systems and I A combined
and have them together in cascade
the overall system would be a system
that would have
2n polls in other words it would be a 2n
order system
that's one very common kind of
connection another
very common kind of connection for
first- and second-order systems
is a parallel connection where in that
case
we connect the systems together as they
indicate here
the overall system function is just
simply the sum of these and that follows
from the linearity property
and so the overall system function would
be as i indicate
algebraically here and notice that
if each of these are second-order
systems
and I had capital and have them in
parallel
when you think a putting the overall
system function over one common
denominator
that common denominator in general is
going to be
all order to an so either
the parallel connection or the Cascade
connection
can be used to implement higher-order
systems
one very common context in which
second-order systems
are combined together either in parallel
or in cascade to form a
more interesting system is in fact
in speech synthesis and what I'd like to
do is
demonstrate a speech synthesizer which I
have here
which in fact is a parallel
combination 04 second-order
systems very much are the type that
we've just talked about
all returned to the synthesizer in a
minute let me
first just indicate with the basic idea
is in speech synthesis
of course what we're trying to represent
a reply man is something dead
corresponds to the vocal tract
the vocal tract is characterized by said
residences
and we can think of representing you to
those residences by a second-order
system
and then the higher-order system
corresponding to the vocal tract
is built by in this case a parallel
combination
the second-order systems and so
for the synthesizer what we have
connected together
in parallel is 4
second-order systems and
a control on each one of them that
controls the center frequency
or the resonant frequency love each oath
the second-order systems
the exhortation is an exhortation
that would represent the airflow through
the vocal cords
the vocal cords vibrate and their pop
severe
through the vocal cords as they open and
close it so the exhortation
for the synthesizer corresponds to
a pulse train representing
the airflow through the vocal cords the
fundamental frequency if this
representing the fundamental frequency
love
the synthesized voice so that's the
basic
structure the synthesizer and what we
have in this
analog synthesizer are separate controls
on the individual center frequencies
their is a control representing the
center frequency of the third resonator
and the fourth resonator and those are
represented by these two knobs
and then the first and second resonators
are controlled by moving this joystick
the first resonator
by moving the joystick along this axis
and the second resonator by moving the
joystick along this axis
and then in addition to controls on
the for resonators we can control
the fundamental frequency the
exhortation and we do that
with this not so let's first of all just
listen
to wanted the resonators and the
resonator that
I'll play is the fourth resonator and
what you'll hear first is the output as
a very
the center frequency of that resonator
stonewalling
share
and then free she's acts
and then as I A indicated I can also
control the fundamental frequency the
exhortation
by turning this knob Ste
slowing the fundamentals she K
he
all right now if the four resonators in
parallel
are and implementation love the vocal
cavity
then presumably we can synthesize when
we put them all in
are Val sounds and let's do that
on now switch in the other resonators
when we do that then
depending on
what choice we have to the individual
resonant frequencies
we should be able to synthesize balanced
sound so here for example is the Val
E Ste here's
of
act and
course we can
generate
lots of other Val sounds
and change the fundamental frequency
same time
now if we want to synthesize speech
it's not enough to just synthesized
steady-state Balzac its
boring after a while course what happens
with
the vocal cavity is that it moves as a
function of time
and that's what generates the the
speech that we want to generate and so
presumably man if we change these
resonant frequencies as a function of
time appropriately
then we should be able to synthesize
speech and so by
moving these residences around weekend
generate
synthesized speech and can let's try it
a with some phrases and I'll do that
by simply adjusting the center
frequencies appropriately
now
well hopefully you
understood that is you can imagine I
spend at least a few minutes before
the lecture try to practice that's so
that it would come out
to be more less intelligible now
the system as i've just demonstrated is
of course a continuous-time system or an
analyte speech synthesizer
their are many versions of
digital or discrete-time synthesizers
one of the first in fact
being a device that many view
are very likely familiar with which is
the Texas Instruments speak n spell
which
I show here and what's
very interesting and rather dramatic
about this device
is the fact that it implements the
speech synthesis in very much the same
way as
I've demonstrated with the analog
synthesizer
in this case it's five second-order
filters
in a configuration that slightly
different than a parallel configuration
but conceptually
very closely related and let's take a
look
inside the box and what we see their
with a slide that was kindly supplied by
Texas Instruments
is the fact that there really are only
four chips in the air
a controller chips and storage and the
important point is the chip that's
labeled
as the speech synthesis chip in fact
is what embodies our implements the five
second order filters and in addition
incorporate some other things a memory
and also the
D-day converters so in fact the
implementation and the synthesizer is
pretty much done on a single chip
well that's a discrete-time
system we've been talking for the last
several lectures about continuous-time
systems and no fuss transform
hopefully what you've seen in this
lecture in the previous lecture
is the powerful tool
dead the a poss transform affords us
in analyzing and understanding
system behavior in the next lecture
what I'd like to do is parallel the
discussion
for discrete-time turn our attention to
busy transform
and as you can imagine simply by virtue
of the fact that
we I've kinda shown you a digital and
analog
version a very much the same kind of
system the discussions
how all themselves very strongly and
dizzy transform
will play very much the same role in
discrete-time that
the apostrophe is formed dozen continues
thank you