the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU ha the
the
the in
the new the in the last lecture we
discussed discrete-time processing of
continuous-time signals
and as you know the basis for that
arises essentially out at the sampling
there now in that context and also in
its own right
another important sampling issue is
the sampling love discrete-time signals
in other words the sampling a sequence
one comic context in which this arises
for example
is if we've converted from a
continuous-time signal
to a sequence and we then
carry out some additional filtering then
there's the possibility
day we can re sable that sequence and as
we'll see as we go through the
discussion
save something in the way of storage or
whatever
so discrete-time sampling
as a indicated has important application
in a context referred to here namely re
sampling
after discrete-time filtering and
closely related to that as well indicate
in this lecture
is the concept love using discrete time
sampling
for what's referred to as sampling rate
conversion and also closely
associated with both those ideas is a
set of ideas that I'll bring up in
today's lecture referred to as
decimation and interpolation love
discrete-time signals are sequences
now the basic process for
discrete-time sampling is the same as it
is for continuous-time sampling
namely we can analyze it and set it up
on the basis love multiplying or
modulating
a discrete-time signal by an impulse
train
the impulse train essentially or pulse
train pulling out
sequence values at the times that we
want to sample
so the basic block diagram for the
sampling process
is to modulator multiply
the sequence that we want to sample by
an impulse train and here
near Paul strain has imposed a space by
integer multiples of capital N this then
becomes the sampling period
and the result is that modulation is
then
the sample sequence X appear vent so
if we just look at what a sequence in a
sample version of that sequence might
look like
well we have here is an original
sequence exit Van
and then we have the
sampling imposed strain or sampling
sequence
and it's the modulation or product if
these two
that gives us the sample sequence X
appear van
and so as you can see multiplying this
by this
essentially pulls out love the original
sequence
sample values at the times that this
post rain is on
and of course here I've drawn as for the
case where capital and
the sampling period is equal to 3
now the
analysis love discrete-time sampling is
very similar to the analysis of
continuous-time sampling
and let's just quickly look through the
steps that are involved where
modulating are multiplying in the time
domain and what that corresponds to
in the frequency domain is a convolution
and
so be spectrum
love the sample sequence
is the periodic convolution love the
spectrum
love the sampling sequence and
the spectrum love the sequence that were
sampling
and since the sampling sequences in
Nepal strain
as we know the 48 transform over Nepal
strain
is itself an impulse train and so this
is the Fourier transform
love the sampling sequence
and now finally the four EA transform
love the resulting sample sequence being
the convolution
love this with the Fourier transform the
sequence that were sampling
gives us then spectrum which consists of
a some
love replicated versions of the Fourier
transform above the sequence that were
sampling
in other words what we're doing very
much as we did in continuous-time
is through the sampling process when we
look at it in the frequency domain
taking the spectrum all the sequester
were sampling
and shifting it and then adding it in
shifting it by editor multiples of the
sampling frequency
in particular looking back at this
equation
what we recognize is that this term
k times to pile over capital and is in
fact
integer multiple love the sampling
frequency
and the same thing is true here this
is K times Omega so badass
where Omega so badass the sampling
frequency
is to pie divided by capital and
alright so now let's look at what this
means
pictorially are graphically in the
frequency domain
and as you can imagine since the
analysis
and algebra is similar to what happens
in continuous-time
we would expect the pictures to more or
less be identical to
what we've seen previously for
continuous-time and indeed that's the
case
so here we have the
spectrum love the signal that were
sampling
this is for EA transform with an assumed
highest frequency of Omega Savannah M
highest frequency over to fire a range
or over Ranger
higher at their and now the spectrum of
the
sampling signal is
what I show below which is an impulse
train
with impulses occurring at multiples
integer multiples of the sampling
frequency
and fan finally the convolution
up these two is simply this: one
replicated at the locations if these
impulses
and so that's finally what I show below
and here are chosen one I've made one
particular choice
for the sampling period this in
particular corresponds to
a sampling period which is
capitol lawn equal to
three and so the sampling frequency
Omega so badass is to pie
divided by three
right now when we look at this what we
recognize
is dead we have basically the same issue
here
as we had in continuous time in the
sense that
when these individual replications of
the 48 transform
when a fit when the sampling frequency
is chosen high enough so that they don't
overlap
than we see the potential for being able
to get one of them back
on the other hand when they do overlap
then what will have
is a daily as saying in particular
discrete-time aliasing
much as we had continuous time a leasing
in the continuous-time case
well notice in this picture dead
what we have is we've chosen this
pictures so that
Omega sieve ass minus Omega 7 a.m.
is greater than Omega Savannah am work
with alertly so that Omega Sebastian is
greater than
to Omega to Omega
so am and so with Omega serve as greater
than 20 may get to them that corresponds
to this picture
whereas if that condition is violated
than in fact the picture that we would
have
is a picture that looks like this and in
this picture
the individual replications of the four
EA transform
of the original signal overlap and we
can no longer
recover the for EA transform the
original signal
and this just as it was in
continuous-time
is referred to as alias
now let's look more closely at the
situation in which there is no aliasing
and so in that case
what we have is a Fourier transform
for the sampled
signal which is as i indicated here
and the Fourier transform for the
original signal
as i indicated at the top and
the question now is how do we recover
this one from this one
well the way that we do that just as we
did in a continuous-time case
is by low-pass filtering in particular
processing in the time domain or in the
frequency domain
this where and idea low-pass filter
has the effect of extracting that part
the spectrum dead in fact we identify
with the original signal that we
began so
what we see it again is that the process
is very much the same as long as there's
no aliasing
we can recover the original signal by
ideal low-pass filtering so
the overall system is
just to reiterate a system which
consists love modulating
the original sequence with
appall strainer and Paul strain
and then that is going to be processed
with a low-pass filter
the spectrum love the original signal X
a van
is what I show here the spectrum of the
sampled signal where I'm drawing the
picture on the assumption that the
sampling period is 3
is now what's indicated where these are
replicated
where the original spectrum is
this is now processed through a filter
which for exact reconstruction
is an ideal low-pass filter
and so we would multiply this spectrum
by this one
and the result after doing that will
generate
a reconstructed spectrum which in fact
is identical
to the original so the time domain
picture is the same I'm sorry the
frequency domain pictures the same
and what we would expect and is that the
time to me
picture would be the same well lets in
fact look at the time domain
and in the time domain what we have
is an analysis more less identical to
what we had in continuous-time
we've course have the same system
and in the time domain we r multiplying
by an impulse train consequently
the sample sequence is
and impose train whose values are
samples affects a van at integer
multiples of capital and
for the reconstruction this is
now process through idea low-pass filter
and that implements the convolution in
the time domain
and so the reconstructed signal is the
convolution
of the sample sequence and
the filter impulse response and
expressed another way namely writing at
the convolution is
some we have this expression and so it
says then
that the reconstruction is carried out
by replacing the impulses here
these impulses by versions of the
filter impulse response
well if the filter is an ideal 0 pass
filter
then that corresponds in the time domain
to assign an ex
over sin x kinda function and that is
the interpolation
in between the samples to do the
reconstruction
also as is discussed some white in the
text we can
consider other kinds of interpolation
for example
discrete-time zero-order hold or
discreet I first-order whole just as we
had in continuous-time
and the issues and analysis for the
discrete-time zero-order hold the
first-order hold
are very similar to what they were in
continuous-time the zero-order hold
just simply holding the value until the
next sampling instant
and the first-order hold carrying out
linear interpolation
in between the samples
now in this sampling process
if we look again at the way forms
involved
or sequences involved the process
consisted
love taking a sequence
and extracting from it
individual bad news and
in between those values we have
sequenced values equal to 0
so what we're doing in this case
is retaining
the same number sequence values and
simply setting
some number of them equal to 0
well let's say for example that we want
to carry out
sampling and what we're talking about is
sequence and let's say the sequence
stored in a computer memory
as you can imagine the notion love
sampling it
and actually replacing some with the
values by zero
is somewhat inefficient namely it
doesn't make sense to think of storing
the memory a lot of zeros
when in fact those zeros that we can
always put back in
we know exactly with the values are and
if we know what the sampling
rate was in discrete-time then we would
know
when and how to put the zeros back in
so actually in discrete-time sampling
what we've talked about so far is really
only one
part for one step in the process
basically the other
step is to take those zeros just throw
them away because
we can put them in any time we want to
and really only retained for example
in our computer memory or less than
sequence values or whatever
only retain the non-zero values
so that process and the resulting
sequence that we end up with
is associated with a concept called
estimation
what I mean by destination is very
simple
what we're doing is instead of working
with
this sequence we're going to work with
this sequence
namely well toss out zeros
in between here and collapse the
sequence
down only to the sequence values
that are associated with the original X
event
now in talking about a decimated
sequence
we could of course do that directly from
misstep down to hear
although again in the analysis it will
be somewhat
more convenient to carry that out by
thinking at least analytically interns
with two step process
one being a sampling process then the
other being
the destination but basically this is
decimated version %uh that now
for the grammatical purists out there
the word estimation of course means
taking every 10 won the implication is
not dead
were always sampling with a period of 10
the idea decimating
is to pick out every and sample and end
up with a collapsed sequence
right now let's now look at a little bit
in the analysis
and understand what the consequences in
the frequency domain
in particular what we want to develop is
how the Fourier transform the decimated
sequence
is related to the Fourier transform
of the original sequence or the sample
sequence
so let's look at this in the frequency
domain
and so what we have is a
decimated sequence which consists
love pulling out every capital and bad
you affect the van
and of course that's in the same as we
can either decimate x7
or we can decimate the sample sick
now in going through this analysis
all kinda go through it quickly because
again
there's the issue with some slight
mental gymnastics and if
you're anything like I am it's usually
best to kinda try to absorb at
by yourself quietly rather than having
somebody throw it at you
let let me say though that that the
steps that are following here are
slightly different
and the steps that I use in the tax is
slightly different wave
I'll going through the analysis I guess
you could say for one thing that
if we go through it twice and it comes
out the same well of course it has to be
right
well anyway a here we have
then the relationship between the
decimated sequence
the original sequence and the
sample sequence and we know of course
that
the Fourier transform love the sample
sequence
is just simply this nation and now
the kinda the idea in the analysis is
that we can collapse this summation
by recognizing bat this
term is only non-zero
at every and value and so if we do that
essentially making a substitution
variables with an equal to small and
times capital and
we can turn this into a summation on am
and that's what I've done here and
we've just simply use the fact that we
can collapse the some
because the fact is dead that all but
every and values equal to 0
so this then is the Fourier transform
all the sample
signal and now if we look at the Fourier
transform of the
decimated signal that for EA transform
of course is this summation
on the decimated sequence
well what we want to look at is a
correspondence between this equation and
the one above it
so we want to compare this equation to
this one
and recognizing that this decimated
sequences just simply
related to the sample sequence this way
these two become equal under
a substitution variables in particular
notice
that if we replace in
this equation Omega by
Omega times capital and and these two
equations become equal
so the consequences that then what it
all boils down to and says
is that the relationship between the
decimated the Fourier transform the
decimated sequence
and the Fourier transform the sample
sequence is simply
a frequency scaling corresponding
to dividing the frequency axis by
capital and
so thats essentially what happens that's
really all
that's involved in the destination
process and now
again let's look at that pictorially and
see what it means
so what we want to look at now that
we've looked in the time domain
in this particular you graph we
now wanna look in the frequency-domain
and in the frequency domain we have
again the
Fourier transform of the original
sequence
and we have the Fourier transform
or the sample sequence
and now the 48 transform of the
decimated sequence is simply this
spectrum with a linear frequency scaling
and in particular it's simply car
sponsor multiplying this frequency axis
by capital and
and notice noticed that this frequency
now
to pry or capital and that frequency
ends up getting rescaled
to a frequency love to pie
so in fact now in the rescaling
its at this point in the decimation
gets rescaled to this point
and correspondingly of course the sole
spectrum
broadens out now we can also look at
that
in the context of the original spectrum
and you can see that the relationship
between the original spectrum and the
spectrum the decimated signal
corresponds to simply linearly scaling
yes but it's important also
to keep in mind dead that analysis
that particular relationship assumes
that we've avoided aliasing
the relationship between the specter the
decimated signal
and the spectra the sample signal is
true whether or not we have a leasing
but being able to clearly associated
with
just simply scaling love this spectrum
the original signal assumes that the
spectrum
the original signal shape the shape of
it is preserved
when we generate the sample sick
okay well when my eight discrete-time
sampling and for that matter decimation
the use well i indicated one context in
which it might be useful
at the beginning at this lecture and let
me now focusing on that
a little more specifically
in particular suppose that we have
going through a process
in which the a continuous-time signal
has been converted to a discrete-time
signal
and we then carry out some additional
discrete-time
filtering so we have a situation where
we've gone through a continuous to
discrete-time conversion
and after that conversion we carry out
some discrete-time
filtering and so
and in particular and going through this
part of the process
we choose the sampling rate for
going from the continuous-time signal to
the sequence
so that we don't violate the sampling
there
well let's suppose then that this is the
spectrum
love the continuous time signal
below it we have the spectrum love
the output of the continuous and
discrete-time conversion
and I've chosen the sampling frequency
to be just high end of so that I avoid
aliasing
okay well
that then is the the lower sampling
frequency I can pick
but now if we go through some additional
ok pass filtering
then let's see what happens if I now
low-pass filter the sequence XFN then
in effect on multiplying the sequence
spectrum by this filter
and so the result of that the product
though the filter frequency response
and the Fourier transform exit then
would have a shape
somewhat like I indicate below
now notice that in this spectrum
although in this the input to the filter
this entire band was filled up
in the output the filter there is a band
that is in fact up zero a that has zero
energy and
so what I can consider doing is
taking the output sequence from the
filter
and in fact we see a planet in other
words
sampling it which would be more less
associated with a different sampling
rate
in the for the continuous-time signals
involved
so I could now go through a process
which is commonly referred to as down
sampling that is
lowering the sampling rate when we do
that of course what's going to happen
is that in fact this spectral energy
will now
fill out more love the band and
for example if I if this was the third
then
in fact if I down sampled by a factor of
three then
I would fill up the entire band with
this energy but since I've done some
additional 0 pass filtering as i
indicate here
there's no problem with aliasing if
I had let's say down sample by a factor
of three and I'm now taking that signal
and can bring it back to a
continuous-time signal
then course the way I can't do that is
by simply running
my output clock for the discrete to
continuous-time converter
I can run my app but clock at a third
the rate
love the input clock and that in effect
takes care the bookkeeping for me
okay so here we have now
the notion love sampling a sequence
and very closely tied in with that the
notion of decimating a sequence
and related to both of those the notion
love
down sampling that is changing the
sampling
rate so that if we were tying this in
with continuous-time signals
we've essentially changed our clock
grade
and we might also want to and it's
important to
considered the opposite of that so
now a question is what's an opposite
what's the opposite destination suppose
that we had a sequence
we decimated thinking about it as a
two-step process
that would correspond to first
multiplying by an impulse train where
there are bunches zeros
in the air and then choosing throwing
away the zeros in keeping only the
values that
are 90 because the zeros we can always
recreate
well in fact the inverse process is very
specifically a process
love recreating the zeros and then
doing that the sampling so in
the opposite operation
what we would do is undue
the decimation step and
that would consist of converting the
decimated sequence
back to an impulse train
and then processing that imposed strain
by ideal low-pass filter
to do the interpolation or
reconstruction
filling in the values which in this
imposed strain
are equal to 0 so
we now have the two steps we take the
decimated sequence
we expanded out putting in 000's
and then we the sample that by
processing it
through a low-pass filter so just
have looking at sequences again
what we have is an original
sequence the secret sex if an and
then the sample sequence is simply a
sequence
which alternates in this particular case
those sequence values 0
here what we're seeing is that the
sampling rate is that that the sampling
period is 2
and so every other value here is equal
to 0
the decimated sequence then is this
sequence
collapsed as a show in the sequence
above
and so it's in effect I'm compressing
the sample sequence or the original
sequence
so that we throw out the sequence value
Z
which were equal to 0 in the sample
sequence
now in recovering the original sequence
from the decimated sequence
we can think up a two-step process
namely
we spread this out
alternating with zeros and again keeping
in mind that this is drawn for the case
where capitalists to
and then finally we interpolate between
the non-zero values here by going
through
a low-pass filter to reconstruct the
original sequence and that's what we
show
finally on the bottom curve so
that's what we would see in the time
domain let's
look at what we would see in the
frequency domain
in the frequency domain we have to begin
with
the sequence on the bottom or the
spectrum on the bottom
which would correspond to the original
spectrum
then through the sampling process that
is periodically replicated
again this is drawn on the assumption
that the
sampling frequency is pie or the
sampling period is equal to 2
and so this is now replicated and
then in going from this to the
spectrum love the decimated sequence
we would rescale the frequency axis
so that the frequency hi now gets
rescaled
in the spectrum for the decimated
sequence
to a frequency which is to pie and so
this now is the spectrum
love the decimated sequence if we now
want to re convert to the original
sequence we would first interspersed in
the time domain with zeros
corresponding to compressing in the
frequency domain
that this would then be low-pass
filtered
and the low-pass filtering would consist
love throwing away this replication
accounting for
a factor which is the factor capital and
and
extracting the portion of the spectrum
which is associated
with the spectrum love
the original signal which we began with
so
once again you can we have decimation
and interpolation
and the decimation can be thought I love
as a time compression corresponds to
frequency expansion and and the
interpolation
process is then just the reverse
now there are lot to situations in which
decimation and interpolation
and discrete-time sampling are useful
and
one context that I just want to quickly
draw your attention to
is the use the decimation and
interpolation in
what is commonly referred to as sampling
rate conversion
what the basic issue in sampling rate
conversion is is that
in some situations in a very common one
is
digital audio continuous-time signals
sample
and those sample values are stored or
whatever
and kinda the notion is that that
perhaps when that is played back
its playback through a different system
and a different system has
a different assumed sampling frequency
your sampling period
so that's kind of the issue in the idea
we have but say a continuous-time signal
which we've converted to a sequence
through a sampling process
using innocent sampling period if t1
and the sequence values made in for
example
be put into digital storage in the case
have a digital audio system it may for
example go on to a digital record
in and it might be the output of this
that we want
to recreate or we might in fact
follow that with some additional
processing
whatever that additional processing is
an all kinda put a
question mark in there because we don't
know exactly what that might be
and then in any case the result is that
is going to be converted back to
a continuous-time signal but
it might be converted through a system
that has a different assumed
sampling period and so
a very common issue and it comes up as i
indicated particularly in digital audio
a very common issue is to be able to
convert
from wanna soon sampling period
t1r sampling frequency to
another soon sampling period now
how would we do that well in fact we do
that by using
the ideas of decimation and
interpolation
in particular if we had for example
the situation where we wanted to convert
from
sampling period t+1 to sampling period
which was twice as long as they're at
then
essentially we got we're going to take
the sequence
and process it in a way
that would in effect correspond to
assuming that we had sample
at half the original frequency well how
do we do that the way we do it
is we take the sequence we have we just
throw away every other bad
so in that case we would then for this
sampling rate conversion
down sample an decime or
actually we might not go through this
step formally we might just simply
destiny
now we might have an alternative
situation
where in fact the new sampling period
sampling purity at put is
half the sampling period the input
corresponding
to soon sampling frequency which is
twice as high
and in that case then that we would go
through a process of interpolation and
in particular we were
up sample and interpolate by a factor of
two to one
so in one case were simply throwing away
every other value in the other case what
we're going to do is take our sequence
putting zeros put it through a low-pass
filter to interpolate
now like would be simple if everything
happen in simple integer amounts like
that
more common situation is that we may
have
and assumed output sampling period
which is three heads above the input
sampling period
and now the question is what are we
going to do to convert from this
sampling period
to this sampling period well
in fact the answer to that is to use a
combination
all down sampling and up sampling or up
sampling and down sampling
covertly interpolation decimation
and for this particular case in fact
what we would do
is to first take the data
up sample by a factor of two
and then down sample the result of that
by a factor of three and what that would
give us
is a sampling rate conversion overall
love three hands or sampling period
conversion three here's
and more generally what you could think
of is how you might do this
if in general the relationship between
the
input and output sampling periods with
some rational number:
P over Q and so in fact in many
systems and hardware systems related to
digital audio
very often the sampling rate conversion
most typically the same thing rate
conversion is done
through apostle process up sampling or
interpolating
and then down sampling by some other now
right now what we've seen we've talked
about in
in a set of lectures is
the concepts love sampling a signal
and what we've seen is that the signal
can be represented by samples under
certain conditions
and the sampling that we've been talking
about is sampling
in the time domain we've done that for
continuous-time
we've done it for discrete-time
now we know that their is some type a
duality
both continuous-time and discrete-time
some type a duality
between the time-domain and
frequency-domain and so is you can
imagine
we can also talk about sampling
in the frequency domain and expected
more or less the kinda properties and
analysis
will be similar to those related to
sampling in the time domain
well i wanna talk just briefly about
that
and leave the more detailed discussion
to the text and video course manual
but let me indicate for example one
context in which
frequency-domain sampling is important
suppose that
you have signal and what you'd like to
measure is it's for a a transformer
spectra
well course if you want to measure it
are calculated
you can never do that exactly and every
single frequency there too many
frequencies namely an infinite number of
them
and so in fact all that you can really
calculator measure
are is the 48 transform data set
love sample frequency so essentially
if you are going to look at a spectrum
continuous-time and discrete-time you
can only really look at samples
and a reasonable question to ask Dan is
when does a set of samples in fact
tell you everything that there is to
know about
the Fourier transform thats that
in the answer to that is very closely
related to the concept
a frequency-domain sample
well frequency-domain sampling just to
kinda introduce
the topic car spines
and can be analyzed interns love
doing modulation in the frequency domain
very much like the modulation that we
carried out in the time domain for
time-domain sampling
and so we would multiply the Fourier
transform
love the signal was for
spectrum is to be sampled by
an impulse train in frequency and so
shown below is what might be a
representative
spectrum for the input signal
and the spectrum then for the
signal associated with the
frequency-domain sampling
consists love multiplying the
frequency-domain
by this impulse train or correspondingly
the for EA transform love
the resulting signal is an impulse train
in frequency with an envelope
which is the original spectrum that we
were
sampling well this of course is what we
would do
in the frequency domain its modulation
by Nepal strain
what does this mean in the time domain
well let's see multiplication in the
time domain is convolution in the
frequency domain
convolution the frequency domain is
multiplication
I'm sorry multiplication the frequency
domain and is
convolution the time to me and in fact
the process in the time domain is a
convolution process
namely the time domain signal is
replicated and
time an integer amounts love a
particular time associated with the
spacing in frequency
under which we doing the
frequency-domain sampling
so in fact if we look at this
in the time domain
the resulting picture corresponds to
an original signal whose spectrum or
Fourier transform we've sampled
and a consequence if the sampling is
dead
The Associated time domain signal
is just like the original signal but
periodically replicated in time now not
frequency but in time
at integer multiples up to par I divided
by
the spectral sampling interval Omega 0
and so this then is the time function
associated with
the sample frequency function now
that's not surprising because what we've
done is generated
a and impose train and frequency with a
certain on below
we know that the important post Raina
frequencies the Fourier transform
love a periodic time function and so in
fact we have a periodic time function
we also know that the envelope all those
impulses we
we know this from way back with when we
talked about for you transforms
the envelope in fact is the Fourier
transform one period
and so all of this of course fits
together as it should in a consistent
way
now given dead we have
is periodic time function whose Fourier
transform is
the samples in the frequency domain how
do we get back
the original time function well
with time-domain sampling what we did
was to multiplying the frequency-domain
by agape or window to extract that part
of the spectrum
what we do here is exactly the same
thing
namely multiply in the time domain by
a time window which extracts just one
period
his periodic signal which with then give
us back
the original signal that we started with
now also let's keep in mind going back
to this spectrum and the related sorry
this time function in the relationship
between them
that again there is the potential if
this time function is too long
in relation to 2pi divided by Omega 0
there's the potential for these two
overlap and so
what this means is that in fact what we
can end up with
if the sample spacing a frequency is not
small enough
well we can end up with isn't overlap in
the replication
in the time domain and what that
corresponds to an what's called
is in fact time a lease so
we can apply merely saying with
frequency-domain sampling just as we can
have
frequency alias saying with time to meet
Sam
finally let me just indicate very
quickly that
although we're not going through this in
any detail
the same basic idea applies in
discrete-time
namely if we have a discrete-time signal
and if the discrete-time signal
is a finite length if we sample
its forty-eight transform the
the type function associated with those
samples
is a periodic replication
and we can now extract from
this periodic signal the original signal
by multiplying by an appropriate time
window
the product if that giving us the
reconstructed time
function as I indicate below
so we've now seen a little bit love the
notion of frequency-domain sampling as
well as
time-domain sampling and let me stress
that although
I haven't gone into this and a lot of
detail its
important it's used very often its
naturally important to understand it but
in fact
there is so much to ality between the
time-domain and frequency-domain
that a thorough understanding of
time-domain sampling just naturally
leads to
a thorough understanding a
frequency-domain sample
all right now we talk a lot about
sampling
and this now concludes our discussion
I stress many times in the lectures
associated with this
dead sampling is a very important topic
in the context of our whole discussion
in part because the poor for such an
important bridge between
continuous-time and discrete-time ideas
and your picture now she can to be a
global one
that sees how continuous-time and
discrete-time fit together
not just analytically but also
practically
beginning in the next lecture what I
will introduce
is the a-plus transform
and beyond that busy transform and what
those will correspond to
are generalizations are the Fourier
transform
so we now want to turn our attention
back to some analytical tools
in particular developing some
generalizations
love the Fourier transform in both
continuous-time and discrete-time
and what we'll see is those that those
generalizations
providers with considerably enhanced
flexibility
in dealing with and analyzing both
signals and linear time-invariant
systems
thank you