the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT ided you
ha
the norm
are
over the past several lectures we've
developed the representation for linear
time-invariant systems
in a particularly important center
systems
which are linear and time-invariant are
those that are represented by linear
constant coefficient differential
equations continuous-time
or when your constant coefficient
difference equations
in discrete-time for example electrical
circuits that are built let's say I dove
resistors inductors and capacitors
perhaps with %ah pants
correspond to systems described by
differential equations
mechanical systems with springs and dash
pots likewise
are described by differential equations
and in the discrete-time
case things such as moving average
filters
digital filters and most simple kinda
data smoothing
are all linear constant coefficient
difference equations
now presumably
in a previous course you've had some
exposure to
differential equations for
continuous-time and
their solution using notions like
particular solution and homogeneous
solution initial conditions center
later on in the course
when we've developed the concept to the
48 transforming after that the
apostrophe its form
will see some very efficient and useful
ways
generating solutions both differential
and difference equations
at this point however I'd like to
just introduce when your constant
coefficient
differential equations and the
discrete-time counterpart
and address among other things the issue
love when they do and don't correspond
to linear time-invariant systems
well let's first consider
what I refer to as an nth order
linear constant coefficients
differential equation as i've indicated
here
and what it consists of is a linear
combination of derivatives up the system
output
y'at equal to a linear combination
of derivatives above the system input
accept T
and is referred to
as a constant coefficients equation of
course because the
coefficients are constant in other words
not assume to be time-varying
and its referred to
as linear because it corresponds to a
linear combination
love these derivatives not because
it corresponds to a linear system and in
fact
as we'll see or as all indicate this
equation may or may not in fact
correspond to
when your system in the discrete-time
case
the corresponding equation is a linear
constant coefficient difference equation
and that corresponds to again
a linear combination love the late
versions of the output equal to
versions at the input
this equation is referred to as an nth
order
difference equation the N referring to
the number of the ladies
are the output involved just as an aunt
order differential equation
the N for the order the equation refers
to the number of derivatives
the output now let's first begin
with the near constant coefficient
differential equations
and the basic
point or the solution for
the differential equations is the fact
dead
if we've generated some solution
which I refer to here's why superiority
some solution
to the equation for a given input then
in fact we can and to that solution
any other solution which
satisfies what's referred to as
the homogeneous equation so in fact
this differential equation by itself
is not a unique specification
the system
if I have any solution then I can
and to that solution any other solution
which satisfies the homogeneous equation
and thus all those two
likewise be a solution and that's very
straight forward to verify
by simply substituting into the
differential equation
some love the particular a particular
and the homogeneous solution
and what you see is that the homogeneous
contribution
in fact goes to zero by definition
what we mean by the homogeneous equation
now
the homogeneous solution for a when your
constant coefficient differential
equation
is of the form that I
indicate at the bottom and
it typically consists love a
song or capital and complex exponentials
and the Constance
are on determined by the equation itself
and this form for the homogeneous
solution
in essence drops out love examining
the homogeneous equation where
if we assume that the former the
homogeneous solution
is a complex exponential with some
on specified amplitude and unspecified
exponent
if we substitute this into are
homogeneous equation
we end up with the equation that i've
indicated
year the factor A&E the st. can in fact
be
cancelled out and we find there that
equation
is satisfied
for capital N values
love s and
that's true no matter what choices made
for these
coefficients and the essential
consequence
have all of that is that the homogeneous
solution
is of the form that I indicated
previously
namely it consists love some
love capital and complex exponentials
where the coefficients the capital and
coefficients
attached to you to those complex
exponentials
is undetermined Iran specified
so what this says is that in order to
obtain the solution for a win here comes
the coefficient differential equation
we need some kind of auxiliary
information
tells us how to obtain these capital and
undetermined Constance and there are a
variety of ways
specifying this auxiliary information or
auxiliary conditions
for example in addition to the
differential equation
what I can tell you is the value
of the output and and -1 up there
and -1 if its derivatives at some
specified time t0 and
so the differential equations together
with the auxiliary information the
initial conditions
van lets you determine the total
solution
which namely lets you determine these
previously unspecified
coefficients in the homogeneous solution
now depending on how the auxiliary
information is stated or what auxiliary
information is available
the system a or may not correspond
to a linear system and may or may not
correspond to a linear time-invariant
system one essential condition
for it to correspond to a linear system
is that
the initial conditions must be zero
and one can see the reason for that
if we refer back to the previous lecture
in which we saw that for a linear system
if we put 0n we get zero out
so if exit see the input is zero the
output must be zero
and so that in essence tells us that at
least for the system to be linear
these initial conditions must be zero
now beyond that if
we want the system to be
causal and linear time in and
time-invariant
then what's required on the
initial conditions is that they be
consistent with
what's referred to as initial rest
initial arrest says
that the output must be
0 up until the time
that the input becomes 90 and we can see
of course that that's consistent with
the notion of causality as
we talked about in the previous lecture
and
its relatively straightforward to see
that if the system is causal and linear
and time-invariant
that will require
initial rest it's somewhat more
difficult see
that if we specify initial rest the NAT
in fact is sufficient to
determine that the system is both causal
in linear
and time very but the essential point
then is that
requires initial rest for both linearity
and causality okay well
let's look at an example and
let's take the example love a
first-order
differential equation as I've
indicated here so we have
a first-order differential equation the
wife TTT
was a yote is the input exit
T and let's first
look at what the homogeneous solution
this equation is
and so we can consider the homogeneous
equation
namely the equation specify solutions
which would correspond to zero input
we in essence guess for impose
a solution love the form the homogeneous
solution
is an amplitude factor times the complex
exponential
substituting this into the homogeneous
equation
we then get the equation that i've
indicated here
what you can see is that this equates in
this equation
I can cancel out the amplitude factor
and this complex exponential
so let's just cancel those out on both
sides of the equation
and what we're left with is an equation
that specifies what the complex exponent
must be
in particular for the homogeneous
solution s must be equal to minus a
and so finally are homogeneous solution
is as I've indicated year
okay now let's look at the solution for
specific input let's consider for
example input
which is a scale units step and
although I won't work at the solution in
detail and perhaps
using what you've worked on previously
you know how to carry out the solution
for that the
a solution with step input
is what i've indicated here scaler one
minus the next financial times unit
staff and you can verify that simply by
substituting into the differential
equations now
we know that there's a family of
solutions in other words
any solution with
a homogeneous solution added to it is
again a solution
and so if we consider the solution I
just indicated
we generate the entire family of
solutions by
ending a homogeneous solution to it and
so
this then corresponds to the entire
family of solutions
where the constant a is unspecified
so far and needs to be specified through
some type avoids avery conditions
now a class A auxiliary conditions
is the Commissioner initial rest which
as i indicated before is equivalent to
the statement that the system
is causal and linear and time-invariant
and
in that case for the initial rest
condition
we would then require in this equation
above
that this constant be equal to 0
and so finally the response
to scales step if the system
is the correspond to cause a linear
time-invariant system
is then just this term namely
constant times one minus an exponential
times step
okay now if the system is a linear
time-invariant system
it can as we know be described through
its impulse response
and as you've worked out previously
in the video course manual for
a linear time-invariant system the
impulse response
is the derivative love the step response
adjusted quickly remind you
love where that result comes from in
essence
we can consider to linear time-invariant
systems and Cascade
wanna differentiator the other the
system that we're talking about
described by
the differential equation and step in
here
then generated in polls into our system
and out comes the impulse response well
just using the fact that
these are both linear time-invariant
systems and they can be cascaded in
either order
then means that if we have step response
to our system and that goes through
differentiator
what must come out again is the impulse
response
so differentiating the step response we
get the impulse response
here again is the step response as we
just worked it out this time for you
next step if we differentiate
we have then since the step response
is the product of two terms the
derivative a product is the sum
the derivatives and carrying that
algebra through
and using the fact that the derivative
the step
is an impulse finally we come down
to this statement for the impulse
response
and then recognizing that this is but
I'm
function times and in polls and we know
that a time function times in polls
takes on
the value at the time that the impulse
occurs
then this term is simply 0
and the impulse response then
finally is an exponential this for
and this is the peking exponential for a
positive
it's a growing exponentially for a
negative and
recall that as we talked about
previously
a system is a linear time-invariant
system is stable
if its impulse response is absolutely
integral
for this particular case this impulse
response
is absolutely integral provided that
the exponential factor a
is greater than 0
okay so what we've seen then is the
impulse response for system described by
a linear constant coefficient
differential equation
where in addition we will impose
causality
when you're ready in time invariance
essentially through the initial
conditions
love initial rest
now pretty much the same kinds of things
happen
with difference equations as we've gone
through
with differential equations in
particular
again let me remind you love the form
love
and aunt order when your constant
coefficient difference equation
its as I indicate here and
again a linear combination this time the
late versions of the output equal to a
linear combination
up the late versions love the input once
again
the difference equation is not
a complete specification the system
because we can and to the response
any homogeneous solution in other words
any solution that satisfies the
homogeneous equation
in the summer those well also satisfy
the original
difference equation so if we have
a particular response that satisfies
the difference equation then ending to
that
any response there is a solution to the
homogeneous equation
will also be a solution to the total
equation
the homogeneous solution again is of the
form
of a linear combination of exponentials
here
we have the homogeneous equation as with
differential equations we can
guests or impose solutions for
eight times an exponential when we
substitute this
into the homogeneous equation we then
end up
with equation that i've indicated here
we recognize again
there a the amplitude
and seats at the end
this exponential factor cancel out
and so this equation is satisfied
for any values love see
that satisfy this equation and
there are and roots C-one through Z and
and so finally the form for the
homogeneous solution
is a linear combination love capital and
exponentials capital and is the order
the equation
with each of those exponentials the
ample to factor is undetermined
and needs to be determined in some way
through
the imposition love appropriate
initial conditions are boundary
conditions
so the general form then
for the solution to the difference
equation
is
some with the exponentials plus any
particular solution
its through auxiliary conditions that we
determine
these coefficients we have
and undetermined coefficients and so
we require capital and auxiliary
conditions
for example some set values
of the output at and this thing instance
time
now this
was the same as with differential
equations in the case a differential
equations we talked about specifying
the value of the output and its
derivatives and
there we indicated dead for linearity
what we required when the arity what we
require
is that the auxiliary conditions 30
and the same thing applies here for the
same reason
namely if the system is to be linear and
the response if there's no input must be
equal to 0
in addition what
we may want to impose on the system is
that it be causal and in addition to
linear
time-invariant and with that requires
again
is that it the auxiliary conditions be
consistent with
initial rest namely that if
the input is zero prior to some time
in the output is zero prior to the same
time
okay so we've seen a very direct
parallel
so far between differential equations
and difference equations
in fact one difference between them dead
in some sense makes difference equations
easier to deal with in some situations
is dead
in contrast to a differential equation a
difference equation if we assume
causality
in fact is and explicit
input-output relationship for the system
now let me
show you what I mean
let's consider the n-th order difference
equation as i've indicated here
and let's assume that we're imposing
causality
so there'd the output can only depend
on prior values at the input and
therefore on fire values at the output
well we can simply rearrange this
equation
solving for Y have an the leading term
with cable 0
taking all the other turns over to the
right side of the equation
and we then have a workers if equation
namely that an equation expresses the
output interns
love prior values if the input which is
this term
and prior values at the output
and so if in fact we have this equation
running
then once it started we know how to
compute
the output for the next time
well
how do we get started the way we get it
started of course
is through the appropriate said love
initial conditions are boundary
conditions and if for example
we assume initial rest corresponding to
a causal when you're time-invariant
system
then if the input is zero up until
sometime
the output must be zero up until that
time and Matt in essence
helps us get the equation started well
let's look at this
specifically in the context love a
first-order difference equation so let's
take
a first-order difference equation
as i've indicated here
and so we have an equation that tells us
that why I have and minus eight times
wider than -1
is equal to exit
now if we want this to correspond to
a causal linear time-invariant system we
oppose initial impose initial rest on it
we can
rewrite the first-order difference
equation by taking
the term involving y ven -1
over to the right hand side of the
equation
right now this gives us a workers if
that expresses the output interns the
input and past values at the output
and since we've impose causality
and if we're talking about a linear
time-invariant system
we can now inquire as to what the
impulse responses and we know of course
that the impulse response
charles is everything that we need to
know about the system
okay so let's shoes and input which is
an impulse so the impulse response
is Beltre van corresponding
to the exit and appear plus eighty Delta
love this should be a chip N -1
and let me just correct that this is a
chip N -1
so we have the impulse response as Delta
van
was eight times a Japan -1
now from initial rest we know
bad since the input namely an impulse is
0 for and less than zero
the impulse response is likewise 0
for and less 0 and now
let's work out what 80 its well
80 with an equal 0 is
delta up zero plus eight times
a chip N -1 HRN minus 10
and so h0 is equal to 1
okay now that we have a chance 0 we can
figure at H
one by running this recursive equations
so 8 you've won is
Delta love one which is zero
plus eight times h0 which we just
figured out as one
so HR one is equal to a and if we carry
this through
will have a chip to equal to a squared
and
this will continue on and in fact we can
recognize
by looking at this and how we would
expect these terms to build
we would see that the impulse response a
Japan
in fact -ism form a to the end times
you have an
and we also can recognize then dead
this corresponds to stable system
if and only if the impulse response
which is what we just figured out if and
only if the impulse response
is absolutely so noble and what that
will require
is that the magnitude a the less
okay now we impose causality linear
ready in time invariance
and generated a solution recur simply
and now of course if we want to generate
the more general
center solutions to this difference
equation
we can't do that by adding all of the
homogeneous solutions namely all the
solutions to satisfy the homogeneous
equation so
here we have the causal linear
time-invariant
impulse response in fact
with an impulse input all of the
possible solutions
are that impulse response plus
the homogeneous solutions the
homogeneous solution is the solution
that satisfies the homogeneous equation
that will in general
believe the form an amplitude factor
times an exponential factor and
if we substitute this into this equation
then we see that the homogeneous
equation is satisfied for any values
have a
in any values see that satisfy
this equation again as we did with
differential equations
the factor Amy cancels out and also in
fact I can cancel out is either the N
there and seat to the end here
and so what we're left with is a
statement that tells us
then dead the homogeneous
solution is over for AC to the end
for any ban you capital A and any value
see it satisfies this equation and
that values the in particular is the
people today so the homogeneous solution
then
is any exponential this form with any
amplitude factor
and so the family of solutions with an
impulse
input is the solution
corresponding to the system being cause
a linear and time-invariant
plus the homogeneous sir
if
we impose causality Lenny a ready in
time invariance
on the system then of course that
additional
exponential factor will be 0 in other
words capital A
is 0
okay now in we seen the
differential equations and difference
equations interns
love
the fact there there are families have
solutions
and in order to get causality Lenny a
ready in time
variance requires imposing a particular
set initial conditions namely
imposing initial rest on the system
let's now look at the difference
equation
and then later the differential equation
interpreted in block diagrams
now p the difference equation at
I just simply repeated here is why I
have an
is accident was a white van -1
where I've taken that the late term
over to the right hand side of the
equation so in effect
what on imposing on this system is
causality
I'm assuming that if I know the past
history
the input and the output I can determine
the next value the out
well we can in fact draw a block diagram
represents that equation the equation
says
we take exit and for any given bad you
a van say n0 whatever bad you were
computing the output were
we take the input at that time
and and to it the factor a
times the output value that we
calculated last time so
if we have excessive and which is our
input
and if we have why I have and which is
our output
we in fact can't get why I have an
by taking the last value why event
indicated here by putting why I have an
threw it away multiplying Matt
by the factor
a
and then Anning that result
to
the input
and the result the doing that is
why event
so the way this block diagram
might be interpreted for example as an
algorithm is this a
dead we take exit Van add to it
eight times the previous value the
output that some gives us
the current value of the output which we
then put out of the system
and also put into a delay element or
basically it was stored register to use
on the next generation a recursion
now how do we get this started well we
know that the difference equation
requires initial conditions
and in fact the initial conditions
correspond to what we store
in that the late register when this
block diagram
equation initially starts up
okay now let's look at
this for the case %uh difference
equations
more generally
so what we said is dead we can calculate
the output by
having previous values that the input
previous values at the output and
forming
the appropriate linear combination so
let's just build up the more general
block diagram
that would correspond to this
and what it says is that we want to have
a mechanism
restoring past values the input in a
mechanism for story past values at the
output
and i've indicated that on this figure
so far by a chain love
the layout its indicating
that whatever what
the output each delay is the input
delayed by one time it's
or or interval and so
what we see down this chain of the
ladies are the late replications
love the input and what we see
on the other chain is delayed
replications love the output
now the difference equation says that we
want to take these
and multiply them by the appropriate
coefficients
the coefficients in the difference
equation and so we can do that
as i've indicated here so
now we have these delay elements each
multiplied
by the appropriate coefficients on the
input and by
appropriate coefficients on the output
those are then
songs together and
so we now what's on these and what's on
these
after we've some these we want to add
those together and there's a factor 1
over 80 that comes in
and that and generates are out
and so this in fact and
represents a block diagram which is a
general block diagram for implementing
war representing near constant
coefficient difference
wage
now if you think about what it means in
terms of what's a computer algorithm or
a piece of hardware
in fact this block diagram is a recipe
or algorithm for doing the
implementation
by it's important to
recognize even at this point dad it's
only one
many possible algorithms or
implementations for this difference
wage
just for example
I can consider that equation
core that block diagram
and here I've redrawn at so
here once again I have the same block
diagram that we just saw
and I can recognize for example
that this in essence corresponds to
to linear time-invariant systems
in cascade
now that assumes of course that my
initial conditions are such dad I that
the system is in fact
when you're and that in turn requires
that we're assuming initial rest namely
before the input does anything
other than 0 there are just zero value
stored in the registers
but assuming that it corresponds to a
linear time-invariant system
this is a cascade to linear
time-invariant systems
we know that two linear time-invariant
systems can be cascaded
in either order so in particular I can
consider
breaking this cascade here and moving
this block
over to the other side and so let's just
do that
and when I do
I then have
this combination systems
and of course you can ask what advantage
there is to do in at
and the advantage arises because it the
fact
there'd in this form
exactly what is stored in these delays
is also stored in the still air
registers
in other words it's this intermediate
variable
whatever it is down this chain of delays
and down this chain of the ladies
and so in fact I can collapse those
delays
into a single chain of delays and
the network that I'm left with is the
network that I indicate
I missed you graph where what I've done
is to simply collapse that
double chain of the ladies into a single
chain
the waves
now want to ask well what's the
advantage to doing that and the
advantage
one advantage simply stated is that when
you think in terms of an implementation
of a difference equation
the lady corresponds to
storage register a memory location and
by this
by simply using the fact that we can
interchange the order in which linear
time-invariant systems are cascaded
we can reduce the amount of memory by a
factor to
okay now
and essentially similar procedure can
also be used for
differential equations in terms of
implementation
using block diagrams for the
interpretation implementations
using like diagrams and let me first do
that
rather than in general let me first do
it in the in
the context love a specific example
so
let's consider a when your constant
coefficient differential equation as
i've indicated here
and I have terms on the left side in
terms on the right side
and with the differential equation
let's consider taking overturns
over to the right side of the equation
except
for the highest the residue in the
output next we
integrate both sides of the equation are
so that
when we're done we end up with the on
the left side of the equation
with y ft on the right side of the
equation with the appropriate number
%uh integrations and so the InterPro
equation
that will get is for this example y ft
the output is except the
plus be the scale factor times the
integral
the input and -8 at scale factor times
the integral
the output so to
form the output in a block diagram turns
we form a linear combination of the
input
scaled in to grow the input and a scale
integral love the output all of that and
it together
so we need in addition to
the input we need the integral
love the input and so this box indicates
an integrator
in addition to the output we need
the integral the output and now
to for why ft we
multiply the integrated in play
by the scale factor B and
and back to exit C
and retake the integrated output
multiplied by Minas de
and and to that
the result are the previous addition
and according to the integral equation
then that forms
the output
so just as we did with the difference
equation
we've converted the differential
equation to
an integral equation and we have a block
diagram for very similar
to what we had in the case the
difference equation now the initial
conditions of course
are tied up and again how these
integrators
are initialized assuming that we impose
initial rest on the system
weekend thinkers the overall system is a
linear time-invariant system
and it's a cascade one linear
time-invariant system with the second
so we can in fact
break this
and consider interchanging the order in
which these two systems a cascade
and so i've indicated that down below
here
I've simply taken the top block diagram
interchange the order in which the to
systems are cascaded and
here again we can ask what the
advantages to this
as opposed to the previous one and what
you can see
just as we saw with the difference
equation is that
now the integrators both integrators
are integrating the same thing in
particular
the input to this integrator and the
input
to this integrator are identical so in
fact
rather than using this one we can simply
tap of
from here we can in fact remove this
integrator
break this connection
and happy and at this point and so
what we've done and by interchange in
the order in which the systems are
cascaded
is reduced the implementation to the
implementation
with a single integrated very much
similar to
what we talked about in the case the
difference wage
now let's just again with the integral
equation
way the differential equation looked at
this somewhat more generally again
if we take the differential equation the
general differential equation
integrated a sufficient number of times
to convert it to an integral equation
we would then have this cascaded systems
and again if we assume initial rest
so that these are both linear
time-invariant systems
we can interchange the order in which
they are cascaded
namely take the second system and
move it
to proceed the first system
and then we recognize is that the input
to this change
integrators and this change integrators
is exactly the same
and so in fact we can collapse these
together
using only one change integrators and
the system
there we're left with then is system
that looks as i've indicated here so we
have
now just a single chain integrators
is that a the two sets in
so we've seen that the situation is very
similar here as it was in the case the
difference equation
again why do we want to cut the number
integrators in half
well one reason is because integrators
in effect represent hardware
and if we use half as much if we have
half as many integrators
then using half as much hard
okay well let me just conclude by
summarizing
a number of points I indicated at the
beginning
that linear constant coefficient
differential equations a difference
equations
will play an important role as linear
time-invariant systems
throughout this coursing throughout the
center lectures
I also stress
the fact that differential or difference
equations
by themselves are not a complete
specification
the system because of the fact that we
can and
to any solution a homogeneous
I do we specify the appropriate initial
conditions
to ensure how do we specify the
appropriate initial conditions to ensure
that the system
is linear and time-invariant well
the auxiliary information namely the
initial conditions
dissociated with the system
be causal linear and time-invariant
are the conditions of initial rest
and in fact for most of the cores
what will be interested in systems that
are in fact cause a linear and
time-invariant
and so we will in fact be assuming
initial rest conditions
now
as I also indicated their are
a variety of efficient procedures for
solving differential
and difference equations that we haven't
yet address and
beginning with the next set of lectures
will be talking about
for EA transform and much later in the
course
what's referred to as the apostrophe its
form for continuous-time
and sea transport for discrete-time and
what we'll see
is that with the Fourier transform in
later with the apostasy transform
will have a number love efficient and
very useful ways
%uh generating the solution for
differential and difference equations
this under the assumption that the
system is causal
when you're in time very
also will see in addition to the block
diagram implementations
the systems that we talked about so far
we'll see another a number of other
useful
implementations that exploit a variety
of properties associated with
Korean past thank you