ha the the
the more
the last time
we talked about the you the
representation
%uh linear time-invariant systems
through the convolution song
in the discrete-time case and the
convolution integral in the
continuous-time
case now although the derivation was
relatively straightforward
in fact the result is really kind of
amazing because
what it tells us is that for linear
time-invariant systems
if we know the response to the system to
a single in polls
at equal 0 or in fact that any other
time
then we can determine from that its
response
to an arbitrary input through the use of
convolution furthermore
what we'll see as the course develops is
that in fact
the class a linear time-invariant
systems is a very rich class
there are lots of systems that have that
property
and in addition there are lots a very
interesting things that you can do with
linear time-invariant systems
in today's lecture
what I'd like to begin with is focusing
on convolution as an algebraic operation
and will see that it has a number of
algebraic properties then in turn
have important implications for
linear time-invariant systems then we'll
turn
to a discussion or what the
characterization %uh linear
time-invariant systems
through convolution implies
in terms of the relationship various
other system properties
to the impulse response let me begin by
reminding you love the basic result that
we
develop last time which is the
convolution some
in discrete-time as
I indicate here and
the convolution integral in
continuous-time
in and what the convolution some more
the convolution integral tells us
is how to relate the output
to the input and to the system impulse
response
and the expression looks
basically the same in continuous-time
and discrete-time
and I remind you also that we talked
about a graphical interpretation
where essentially to graphically
interpret convolution required for
was developed in terms
or taking the system impulse response
flipping it sliding it past the input
and with positioned appropriately
depending on the
value of the independent variable for
which were computing
the convolution and then multiplying and
summing in the discrete-time case or
integrating
in the continuous-time case now
convolution as an algebraic operation
has a number or important properties
one of the properties of convolution
is that it is what is referred to as
commuted
community here means that
we can think either a convo loving
X with age or H with axe
and the order in which that's done
doesn't affect the output result so
summarized here
is what the community operation is
in discrete-time or in continuous-time
and it says as I just indicated that
x7 convolved with a chip and
is equal to a chip and convolved
with exit or the same course
in continuous-time and in fact
in the lecture last time
we worked an example where we had
indiscreet I'm an impulse response which
was an exponential
and an input which is a unit step
and in the text what you'll find is
the same example work except in that
case
the input is the exponential and the
system impulse response is the step
and that corresponds to the example in
the text
which is example 3.1
and what happens in an example is that
in fact
what you'll see is that the same result
occurs an example 3.1 as we generated
in the lecture and there's a similar
comparison
in continuous-time this example was
worked in
lecture and this example
is work in the text in other words
the text works the example where the
system
impulse response is
unit step and the input is an
exponential
right now the community property as I
said tells us
that the order in which we do
convolution
doesn't affect the result to the
the same is true for continuous-time and
discrete-time
and in fact for the other algebraic
properties that I'll talk about
the results are exactly the same for
continuous-time and discrete-time
so in fact what we can do is
drop the independent variable as an
argument
so that we suppress any kinda difference
between continuous and discrete-time
and suppressing be independent variable
within state the community property as
I've
rewritten it here just X convulsed with
age because
H involved with the ex the same in
continuous-time
and discrete-time now
the derivation to the community property
is
more less amount you bro which you can
follow through in the book it involves
soem changes variables and
in some things that sort
what I'd like to focus on with that and
other properties
is not the derivation which you can see
in the tax
by rather the interpretation
so we have the community property and
now there are two other
important algebraic properties one being
what is referred to as the associative
property
which tells us that if we have X
convulsed with
the result ok involving h1 with h2
that's exactly the same as X convolved
with h1
and that result involved with h2
and what this permits is
for us to write for example ex-convict
alt with h1
involved with h2 without any ambiguity
because it doesn't matter from the
associative property
how we grew the terms together
the third important property is what is
referred to as the distributive property
namely the fact the convolution
distributes over addition
and what I mean by that is what i've
indicated
here on the slide dead if
I think or X convo with the psalm
of h1n h2 that's identical
to first involving X with h1
also can bombing X with h2 and then
adding the two together and that result
will be the same as this result
so convolution is community
associative and it distributes over
addition
three very important algebraic
properties and
by the way there are other algebraic
operations that have
that same property for example
multiplication
numbers is likewise commuted to
associative
and distributed now
let's look at what these three
properties
imply a specifically for linear
time-invariant systems
and as we'll see the the implications
are both very interesting and very
important
let's begin with the community property
and consider in particular
a system with an impulse response age
and I represent that by simply writing
the H inside the box
an input tax and an output then
which is X convulsed with age
now since this operation is commuted to
I can right is that affects convolved
with a I can write
H convolved with ex and that would
correspond
to a system with impulse response
X and input H and output then
age involved with ex
so the community property
tells us therefore a linear
time-invariant system
the system output is independent
all which function we call the input
and which function we call the impulse
response kind amazing actually
we can interchange the role input and
impulse response
and from input or permit output point of
view
the output for the system doesn't care
now furthermore if we combine the
community property
with the associative property we get
another very interesting result
namely that if we have two linear
time-invariant systems in cascade
the overall system is independent of the
order in which they are cascaded
and in fact in either case the Cascade
can be
collapsed into a single system
to see this let's first consider
the Cascade or two systems one with
impulse response h1
the other with impulse response h2 and
the outputted the first system is then
X convulsed with h1
and then that is the input to the second
system
and so the output a bad is that result
convolved with h2
so this is the result of cascading the
two
and now we can use the associative
property
to rewrite this and as
X involved with h1
involved with h2 where we grew these two
terms together
and so using the associative property
we now can collapse that into a single
system
with an input which is ax an impulse
response which is h1 convolved with h2
and the output is then ex-convict all
with
the result that those two can borrow
next we can apply the community property
and the commuter property says we could
write
this impulse response that way or we can
write it this way
and since convolutions community the
resulting output will be exactly the
same
and so these resulting output will be
exactly the same
and now once again we can use the
associative property
to group these two terms together
and X convulsed with h2
corresponds to putting X first through
the system h2
and then an output through the system h1
and so
finally applying the associative
property again as I just outlined
we can expand that system back into
two systems in cascade with h2 first
NH one second
okay well that involves a certain amount
love algebraic manipulation
and that it's not the algebraic
manipulation that's important is the
result that it's important
and what the result says to reiterate
this if I have to
linear time-invariant systems in cascade
I can cascade them in any order and the
result is the same
now you might think well G maybe that
actually applies the systems in general
whether you put them this way or that
way but in fact as we talked about last
time
and I illustrated with an example
in general if the system is not linear
the systems are not linear and
time-invariant then
the order in which they are cascaded is
important to the interpretation of the
overall system
for example one system took the square
root
any other system double the input
taking the square root and then doubling
gives us a different answer doubling
first and then taking the square root
and of course one can construct much
more elaborate example
net so it's a property very particular
to linear time-invariant systems and
also
one that we will exploit many many times
as we go through this material
the final property related to
interconnection systems that I want to
just indicate
develops ida the distributive property
and what it applies to is an
interpretation
%uh the interconnection of systems in
parallel
recall there the parallel combination
systems corresponds is a indicate here
to a system in which we simultaneously
feed the input into
h1 nh2 these representing the impulse
responses
and then the outputs our song and to
form
the overall output and
using the fact their convolution
distributes
over addition we can rewrite yes
as X involved with h1
plus h2
and when we do that then we can
recognize this
as the output the system with input acts
and impulse response which is the sum of
these two impulse responses
so for linear time-invariant systems in
parallel
we can if we choose
replace that interconnection by a single
system
whose impulse response is simply some
those impulse response
okay now we have this very
powerful representation for linear
time-invariant systems
terms 0 convolution and we've seen so
far in this lecture
how convolution and the representation
through the impulse response
leads to some but important implications
for system interconnections
what I like to turn to now are other
system properties
and see how for linear time-invariant
systems in particular
other system properties can be
Associated
with particular properties or
characteristics
love the system impulse response and
what will talk about
are a variety of properties will talk
about the issue memory will talk about
the issue
portability and will talk about the
issue
causality and also stability
well let's begin with the issue of
memory and the question
now is what are the implications
for the system impulse response for a
linear time-invariant system remember
that we're always imposing that on the
system
what are the implications on the impulse
response if the system
does or does not have memory
well we can answer that by looking at
the convolution property
and we have here as a reminder the
convolution integral
which tells us how accept an hour in a
chip T-minus
now are combined to give us y'at
and what I've illustrated above is
only general kind of example
here is except al here is
a chip T-minus now an
to compute the output at any time T
we would take these two multiply them
together
and integrate from minus infinity the
plus infinity
so the question then is what can we say
about
H T the impulse response
in order to guarantee let's say
that the output depends only on the
input at time t
well its pretty much obvious from
looking
at the grabs
if we only want the output to depend
on XO how at Tower equals T
then a chip T-minus have 0 better
be non-zero only at Tower equals T
and so the implication is that
for the system to be memory less
what we require is that HFT -10 now
be 90 only at outcalls
T so
we want the impulse response to be 90
and only one point
we wanted to contribute something after
we multiply and go through an integral
an effect with that says is the only
thing they can be
and meet all those conditions is a scale
dimples
so if the system is to be memoryless
then that requires that the impulse
response you scale them poles
any other impulse response
then in essence requires
that the system has memory or implies
that the system member
so for the continuous-time case then
memoryless would correspond only to the
impulse response being proportional to
an impulse and in the discrete-time case
a similar statement in which case
the output is just proportional
to the input again either in the
continuous-time
war in the discrete-time case
right now we can turn our attention to
the issue
love system inverter ability and
room recall that what is meant by
inverted bility of a system or the
inverse of a system
the inverse nervous system is a system
which one week cascaded
with the one that were requiring about
the overall cascade
is the identity system in other words
the output is equal to the in
so let's consider a system with
impulse response age input is ax
and let's say that the impulse response
that the inverse system is a
by and the output is why
then the output of this system is
X convolved with age convolved with a
stir by
and we want this to
come out equal X and what that requires
then
is that this convolution
just simply be equal to an impulse
either in the discrete-time case
or in the continuous-time
and under those conditions then HD by
is equal to the University
rotationally by the way its of
inconvenient
to right instead of eight supply as the
impulse response
the embers will find it convenient of
any more typical
to write as the in burners instead of
age to buy
age to the -1
and we mean by that the inverse
impulse response and one has to be
careful not to misinterpret this
as the reciprocal have a chip to your
YouTube and
which meant in this notation is the
inverse system
now if age to buy
is the inverse of age is H the inverse
have a supply
well it seems like that or be plausible
or
perhaps make sense the question if
you believe that the answer is yes is
howdy how in fact
you verified that and
I'll leave that to you think about it
the answer is yes that
if a surprise the inverse of age than H
is the inverse a pizza by
and the key to showing that is to
exploit the fact
that when we take the systems and
Cascade them we can cascade
them in your order
all right now let's turn to another
system property
the property love stability and again
we can't I that property directly
to issues related
in particular to the system impulse
response
now stability is defined as we've chosen
to define it as I
I by the previously as bounded input
bounded out but stability in other words
for every bounded input
is a bounded out what you can show
and I won't go through the algebra here
it's
going through in the book is the
a necessary and sufficient condition for
a linear time-invariant system to be
stable
it in the bounded input bounded output
sense
is that the
impulse response be what is referred to
as
absolutely so mobile in other words if
you take the absolute values
and some over infinite limits that's
fine I
or in the continuous-time
case that the impulse response is
absolutely integral
in other words if you take the absolute
bad news have a chip T
integrate that's fine I'd and under
those conditions
the system is stable if
those conditions are violated then
for sure as you'll see in the text the
system
is on stable so stability can also
be tied to the system impulse response
now the next property that I wanna talk
about
is the property of causality
and before I do what I'd like to do
is introduce peripheral result that will
then
use when we talk about causality
namely what's referred to as the zero
input response
when your system
the basic result which is a very
interesting and useful one
is that for a linear system and in fact
it's whether it's time invariant or not
this applies
if you put nothing into it you get
nothing out
so if we have an input
accept T which is zero for all T
and if the output that system
is y'at
if the input is zero for all time
then the output likewise is 0 for all
time
that's true for continuous-time and
it's also true for discrete-time
and in fact to show that result
is pretty much straightforward we could
do it either by using convolution which
would of course be associated with many
a ready in time invariance
but in fact we can show their property
relatively easily
by simply using the fact that for a
linear system
what we know is that if
we have an input exit T
with an output y'at
then if we scale the input
then the output scales accordingly
well we can simply shoes
as the scale factor eight equal 0
and if we do that it says put nothing in
you get nothing out and
what will see is that that has some
important implications
interns love causality
it's important though wall or on it to
stress that
not every system obviously has that
property did nothing
you get nothing out a simple example
is let's say a battery
let's say not connected to anything the
output is six bolts no matter what the
input is
and it of course then doesn't have this
0 response to zero input very particular
the linear systems or I will now
let's see what this means for causality
to remind you causality says in effect
that the system can't anticipate the
input that's what
basically causality means when we
talked about it previously we defined it
in a variety of ways
one of which was the statement that
if two inputs are identical up until
sometime
than the outputs must be identical up
until the same time
the reason kinda to Italy is that
if the system is causal so it can
anticipate the future
can anticipate whether these two
identical imports are
sometime later going to change from each
other
or not
so causality in general is simply this
statement
either continuous-time and discrete-time
and now let's look at what that means
for a linear system for a linear system
what that corresponds to or can be
translated to
is a statement it says that
if x50 is 0 party less than $30,000
then y'at is the must be zero
party less than $30,000 also
and so what that in effect
says is that the system
for a linear system to be causal
in mice have the property sometimes
referred to
as initial rest meaning
it doesn't respond until there's some
input that happen
that it initially at rest until the
input becomes
90 now why is this true why
is this a consequence of causality for
Lee year systems well the reason is
we know that if we put nothing in we get
nothing out
if we have an input that 0 perty less
than t0
and the system can't anticipate whether
that input is going to change from zero
or not then yes it must also the system
must generate
and output that 0 up until that time
following the principle that if two
inputs are identical up until sometime
the outputs must be identical up same
time
so this basic result
for when here systems is essentially
a consequence all the statement there
for a linear system 0n
gives us 0 out
now bad tells us
how to interpret or hi I don't tupac was
ality
for linear systems now let's proceed to
linear time-invariant systems
and in fact we can carry the point one
step further
in particular necessary and sufficient
condition
for causality in the case linear
time-invariant systems
is there the impulse response
be 0 party less than zero
in the continuous-time case or
for and less than zero in the
discrete-time case
so for linear time-invariant systems
causality
is equivalent to the impulse response
being 0 up until to your and equal to 0
now to show this it essentially follows
by first considering
why causality
would imply that this is true
and that follows because if the
straightforward fact
that the impulse itself is 0 perty less
than zero
and what we saw is there before is that
for any linear system causality requires
that if the input is your office or
sometime
the output must be zero up until the
same time
and so thats showing
the result in one direction to show the
result
in the other direction namely to show
you that
yeah in fact the impulse response
satisfied that condition then the system
is causal
while I won't work through it in detail
it essentially boils down to recognizing
that in the convolutions some
or in the convolution integral
if in fact that condition is satisfied
on the impulse response
then the upper limit on the song the
discrete-time
case changes an and in the
continuous-time
case changes to see and that in effect
says that bad news or
the input only from minus unity up the
time n
are used in computing y van and a
similar kind of result
for the continuous-time case why
T
okay so we've seen how the impulse
response
or rather how certain system properties
in the linear time-invariant
case can be converted into
various requirements on the imports
responsible when your time
very insist on the impulse response
being complete characterization
let's looked at some particular examples
just
to and a cement the ideas further
and let's begin with a system that
you've seen previously which is
accumulator accumulator as you recall
has an output why I have an
which is the accumulated value
up the input from minus infinity up to n
now you've seen in the impose in in
a previous lecture or rather in the
video course manual for previous
lecture that an accumulator is a linear
time-invariant system
and in fact it's impossible sponsor is
the accumulated
bad news opinion polls namely the
impulse response
is equal to a step
so what we want to answer is
what knowing what that impulse responses
what
some properties are the accumulator
and let's first ask about memory
well we recognize that the impulse
response
is not simply an impulse in fact it's a
step
and so this implies what well
it implies that the system has
memory
second the impulse response
is zero more and less than zero
that implies that the system is
causal
and finally if we look at
the some the absolute values at the
impulse response from minus infinity
plus infinity
this is a step we accumulate those
values over infinite limits
then at in fact comes out to be infinite
and so what that implies then is that
the accumulator is not stable in
the bounded input found that out what
sets
now I want to turn to some other systems
but while we're on the accumulator I
just want to draw your attention to the
fact
which will kinda come up in a variety of
ways again later
that we can rewrite the equation for an
accumulator the difference equation
by recognizing that we could in fact
write the output as the accumulated
values
up the time n -1 and then and on the
last value
and in fact if we do that this
corresponds to why
van -1 and so
we could rewrite this difference
equation as why I have an
is why event -1 a sexy
so the output is the previously computed
output
plus the input expressed that way
what that corresponds to is what is
collar workers a difference equation and
difference equations will be a topic
I'll considerable emphasis in the next
lecture
now does an accumulator have an inverse
well
the answer is in fact yes and let's look
at what
the inverse that the accumulator is
the impulse response the accumulator is
a step
to inquire about its inverse in we
inquire
about whether there's a system which one
we cascade
the accumulator with that system which
i'm calling its in burrs
we get an impulse out
well let's see the impulse response
the accumulators staff we want to put
the step into something
and get out in polls and in fact
what you recall from the
lecture in which we introduce steps and
impulses
the impulse is in fact the first
difference of the units that
so we have a difference equation
that describes 4s how the impulse
is related to the step and so
if this system does this the output will
be
that an impulse and so if we think
or x2 a van
and as the input and y2 event is the
output
then difference equation for
the inverse system is what i've
indicated here
and if we want to look at the impulse
response to that
we can then inquire as to what the
responses with an impulse in
and white develops in a straightforward
way
and is Delta van which is are important
point
minus Delta again -1
is equal to the impulse response
in burrs system so alright that
as age in person
now we have been that the accumulator
as it infers and this is the embers
and you can examine issues a memory
stability causality et cetera
what you find is that the system has
memory
the University later it's stable
and its causal and it's interesting to
note by the way
that although the accumulator with an
unstable system
the embers are the king later is a
stable system
in general if a system is stable its
inverse
does not have to be stable or vice versa
and the same thing with causality
okay now there are
a number of other examples which course
we could discuss
and let me just quickly point to
in one example which is a difference
equation as i've indicated
here and as will talk about it more
detail
in our next lecture will will
get involved in a fairly detailed
discussion linear cut coefficient
difference
and differential equations this falls
into that category
and under the imposition
what's referred to as initial rest
which corresponds to response being 0
up until the time that the input becomes
non-zero
the impulse response is a to the N
times you have an and something that
you'll be asked to think about in the
video course manual
is whether that system has memory
whether its causal
and whether it's stable and likewise
for a linear constant coefficient
differential equation the specific one
that I've indicated here under
the assumption of initial rest the
impulse response
is into the minus two tee times you the
and in the video course manual again
you'll be asked
to examined whether the system has
memory
whether its causal and whether it's
stable
okay well as i've indicated in the next
lecture will
return to much more detailed discussion
when your constant coefficient
differential and difference
equations now what I'd like to finally
doing this lecture is use the notion of
convolution in a much different way
to help us with a problem that I alluded
to earlier
in particular the issue love how to deal
with some other mathematical
difficulties associated
with impulses and steps
now let me begin by illustrating
kinda what the problem is and the
an example of the kinda paradox that
sore right to
when dealing with impose functions and
step
options
let's consider first the ball a system
which is the identity system and so the
output is
course equal to the input and
again we can talk about that either in
continuous-time and discrete-time
well we know that the function that you
convolved with a signal to retain a
signal
is an impulse and so that means that the
impulse response
love and identity system is an impulse
makes logical sense
furthermore if I take to identity
systems and Cascade them
I put in an input get the same thing and
the first system that goes into the
second system get the same thing at the
second
in other words if I have to
identity systems in cascade
the cascade likewise is an identity
system
in other words this overall system is
also and identity system
and the implication there is that the
impulse response
up this is an impulse the impulse
response if this is an impulse
and the convolution of those two is also
an impulse
so for continuous time we require than
that
interpose convolved with itself was an
impulse
and the same thing for discrete-time
now in discrete-time
we don't have any particular problem
with that if you think about convolved
in these together
it's a straightforward mathematical
operation
since the impulse in continue in
discrete-time
is very nicely defined
however in continuous-time we have to be
somewhat careful
about the definition at the impulse
because
it was the derivative a step-by-step has
a discontinuity
you can't really differentiate at a
discontinuity
in the way that we dealt with that was
to expand out the discontinuity so that
it had some finite time region in which
it happen
when we did that we ended up with a
definition for the impulse
which was the limiting or up this
function
which is a rectangle with Delta
and height one over Delta and an area
equal to 1
now if we think I'll convolved being
this signal with itself the impose being
a limiting
former this then the convolution
up this with itself is a triangle
with to Delta height1 over Delta
in area 1 in other words
this triangular function is this
approximation delta sig Delta T
can't fault with dealt this adult T
and since this would then
the limited this would correspond to the
impulse response
all the identity system
convolved with itself the implication is
that not only should the top
function this one
correspond in its limiting form to an
impulse
but also this should correspond it is
limiting
form to an impulse so one could wonder
well what is an impulse is it
this one in the limit or is that this
one in the limit
now beyond that there
so kinda what this suggests is that in
the limiting
for me kinda run into a contradiction
unless you don't
try to distinguish between this
rectangle in the Triangle
things get even worse when you think
about
what happens when you put an impulse
into a differentiator in a
differentiator is a very commonly
occurring system
in particular suppose we had a system
for which
the output was the derivative of the
input
so if we put in extra T we got out the
exit
the DT if I put in an impulse or if I
talked about the impulse response what
is that
and of course the problem is that if
you think that the impossible self is
very badly behaved
then what about its derivative which is
not only
infinitely big but there's a positive
going on in negative going one in the
difference between a handsome area
and you your end up in a lot of
difficult
well the way around this formally is
through
a set of mathematics refer to as
generalized functions
we won't be quite that formal but I'd
like to at least
suggest with the essence that formality
is and it really
helps us in interpreting the impulses
and steps and functions at that time
and what it is is operational definition
love steps impulses and their
derivatives
in the following sense: usually when we
talk about a function
we talk about what the bag with the
function is at any instant of time
course the trouble with an impulse is
it's infinitely bigan 0 within has some
areas center
well we can turn to is what is referred
to as
and operational definition where
the operational definition
is related not to what the impulses
but to what the impulse does under
the operation convolution so
what is an impulse and impose is
something which under convolution
retains the function
and net then conserve as a definition of
the imports
well let's see where that gets us
suppose that we now
want to talk about the derivative up the
in polls
well what we ask about is
what it is operationally and so if we
have a system
which is a differentiator an
we inquire about it's impossible
response which let's say we define
rotationally as you serve 180
what's important about this function you
serve one ft
is not what it is at each value time
but what it does under convolution
what is it doing a convolution well the
output the differentiator is the
convolution
up the input with the impulse response
and so what you serve 180 does on the
convolution
is to differentiate
and Nat is the operational definition
and now of course we can think extending
net
not only would we want to think about
differentiating
an impulse but we would also what about
want to think about differentiating the
derivative opinion polls
will define that as a function use up to
eighty
use up to 50 because we have
this impulse response convolved with
this one is you wanna T convolved you
wanna T
and what is you 280
operationally it is
the operation such that when you can
ball
that with except he what you get
is the second derivative
okay now we can carry this further and
in fact
talk about the result I'll involving
you wanna TE with itself
more times in fact if we think that the
convolution
or you want it T with it so k times
then logically we define that as use a
Kft
again we would interpret that
operationally
and the operational definition is
through
convolution where this corresponds to
use a cave T in the impulse response
love k differentiators in cascade
so what is the operational definition
well it simply
that except the convolved with you sir
kute
is the K derivative
accept T and
this now gives us a set 0 what are
referred to as singularity functions
very well
badly behaved mathematically in a sense
but
as we've seen reasonably well defined
under an operational definition
the cake was 0 incidently that's the
same as
what we have referred to previously as
the impulse so
cake 0 that's just dealt T
now to be completely can also go the
other way and talk about
the impulse response a string 'em
integrators instead of a string it
differentiators
course the impulse response a single
integrator is a unit step
to integrators together is the integral
the units that
et cetera an that
likewise corresponds to
a Sat Nav what are called singularity
functions
in particular if I take string or
am integrators in cascade
then the impulse response that is
denoted as use up minus MFT
and for example with a single in a
greater use up minus 150
corresponds to are unit step
as we've talked about previously use a
-2 ft
our spines to unit ramp
et cetera and there is in fact a reason
for choosing negative values have the
argument
when going in one direction here
integration as compared with positive
values the argument we going
in the other direction namely
differentiation
in in particular we know bad
with uses my sms to the
the operational definition is the AM
running into kroll and
like why is use a Kft
so with a positive subscript has an
operational definition
which is the derivative so
if the Cape derivative exit T
and in partly as a consequence if that
if we take use it Kft
and convolved it with use ability the
result
is this the singularity function with
the subscript which is the sum
K&L and that holds whether
this is positive values that the
subscript or negative values at the
subscript
so just to summarize this last
discussion
we've used an operational definition to
talk about derivatives love impulses
and integrals impulses this led
to said a singularity functions work all
singularity functions of which
the impulse in the stepper two examples
by
using an operational definition through
convolution
allows us to to find
at least an operational sense these
functions that otherwise a very badly
a
okay now in in this lecture in
previous lectures for the most part our
discussion has
been about linear time-invariant systems
fairly general terms and we've seen a
variety
properties representation through
convolution
and properties as they can be associated
with the impulse response
next lecture will turn our attention to
a very important
subclass those systems namely systems
that are described below beilin your
constant coefficient
difference equations in the
discrete-time case and when your car is
the coefficient
differential equations in the
continuous-time case
those classes while not
forming all the classic linear
time-invariant systems
are very important subclass and will
focus in on those specifically next
thank you