the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home in
the
the in
the menu
are
for last time we
introduce the notion that mapping
continuous-time filters to discrete-time
filters and we developed in Polson
variance as
one useful technique for carrying out
that type mapping
but I'd like to do in this lecture
is illustrate in Polson variants as a
design procedure
in the context so one specific
class all filters namely Butterworth
filters
and in then following that will proceed
on to discuss
another very important and useful
mapping or design procedure referred to
as the by linear transformation
so to begin let me
just discuss briefly what the class a
Butterworth
filters is and specifically
the Butterworth filters are the fine
through their frequency response a
transfer function and I'm
using capital be to denote a Butterworth
filter
and by definition the magnitude square
to the frequency responsible Butterworth
filter
is given by this expression and for
example
if and more equal to 1 then this would
simply
correspond to the magnitude squared love
the frequency response
for a first order differential equation
now if you
look at the frequency response be a
filmmaker
for this class the filters
I've illustrated that below and
what we see is that
the frequency response starts at Unity
because that's that's the way that its
normalized and it has
a monatomic characteristic in the past
band and the stop and
at a frequency equal to the pram inner
Omega subsea
up here which is referred to as the
cutoff frequency
the Butterworth filter frequency
response
always goes through the same point
namely point 707
and as the order the Butterworth filter
capital and
increases the transition
from the passband to the stop band
becomes sharper and sharper so for
higher-order filters then
the frequency response is flattering the
passband
and drops of more quickly and attenuates
more
in this topic now
in designing Butterworth filters what we
we want to look at is the location at
the polls
all the system function and
we can in for those from our definition
I'll what the frequency response for the
Butterworth filter is
in particular we have this expression
for the magnitude squared the frequency
response
and we recognize that of course as
be love J Omega times be
love minus J Omega that's what the
magnitude squared
will be equal to and in order to convert
this
to an expression describing the system
function or in terms that the
more general applause transform variable
ass
well we recognize is dead J Omega
in the more general setting simply
corresponds to
the applause transform variable s so
this product in fact
is the applause transform for st. go to
jail make a
more generally then this is the result
of evaluating
be a vast eyes be a minus S&S equals J
Omega
consequently comparing this expression
with this statement leads us to the
conclusion
dead the transfer function be a badass
the Butterworth filter times be off
minus s
is given by the expression that I
indicate here
simply replacing J Omega by S
now what we want to look at are the
holes
all be a vast that's what we'll want to
get as we
design a Butterworth filter and
we can recognize the polls love this
product
simply by looking at the roots at the
denominator polynomial
and those roots are just taking a
counter this factor 2n
those routes are at J Omega subsea
times the 2n roots I'll
-1 those roots in fact all I on a circle
an the consequences that is that
the holes all this expression
are on a circle the circle
is radius omega-6 see and the polls are
distributed
around the circle so here I demonstrated
the polls love be a vast size be at
minus s
for the specific case for capital and is
equal to 3 so there are a total of six
polls
around the circle and
then for this specific case the polls a
space by
sixty degrees now we have PSA's be at
minus s
to get the system function for the
Butterworth filter we'd like to get
BFS and the question now is how do we
get that
well the thing to recognize is dead
wherever
this factor has a route
this factor has to have a root at
the negative location so in fact when we
look at these polls we compare them
with this for example associated with be
a badass
this associated with the at minus s and
likewise we compare these two together
and so we can extract the evas from this
product
simply by taking one poll at a beach
those pairs
now a question of course is I did each
pair which one do we associate with BFS
wish to associate with the minus says
and the answer drops out fairly simply
if we recognize dead if
we want to design filters that are
stable
then be a vast the transfer function
that we're designing
must have all its polls in the left
after the S play
so in fact we would associate outta each
of these pairs
we would associate the left airplane
poll with the evas
and so the transfer function
for the Butterworth filter for this
particular case where the parameter
where this designates the parameter
Omega subsea
capital and his three namely a third
order Butterworth filter
is this center pole locations given
those
of course we can figure out simply
throughout your break means
what the transfer function be a veces
alright so that's what in Butterworth
filters are in now
what I'd like to do is talk about
the design or additional Butterworth
filter
using the design technique that we
introduced last time namely in polls and
variance
and the context in which I will
phrase the design is the context
love mapping a
continuous-time signal to a
discrete-time signal
carrying out filtering using the
discrete-time
go to that we're designing and then
mapping back so
we're talking about now a discrete-time
filter
that we want to designed to impose
severe in variance from
Butterworth filters from continues time
Butterworth filters
and we're going to get our design
specifications
in the context loved having
considered discrete-time processing of
continuous-time signals
where we will map from
a continuous-time signal to a sequence
carry out the filtering with the
discrete-time filter
that we're going to design and then
we will take the resulting filtered
output
and map it back to the continuous-time
signals
but this discrete-time filter is
the one that we're talking about
designing and
for choice a parameter there's a
sampling frequency of course involved in
this process
and the value that I'll pick for the
sampling frequency
is 10 killers
okay all fairly straightforward so far
and so since we have a
sampling rate of 10 killer hurts we
want to first look at our specifications
on the desired continuous type filter
and then mapped those to appropriate
specifications on the discrete I told
and what I'll pick for the
desired specifications on the
continuous-time filter
is that at
one kilohertz I will ask
that the continuous-time frequency
response
be down by no more then 1db
in comparison with its value at Omega
equal 0
so that in effect specifies the behavior
in the past band
for the specifications on the passband
and
for the stop band specify dead
the filter is down by 15 DB
by the time we've gotten to
one-and-a-half kilohertz
so we have in essentially the beginning
of the transition band the end of the
past and it won't kill hurts
and the beginning at the stop and at one
point five killer hurts
and since we're talking about designing
a Butterworth filter we know that the
Butterworth filter is
monatomic in the past and stop and and
so
will have a filter specification
something is a show here this represents
the allowable passband tolerance
this is the allowable stop and tolerance
and if I can draw this without
getting myself into trouble a sexually
were looking for a filter then
then always stays between
the specified boundaries
here
now what we have to figure out is what
the corresponding specifications
are for the digital filter in the
strategy let me emphasize
is dead we have
situation where we're doing
continuous-time and discrete-time
processing continuous-time signals
and we have specifications associated
with that
that imposes specifications on our
discrete-time
filter and then we wanted design
the discrete-time filter using impose
invariance
and that's the discrete I feel to their
will use the overall system
right now we want specifications
on the discrete-time filter
and we want the continuous overall
equivalent system
to have certain arm
meet certain specifications a certain
frequencies related to
continuous-time frequencies recall
that when we sample a continuous-time
signal
is a very specific mapping from the
continuous-time
frequency axis to the discrete-time
frequency axis
in particular the sampling frequency
gets mapped to to Part II
well that means there are other critical
frequencies get mapped
in proportion to that so one killer
hurts which is a 10
love the sampling frequency with then
convert to a discrete-time frequency
love point2 pie
and one-and-a-half kilohertz will
convert to
a discreet I frequency love point three
pie
so what this says is that for the
discrete-time
filter we would like
the same behavior
but at frequencies are the same
specifications
but at frequencies normalize
to the discrete-time frequency axis
that means dead we want the
discrete-time
frequency Mac frequency response
magnitude
to be greater than or equal to -1 DB at
two-tenths pie corresponding to the one
killer hurts and continuous-time
and four the beginning
love this top band in that would occur
at point three pie
at which point we want this less than or
equal to minus 15
so those are our discreet I
specifications
and we now wanted design the
discrete-time filter using impulse and
parents
now in the polls in variance as you
recall
it corresponds to
sampling generating an impulse response
which is a sampled
version love the continuous-time impulse
response
and there is a temptation naturally
to think love this parameter capital T
as necessarily identical
to the sampling
in the system in which the filter is
going to be use
now this is a fairly subtle complicated
tongue twisting issue
but the bottom line on at the essential
point
is that the parameter capital T that we
use in imposing variant
design as a totally different unrelated
and in fact as it turns out arbitrary
parameter
which is not necessarilly pegged
to the sampling frequency and I think it
would be difficult for me to totally
clarify that
during the lecture it's discussed more
the book
and certainly you should take plenty of
time to reflect on
for it but let's no look then
at where we are in our design procedure
and specifically what it is that we need
to do
in order to design the digital
Butterworth filter now we have
a set of specifications there we
we've generated relating essentially to
how we want the passband if the digital
filter
and the stop and above the digital
filter to behave
course since this isn't an ideal filter
it has sound transitions from passband
to stop and
and as we discussed last time there is
aliasing which we need to at least
beware oath
we specified certain frequencies along
this axis
which are easily converted by
relating the the two axes through this
mapping
are you easily related back to
the continuous-time
frequency axis as we have here
and in particular now if we
word is simply pick that parameter in
the imposing variant design capital T
as equal to unity and I indicated just a
minute ago that we can pick it
arbitrarily
if I a pic is unity then the procedure
which consists
about designing the continuous-time
Butterworth filter
with meeting the pro or exceeding the
appropriate specifications
and then going through the imposing
variant procedure
alright so let's do that then
we want the discrete-time impulse
response to be the continuous-time
paul's response sampled and for
convenience I'm going to pick this
parameter capital T equal to 1
that means dead the frequency
normalization between
the discrete-time frequency axis and the
continuous-time
frequency axis in fact is
those axes are scaled identically
because
capital T is equal to 1 and so now
we want the analog for continuous-time
specifications and so what we need to do
then
is design a Butterworth filter I'm using
capital be here again to denote
the frequency response the Butterworth
filter the Butterworth filter
to have a magnitude which is greater
than or equal to -1 DB
prior to the frequency 0.2 pie
and less than or equal to -15 at a
frequency
beyond 0.3 part
and so now what we need to do is
determine
capital and and Omega subsea
in order to meet or exceed the
specifications
now if you go through The Associated
algebra doing at let's say that
you decide that you want a pic capital
and omega-6
see to exactly meet those inequalities
at
the to frequencies point to point point
three pie
what you'll find after going through the
algebra
is that there exactly Matt
if capital and is 5.88
and omega-6 see is point 7047
and this obviously can't
is in satisfactory as parameters for the
Butterworth filter
why is that the reason is
that capital and isn't an integer and in
the class a Butterworth filters to
generate a rational transfer function
capital N this parameter must be an
integer
so since it can't be 5.88
the natural thing to do is to move it up
to the next closest integer namely 6
and that means that will end up with a
filter that goes even better
in the specifications on the other hand
there's something kinda underneath the
surface
dead is inherent in the impulsive area
design procedure
namely the fact dad there will always be
some aliasing
so one strategy and a natural one often
imposing variant design is to
shoes and as the next highest integer as
I've done
and then shoes the parameter omega-6 see
so that the passband specifications
are exactly met and the stop and
specifications are then slightly
exceeded
and that will leave some margin for
releasing
right now continuing this example then
how would we complete the design
well we know what are two parameters
capital and and omega-6
CR in that means that we can determine
BFS
times be at minus s those polls are
located
on a circle in the complex s plane
and the polls on that circle are paired
Sat some being associated with BFS and
some would be a minus s
and in particular to determined be a
badass
we would simply take the polls
on the portion of the circle it's in the
left after the S
point now
with active service is a
butterworth continuous-time filter
which we're then mapping to impose
invariance
with capital T equal to 1 to
a discrete-time filter that
discrete-time filter
to be used in a system
which has disassociated sampling
frequency
which is 10 killer hurts
so to get the discrete-time filter then
we first determine be a vast as we just
did
or at least they indicated how to do it
we would then expand that out in a
partial fraction expansion
and then apply the imposing variant
procedure
which consists love mapping the polls
in the S plane to polls in the seaplane
at locations either the s2k
capital T your capital T is equal to 1
and retaining the residue where the
coefficients
in the expansion and this ban
will give us the transfer function for
the discrete-time
filter so
if in fact we
did at than the resulting frequency
response
that we would get is what i've indicated
here
and I indicated first on a magnitude
scale linear magnitude scale and second
on a like a rhythmic scale and
as we had originally specified the
digital filter
is supposed to be greater than a recall
to
-1 dB at point to pie and less than or
equal to -15
the be at point three pie
and in fact this slightly exceeds the
specifications
since we had purposely allowed some
margin
in this topic
now this is an illustration of the
impulse invariant procedure
and it has a number very nice properties
one of which is that
it takes a continuous-time filter
frequency response
and it converts it to a discrete-time
frequency response which
in the absence Bailey is saying looks
identical except for linear frequency
scale change and in fact we pick capital
T equal to one in there is no scale
change
it has the major disadvantage
dead there is always daily as saying and
for some
design for some problems for example if
the filter we're trying to design
is not ban limited or low pass
then the alias saying will actually
become intolerable
well there's another design procedure
which I now want to introduce
which totally avoids the problems have
aliasing
but obviously then has its own costs
associated with
and that procedure is referred to as
the by linear transformation
the by linear transformation which our
own
try to drive here in any detail
is a mapping love continuous-time
filters
to discrete-time filters corresponding
to taking the applause transform
variable ass
in the continuous-time filter and
replacing it
by what is referred to as a file in your
function at z
and so if I substitute this in here
that will give me the discrete-time
frequency response
again in this procedure there's a primer
capital T
which again is totally irrelevant given
the approach that we're taking
and which we will generally tend to
normalize out to unity
and let me just say quickly and passing
dead although we all go through this the
notion of the by linear transformation
can be tied to the concept love
taking the differential equation for the
continuous-time
filter converting it to an integral
equation by integrating
enough times on both sides
and then converting Matt to
a difference equation by approximating
the integrals with the trapezoidal rule
and that in effect will correspond
to mapping the continuous-time filter to
a discrete-time
filter with the by linear transformation
well we'll just focus on
the properties love the mapping and in
particular
if we were to substitute into
the expression see equal to you DJ Omega
corresponding to the unit circle
we would find dead the unit circle
in discrete-time corresponds to mapping
DJ Omega axis in continuous-time which
is exactly
what we want now the mapping
between the continuous-time frequency
and the discrete-time frequency
is a nonlinear mapping which
is given by the algebraic expression
that I indicate here
and if we plot this mapping
but we have is this Kurt
and what this corresponds to then
is a mapping cause the J Omega axis or
continuous time-frequency
to discrete-time frequency
and if we think more generally oath the
mapping represented by the by a linear
transformation
in the context of the S plane in the
seaplane
it corresponds to mapping
DJ Omega axis in the S plane
to what's around the unit circle in the
seaplane
and you can also convince yourself
that the left after the S plane maps
to the inside the unit circle and
so that means dead stable
continuous-time filters will always map
to stable
discrete-time filters which is exactly
what we desire
now notice in this that there's no issue
avail yes and what's happened is
that we've replaced espy function FZ
corresponds to
mapping BS point too busy playing fact
the whole J Omega axes
has mapped to once around the unit
circle
which obviously requires some type of
nonlinear mapping because
like the jamming axis is infinitely long
the unit circle has a fine I radius
and so essentially what has to happen is
if you think
love walking along the continuous-time
frequency axis and simultaneously
walking around the unit circle
if you walk at a constant rate around
the unit circle
and your simultaneously walking up the
jam a axis
if you want to get around the pie by the
time
here you've gotten tune infinity along
the continuous-time frequency axis you
better
wats kittens are walking faster faster
faster because you've got
an infinite distance to cover while you
just go over a finite distance here
well worldwide says really is that
that's why in fact we're taking
the entire or were able to take the
entire
Omega axis and just map it into an
interval
all above link pie
right now that means that their
is a nonlinear distortion of the
frequency axis
if we were to take a continuous I filter
and converted to
a discrete type filter with the by a
linear transformation
how do we account for that were for that
matter
when can we really use it and
we can see how to had a both take
account of it
and what its limitations are by
recognizing the following suppose that
I wanted design a
discretized salter and
what is going to happen is that it will
be mapped to a continuous-time filter
the relationship between
the two frequency axes will be given by
this Kurt
so let's supposed dead the
continuous-time frequency response looks
as I've shown here
with a passband cutoff frequency and its
top and cut-off frequency
if this were mapped
through the by a linear transformation
to
a discrete-time filter then this cutoff
frequency
would fall over here
which is related through this curve and
this cutoff frequency to stop and age
would be here again reflected it's these
frequencies reflected
through this skirt
so let's suppose now that what I'd like
to do is design
a discrete-time filter where the
discrete-time filter has
certain frequency specifications
which is what are previous example has
it has let's say a specified stop and
age
as specified past bandage and assess
specified stop and age
the design procedure within correspond
to
mapping those frequencies
to the corresponding continuous-time
frequencies
designing the continuous-time filter
to me this specification space
on those critical frequencies
then taking the continuous-time design
and mapping it back to a discrete I
filter
through the by linear transformation
right now what we want to do is
again map a Butterworth filter
continuous-time Butterworth filter to
to a digital filter in such a way that
the digital filter approximately
meets the specifications that we had
before
and let me just remind you love where we
were
the critical frequencies were at 0.2 pie
and 0.3 pie and
what we had asked for is dead the
frequency response
be down by no more than one dB
up 2.2 pie and down by
at least 15 TV at Point three-part
so we want to design the same
discrete-time filter as we did before
with imposing variance
we now want to do it with the by linear
transformation
applied to an appropriate butterworth
design
okay well so let's see what kinda
specifications we have
we know that the frequency the critical
frequencies are mapped
through this curve for this equation
and I indicated again that this
parameter capital T is
arbitrary in the design procedure
that may seem confusing initially but
this some further discussion of it in
the book and it's true an important to
sort out
so we're going to pick capital T equal
to unity
and that means then that the
corresponding critical frequencies
all the continuous-time filter
are at twice but ancient love
0.2 pie over to and twice the tangent
love 0.3 pie over to
so that means then there the
specifications on
our continuous-time filter
are given by this sensually
past fans stop and edges warped through
that nonlinear curve this nonlinear
curve
and I'm using capital G here to denote
the system function for the
resulting continuous-time salter
and so now we could think of designing a
Butterworth filter
that lets say exactly meets the
specifications
well if you do that what you'll find is
dead
you get exact a quality
here if you pick capital N
equal to 5.3
and again we have the issue that
if we want to meet or exceed the
specifications we can't make
the filter order lower we have to make
it higher and so
we would make it is so to 5.3 with make
the filter order equal to 6
and now again we have several
options and trade-offs before with
imposing variance
we essentially decided to meet the
passband specifications and exceed the
stop and specifications
to provide some margin for aliasing
here we don't have any a leasing
and we can't ratings of any way we'd
like
the way that are chosen to do it is to
exactly me the
stop and cut off and exceed
the passband specifications and
the result to doing that is to choose
a filter order capital and equal to 6%
and though parameter Omega subsea in the
Butterworth filter
is given by 0.7 6622
alright so now we have
the parameters for
the continuous-time Butterworth filter
which when mapped to
the discrete-time filter through the by
linear transformation
will exceed our requirements in the past
band and Justin
just me the stop and cut off and so
now we want to complete the design
procedure and
given the parameters
up the Butterworth filter we can draw
are appropriate circle in the S plane
which happens to be the same circle as
before
but with a different radius and
then associate polls on this circle
with be a bass and be a minus s in
particular take the ones in the left
after the S plane
same ones we had before except we have a
different value for Omega subsea
in and does then represent
BFS so we can now determine be a badass
and new ones we have the transfer
function be a badass
we then map that to a
discrete-time filter by mapping through
the by linear transformation and that
then
is the design procedure through
which we would follow for this example
by well let's just see what
the result looks like when we're done
here I show again on both
a linear magnitude scale in on
a logarithmic good DB scale the
frequency response
love the resulting filter and recall
that the specifications were dead 8.2
pie
we should be down by no more than 1d
being clearly we've exceeded that
considerably
and 8.3 pie we should be
are down by at least 15 DB and we chose
the design so that we would exactly
meet that edge so we've met this point
and exceeded this point and this is our
Design
now let's just compare this
with the impulse invariant design that
we saw
a few minutes ago
and the impossibility and design is
what I indicate here be
by linear transformation design is
now overlaid on top of that
it's hard to see much difference on a
linear
magnitude scale but let's look online
horrific scale
and this one that I'm lifting is the by
linear transformation
and this is imposing variance
and notice in fact something very
interesting
which is dead the sold the
filter dead we obtained by
mapping the Butterworth filter to a
digital filter through the by a linear
transformation
in fact falls off in frequency
much more rapidly then the one that we
got through imposing variance
the question is why now one thought that
might come to mind is well we possibly
Reince as a leasing by linear
transformation doesn't have a leasing
that must be a consequence a daily as
saying
in fact that's not the reason aliasing
as it turns out in this particular
design is raw
was relatively minimal in the opossum
variant design
the reason has to do with
is nonlinear mapping in the by a linear
transformation
from the continuous-time frequency to
the discrete-time frequency
keep in mind dead through then mapping
as you start walking around the unit
circle and moving up the Chi Omega axis
as you move up the jam make access you
have to move faster faster faster faster
and what's in continuous-time frequency
and infinity
is what you get to in a discrete-time
frequency by the time you get around the
park
so in fact what we're looking at is
as as we look out along this frequency
axis
is we're seeing
higher and higher and higher frequencies
in the continuous-time
filter by the time we get the pie
we should in fact be in the
continuous-time goals are equivalent Lee
off to infinity which sounds like pretty
uncomfortable place to be
okay now this was a a fairly
rapid trip through a number of issues
i in particular some the issues
associated with the filing your
transformation
and and also this issue
love how you pick this parameter capital
T and how it might be associated with
the
sampling frequency if you doing
discrete-time processing
a continuous-time signals and we don't
have time
to explore summer those issues more
fully
in this lecture but in I'd like to
conclude by making a
couple comments 1 comment is there the
two techniques that we've talked about
impulse and Berrien center by linear
transformation
are the two techniques that are
principally
used when one thinks mapping
continuous type filters to discrete-time
filters for whatever application and I
stress again
that you may want to do that mapping
whether or not
the discrete-time filter is eventually
going to be used for processing
continuous-time signals
now imposing variants
have a characteristic dead it very nice
characteristic that are
that it corresponds to a linear mapping
between the two frequency axes
except for the issue with aliasing
and that's a problem with that and in
particular limits its usefulness
to filter designs or for mapping
continuous-time
filters their band limited
on the other hand we have the by linear
transformation as a design procedure
which totally avoid daily as saying
but has the disadvantage or difficulty
better represents a nonlinear mapping
from the continuous type filter
to the discrete-time filter now this
nonlinear distortion
is perfectly acceptable if we're
designing
or attempting to designed filters that
have flack frequency characteristics
it's not acceptable if for example we
had a linear frequency characteristic
that we wanted to map to discreet I
filter and end up with a linear
frequency characteristic
it won't come out to be linear because
all
this nonlinear mapping at the frequency
axis
now in there are also
a number of other design procedures
which we won't go into
for designing discrete-time filters and
among them
are a variety of techniques including
for example
computer-aided design procedures and I
invite you
if you're interested and want to dig
into that
in more detail and more deeply to
explore that topic by making reference
to
various love the books listed in the
bibliography
in the text thank you