the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU ha the
the
the in
the new the last time
we began a discussion feedback
and I briefly introduce the number
applications for example
the user feedback in compensating for
non-ideal elements in a system
and also is another example
the user feedback in stabilizing
unstable systems
in this final lecture what I'd like to
do
is focus in more detail on the user
feedback
to stabilize unstable systems and the
specific context in which I'd like to do
that
is in the context love the inverted
pendulum now
i've referred to the inverted pendulum
in several
past lectures and basically as everyone
realizes
a pendulum is essentially a ride with
the weight on the bottom
and naturally an inverted pendulum is
just that upside down
and so it's essentially a ride that's
top-heavy
and the idea with the inverted pendulum
is although by itself
its unstable around a pivot point at the
bottom
the idea is to applying external input
an acceleration
essentially to keep it balanced and
we've all
probably done this type of thing at some
point in our lives
either childhood or not and so that's
the system that I'd like to analyze and
then
illustrate in this lecture now the
context
in which will do that is not with my
son's
course but actually with an inverted
pendulum
which is mounted on a card and first I'd
like to go through an analysis of it and
then
will actually see how the system works
well basically then
the system that we're talking about is
going to be a system which is a movable
card
mountains on the card is
a ride with the weight on the top and
this then becomes the inverted pendulum
and the cart has
and external acceleration apply to it
which
is the input that we can apply to the
system
and then in general we can expect some
disturbances and I'm gonna represent the
disturbances
interns love and angular acceleration
which shows up around the wait at the
top of the rock
so if we look at the system then
as I've kinda indicated it here
basically we have
two inputs we have
an input which are the external
disturbances
which we can assume that we have no
control over
and then their is the acceleration
thats applied to the cart: externally or
in the case so
balancing my son's course it's the
movement my hand
and then through the system dynamics
that ends up influencing the
angle of the ride and will think
love the anchor the angle of the ride as
the system output and basically the idea
then
is to try to keep that angle at zero
by applying the appropriate acceleration
now
as i've mentioned several times
previously if
we know exactly what the system dynamics
are
and if we know exactly what the external
disturbances are
then theoretically we can choose an
acceleration
for the card which will exactly balance
the system
or balance the ride however says the
system is inherently unstable
any deviation from that model in
particular any
unanticipated external disturbances will
excite the instability
and what that means is that the rival
for
so the idea then is
as we'll see to stabilize the system
by placing feedback a rounded in
particular
by through measurement the output angle
process through some appropriate
feedback dynamics
using Matt to control deceleration
the cart and if we choose the feedback
dynamics correctly
then in fact we can end up with
a stable system even though the
open-loop system is unstable
well as a first step let's analyze the
system in its open loop form
their particular let's analyze the
system without feedback
demonstrate dead indeed it is unstable
and then
see how we can stabilize using feedback
so the system then is
as we've indicated the variables
involved
are the measured angle which represents
the output
the acceleration angular acceleration
due to external disturbances
and then there is the applied external
acceleration on the card so these
represent the variables with
lol representing the link to the rod and
SFT I indicate here which we won't
really be paying attention to
as the position of the card
and without going into the details
specifically what we'll do is
set up the equation to write the
equation in terms of balancing the
accelerations
and if you go through that process then
the basic equation that you end up with
is
the equation that I indicate here and
this equation then tells us how the
basic forces are accelerations a balance
where this is the second derivative or
the angle and then we have
deceleration due to gravity reflected
through
the angular acceleration times sign
love the angle the angular acceleration
due to the external disturbances and
finally
the angular acceleration due to the
motion the cart
now this equation is written here is a
nonlinear equation
in the angle say to T and
what we'd like to do is linearized
equation
and really arise the equation by making
the assumption
dead the angle is very small close to
zero
no other words what will assume is that
we're able to keep
the rod relatively vertical and our
analysis
because we're winning a rise in the
equations will obviously depend on that
so making the assumption that the angle
is small
we then assuming that the sign up the
angle is approximately equal to the
angle
and the cosine the angle is
approximately equal to 1 that will then
linearized this equation
and the resulting equation then
in its linearis form is the one that I
indicate here
so we have an equation emotion which
which linearis is the balances the
accelerations
and what we see on the right hand side
of the equation
is the combined inputs
due to the angular acceleration of the
ride and the acceleration of the card
and on the left hand side of the
equation we have
the other forces due to the changing the
angle
so this is Dan the differential
equations Associated
with the open-loop system the basic
dynamics at the system
and if we apply the law applies
transform to this equation
and solve for the system function than
the basic equation that were left with
expresses
the applause transformer the angle
equal to the system function the
open-loop system function
times the applies transform all the
combined in points
and I remind you again that are sumptin
is that this is an input that we have
no control over this is the input that
we can control
and the two together of course form the
combined input
now we can of course saw for the poles
and zeros there are
no zeros and their two polls since this
is the second order denominator
and looking at the polls in the S plane
then we see that we have a pair of polls
one
at minus the square root of G over L and
at plus the square root G over L
and the important observation and is
dead while
this poll represents a stable poll
the right half plane poll represents
unstable pole
and so this system in fact is
unstable system it's unstable because
what we have is a poll in the right half
plane
for the open-loop system
now before we see how to stabilize the
system what's in fact
look at the mechanical setup
which we I won't turn on for now
and just see essentially what this
instability means and
what the physical or irritation at the
equipment is
so what we have which you just saw a
caricature of
in a few graph is an inverted pendulum
this represents the pendulum and
it's mounted with a pivot point at the
bottom
it's mounted on a cart and here we have
the card
and this is a pivot point
and as you can see the cart can move
back and forth
on a track and the external acceleration
which is applied to the card is applied
through this cable
and that cable is controlled
by motor and we have the motor
at this ended the track and so
as the motor turns than the cart will
move back and forth
okay now since the system
is not turned on and has no Feedback in
fact
the system as we just saw in the
transparency is
unstable system and what then is the
ability means
is that for example if I
set the angle 20 and then let it go
then as soon as there's a slight
external disturbance
it will start to fall now you can
imagine
that not only is the system unstable as
it is
but certainly can't accommodate changes
in the system dynamics for example if we
change
let's say the way to the pendulum so we
thought for example
love changing the wait by let's say
putting something like a glass with
something in it on
top and I think about trying to balance
it by itself obviously
thats part in fact I would say without
turning this system on
guaranteed to be impossible so
the basic system as we just analyzed it
is
inherently an unstable system the
instability reflecting the fact
that the pendulum are following its own
natural forces will tend to fall
and now what we want to look at is how
through the use the feedback weekend in
fact
stabilize the system
so let's first
once again look at the
open-loop system and
the open-loop system function that we
saw was the system function
of this form one over LS squared minus G
and that represents the system function
Associated with the two inputs one being
the external disturbances
the other being the externally applied
acceleration
and the system function here
is the represents the system dynamics
and
the resulting output is the angle
now the feedback to basic strategy
behind the feedback is to in some way
use the measured angle make a
measurement of the angle
and use that through appropriate
feedback dynamics to stabilize the
system
and so with feedback applied around the
system then
their would be some measurement up the
angle
through so appropriately chosen feedback
dynamics
and that dan would determine 4s
the applied external acceleration
corresponding
to what the motor does by pulling the
cable back and forth
and we would like to choose she evas so
that the overall system is stable
now as you recall from the lecture last
time
with the feedback around the system
expressed here
interns have negative feedback the
overall transfer function then is the
transfer function
associated with the basic feedback loop
where HFS
is the open-loop system and GFS
corresponds to the feedback dynamics
now that's the basic strategy we haven't
decided yet
how to choose the feedback dynamics and
that becomes the next step and we want
to choose the dynamics in such a way
that the system ends up being stabilized
well I think the thing to do is just
simply begin
with what would seem to be the most
obvious which is
a simple measurement of the angle let's
take
the angular measurement feat that back
let's say through a potentiometer and
perhaps an amplifier so that there's
some gain
and see if we can stabilize the system
simply through
feedback which is proportional to a
measurement of the angle
what is typically referred to as per for
proportional feedback
well let's analyze the results
doing that once again we have
the basic feedback equation where
the open-loop transfer function is what
we had
developed previously given by the
second-order expression
now using proportional feedback
we shoes the acceleration
a hefty to be directly proportional
through a game constant or attenuation
constant k1
directly proportional to the measured
angle theta ft
and consequently the system function in
the feedback
path is just simply a gainer for
attenuation k1
so this then is the system function for
the feedback
well substituting this into the
closed-loop expression
then the overall expression for
the apostrophe its form of the output
angle
is as i indicated here
namely that faded ass is
proportional through this system
function
to the apostrophe its form love the
input X 50 and let me remind you that
X 50 the external disturbances now
represent the only input
since the other input corresponding to
the applied acceleration so the card
is now controlled only through the
feedback
luv so we have this system function then
for the closed-loop system we recognize
this once again
as a second-order system and
the polls both this second order system
are then given by plus and minus the
square root
love G minus k1 divided by L
so k1 the feedback constant
clearly influences the position at the
polls
and let's look in fact at where
the polls are in the S play
well first of all with
k1 equal to 0 which of course is no
Feedback
and corresponds to the open-loop system
we have the polls
where they were previously
and if we now choose k1 let's say less
than zero
than what will happen as
k1 becomes more and more negative
so that this term is more and more
positive is dead
the left here plane poll will move
further into the left airplane
the right half plane poll will move
further into the right half play
so clearly with K one negative
this poll which represents an
instability because
even more unstable well
instead a K one negative let's try K one
positive and see what happens
and with k1 positive
what happens in this case is dead
the left hip plane poll moves
closer to the origin the right half
plane poll
was closer to the origin what one would
hope is that
they both end up in the left airplane at
some point but in fact they don't
what happens is that eventually they
both reach the origin
split at that point and travel along
the jail make axis now this movement of
the polls
as we very k1 either positive or
negative
we all we see is that the open with the
open-loop system
as we introduce feedback those basic
polls
move in the ass plane either this way
as K one becomes more negative or for
this particular case
K one is positive they move in together
split move along the jail make axes
and that locus the polls in fact is
referred to
if the back terminology as the root
locus and as is discussed in
much more detail on the tax there are
lots of ways
love determining the root locus for
feedback systems
without explicitly solving for the roots
for this
particular example in fact we can
determine the root locus
the most straightforward way simply by
song for the roots
I'll that the nominator the system
now notice that in this case these polls
with K one positive have moved together
they move along the jail make axes and
before they come together the system is
clearly unstable
even when they come together and split
the system is marginally stable
because in fact the system with 10
docile E
and what that isolation means is that
with the measurement of the angle
essentially if the polls are operating
on the J Omega axes
what will happen is that
things will oscillate back and forth
perhaps with
the cart moving back and forth trying to
compensate
and the ride sorta moving in the
opposite direction
in any case what's happened is with just
proportional feedback
we apparently are unable to stabilize
the system
well you could think that the reason
perhaps is that we're not responding
fast enough for example
if the angle starts to change
perhaps in fact we should make the
feedback proportional
to the rate of change Bengal rather than
to the angle itself
and so we could examine the possibility
using
what's referred to as thrifty back
and derivative feedback what we would do
is to shoes
for the feedback equation
or for the feedback system function
something reflecting a measurement love
the derivative
the angle and so here again once again
we have the open-loop
system function with the river to
feedback will attempt
to or we will use this feedback
and acceleration which instead of being
proportional to the angle as it was in
the previous case
and acceleration which is proportional
to
the river the ankle and so the basic
feedback dynamics or feedback system
function
is their GFS is equal to k to times s
the multiplication by ass reflecting the
fact that in the time domain
its measuring the derivative the angle
The Associated system function is then
indicated here and if we saw again this
second order equation
for its roots that tells us that
the location the polls are given
by this equation
and so now what we would want to look at
is
how these polls mu as we very
the derivative the back constant k2
so let's look at the root locus for that
case
and first once again
we have the basic open loopholes
and the open loopholes consists of a
poll on the left half plane and a pole
in the right half plane
corresponding in this equation 2k to
equal to 0
that is no feedback in the system
if k2 is negative then what you can see
is that
this real part will become
more negative since K two squared here
this is still a positive quantity and in
fact
then with k2 less than zero the root
locus that we get
is indicated by this
now notice then that this right half
plane poll
is becoming more unstable and
the left airplane poll likewise is
becoming more unstable
and this point by the way corresponds to
wear this poll ends up
or where the root locus ends up went 8-2
eventually becomes infinite
so clearly k to negative is not going to
stabilize the system
let's try k2 positive
and the root locus dictated by this
equation then
is what I indicate here
the left half plane poll moves further
into left airplane that's good that's
getting
more stable the right half plain polo is
moving
closer to the left airplane
but unfortunately never gets there and
in fact
its when k2 eventually becomes infinite
that this poll
just gets to the point where the system
becomes
marginally stable so
what we found is dead with proportional
feedback
we can stabilize the system with the
Riveter feedback
we can stabilize the system by
themselves
and a logical next choice is to see if
we can stabilize the system
by both measuring the angle and at the
same time
being careful to be responsive to how
fast that angle is changing so that if
changing too fast
we can move the cart are here are or are
hand under the inverted pendulum were
quickly
well now then what we want to examine
is the use love proportional plus the
Riveter feedback
and in that case we
then have a
choice for the acceleration which
is proportional with one constant to the
angle
and proportional with another constant
to
the derivative up the angle and so
the basic system function then
with for for proportional plus the river
to feedback
is a system function which is K one-plus
K two times s
we then have an overall closed-loop
system function
say to the vastus which is given by
this equation and
so the roots at this equation then
represent the polls love the closed-loop
system
and those polls involved
to parameters they involve the primer k2
which is proportional to the derivative
the angle
and the constant k1 which is
proportional to the angle
and will
first have all examine this with just
with
k to positive because well we can see is
that as we very k1
k2 or negative that would more less
immediately
put polls into the right half plane and
the more
negative K two got the larger this term
is going to get so in fact is it will
turn out we can stabilize the system
with provided that we to choose k2
to be greater than 0
all right now with k2 greater than 0
what happens in the
location at the polls is that
if k2 is greater than 0
every choose k1 greater than 0 I'm sorry
choose k1 equal to 0
then in effect the influence of k2
is to shift the polls
of the open-loop system slightly and so
with k2 greater than 0
and k1 equal to 0 we have a set of polls
which are indicated here
and so this is just a shift slight shift
to the left
depending on the values k2 shift to the
left
the open loop holes now as we very k1
and in particular we're going to choose
k1
greater than 0 what happens is that
the polls will begin to move together
as they did previously when we had
one we looked at the variation k1
the polls will move together reach a
point where we have a second-order poll
and then those polls will split and move
parallel to the Chi Omega axis so
with syndicated here is the root locus
and what this represents then
as long as we make a one large enough so
that
this pole moves into the left airplane
is
that represents now stable system
okay so what we've seen is that
proportional feedback
by itself or derivative feedback by
itself
won't stabilize the system whereas with
the right choice
a feedback Constance proportional plus
the rivet if the back well and we saw
that
basically by examining the root locus in
the ass play
alright well let's actually watch the
system
in action and I described it to you
previously basically an inverted
pendulum on a card
and so I still have it off and of course
we have the pendulum
and as i indicated its
pivoted at the base and the
angle is measured by a potentiometer
that we have attached to the pivot point
and
the measurement of the angle is fed back
through this wire to motor day
we have at the other end of the table
and
then that motor basically is used to
provide the acceleration
to drive the cart okay well
let's turn it on and when we turn it on
it'll take
just an instant to stabilize
and
fortunately we have the cast set right
and there we have now
the stabilization up an unstable system
remember there with the feedback of the
system is unstable because the pendulum
will fall
whereas now it's stabilized now also
as you can see not only have we
stabilized it but we're able to
compensate for the feedback
to changes in the external disturbances
for example by tapping it
because it the feedback and the
measurement of the angle it will
more or less automatically stabilize
now in addition to being stable in the
presence of external disturbances
it also remain stable in remains
balanced
even if we were to change the system
dynamics
and let me just illustrate that with
the class that we talked about before
let's first
not be too bold and will take the liquid
out of the class
and presumably if it can adjust
to changes in the system dynamics that
if I put the glass on
in fact it will remain balanced and
indeed it does
and let me point out by the way that I
don't have to be very careful about
exactly where
I position the class and furthermore I
can change the
overall system even further
by let's say for example pouring a
liquid and
and now let me also comment that
change the physics of a little bit
because the
the liquid can slash around a little bit
it comes a little more complicated
system
but as you can see it still remains
balance
now if we really don't want to be too
conservative that all we can wonder
whether
with the feedback Constance we have we
could
in fact balance the picture on the top
and
well I guess we may as well give that a
try
and so
now we're changing the mass at the top
to the the pendulum
by a considerable amount
and again the system basically can
respond to it
now this is a fairly complicated system
the liquid sloshing around we in fact as
you can see have instability right now
although its control and that's because
the physics at the dynamics is changed
and we can put a little bit more mass
into the system
and maybe or maybe not that will cut
down on the instability
okay well in fact what happened there is
that we
increase the mass at the top the
pendulum slightly
and that provided just enough damn thing
to do
stabilize the system
okay well with
this lecture and this demonstration this
concludes this entire set of lectures it
concludes especially if the pitcher
happens to fall
but seriously this concludes the
said lectures as we have put them
together
and let me just comment that
as a professor of mine once said in
which I've never forgotten
the purpose all over said have lectures
or a course or for that matter anything
which is study
is not really to cover a subject
but to uncover the subject and I hope
dead
at least in to some degree
we were able to uncovered the topic of
signals and systems through the series
of lectures
there are a lot of topics that we
got only a very brief glimpse into
and I hope that at least four we've been
able to do
is get you interested nothin I'm so that
you pursue some of these on your own and
so I'd like to conclude by thanks to you
both for your patience and your interest
and I hope that you have enough interest
to
pursue some these topics for them thank
you