the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from 100 to them IT courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT ided you
home for
the
in
the No
for last time
we began to address the issue a building
continuous-time signals out a linear
combination of complex exponentials
and for the class a periodic signals
specifically what this led to was the
Fourier series representation
for periodic signals let me just
summarize
the result that we develop last time for
periodic signals we had the
continuous-time for you
for a series where we built
the periodic signal I dove a linear
combination
love harmonically related complex
exponentials
and what that led to was what we refer
to as
the synthesis equation and we
briefly address the issue love when this
in fact bills
when this in fact is a complete
representation at the periodic signal
and in essence what we presented was
conditions either Forex city being
square integrable
or X-eighty being absolutely inevitable
then the other cited the for a series
is what I refer to as the analysis
equation
and the analysis equation was the
equation the told us how
we yet the forty a series coefficients
from x50 and so this equation
together with the synthesis equation
represent
the forty a series description for
periodic signals
now we'd like to do is
extend this idea to provide a mechanism
for building not periodic signals also I
have a linear combination
complex exponentials and the
basic idea behind doing this is very
simple
and also very clever as i indicated last
time essentially
the thought is the following if we have
a non periodic signal or a periodic
signal
we can think love constructing a
periodic signal
by simply periodically replicating
that a periodic signal so
for example if I have in a periodic
signal
as i've indicated here I can consider
building a periodic signal where
I simply take this original signal
and repeated at multiples love some
period t0
now two things to recognize about this
one
is that the periodic signal
is equal to the a periodic signal
over one period and the second is that
as the period
goes to infinity then in fact
the periodic signal goes to
the a periodic signal so
the basic idea then is
to use the free a series to represent
the periodic signal and then examine the
4e a serious expression
as we let the period go to infinity well
let's quickly see how this develops
interns up the Associated equations here
again we have the periodic
signal and what we want to inquire
into is what happens to the forty a
serious expression for this
as we let the period go to infinity as
that happens
whatever for a series representation we
end up with
will correspond also to a representation
for this a periodic signal
well let's see the forty a series
synthesis expressions for the periodic
signal expresses
extol dirty the periodic signal as a
linear combination
of harmonically related complex
exponentials
with the fundamental frequency Omega 0
equal to 25 divided by the period and
the analysis equation tells us
what the relationship is for the
coefficients
interns are the periodic signal now I
indicated
that the periodic signal and the a
periodic signal
are equal over one period we recognize
that this integration in fact only
occurs over one period
and so we can really express this
interns
all our original a periodic signal so
this tells us the for a series
coefficients
interns affect safety
okay now
if in we look at this expression which
is the expression for the 4e
coefficients the a periodic signal one
other things to recognize
is dead in effect what
this represents are samples
all an integral where
we can think all the variable Omega
taking on values better integer
multiples
Omega 0 said another way let's define a
function as i've indicated here
which is this in a brawl where
and we may think it will make a as being
a continuous variable
and then the forty a series coefficients
correspond
to substituting Omega
is for Omega K
Omega 0 now one reason for doing that as
we'll see is that in fact
this will turn out to provide us with
the mechanism
for forty-a representation affect safety
and this in fact and is an on below
all the four EA series coefficients
in other words t0 the period times the
coefficients
is equal so this integral at integer
multiples
Omega 0
okay so this effect tells us how to get
the for a series coefficients the
periodic signal
interns love samples of an envelope and
that will become a very important notion
shortly and in
that in effect will correspond to an
analysis equation
to represent the a periodic signal now
let's look at the synthesis equation
group call that in the synthesis our
strategy is
to build a periodic signal and let the
period go to infinite
well here is the expression
for the synthesis the periodic signal
now expressed interns
I'll samples of this envelope function
and where I've simply use the fact that
the substitution
that t0 is to pile for Omega 0 and so I
have an Omega 0 here
and a 1-over to pie and the reason for
doing that
as we'll see in a minute is that this
then turns into an integral
specifically then the synthesis equation
that we have is
what i've indicated here we would now
want to examine this
as the period goes to infinity which
means that
Omega 0 becomes infinitesimally small
and without dwelling on the details
and with my suggesting that you give
this a fair amount of reflection
in fact what happens as the period goes
to infinity
is that this some Asian approach is an
integral
over Omega where Omega 0 becomes the
differential
and Omega and the periodic signal of
course
approaches the a periodic sick so
the resulting equation that we get outta
the original for a series synthesis
equation
is the equation
that I indicate down here X if T
synthesized interns all this
integral which is what the forty a
series approaches
as Omega 0 goes to zero and
we had previously that XO maker
was in fact an envelope function
and we have then the corresponding for
EA transform analysis equation
which tells us how we arrive at that
envelope
interns love accept T okay so
we now have and analysis equation and
synthesis equation which in effect
expresses 4s
how to build XFT interns or
if into tears and we finally space
complex exponentials
the strategy to review it
and which I'd like to illustrate with
a succession of overlays was
to begin up
with are a periodic signal as
I indicate here
and then reconstructed from that a
periodic signal
and in this periodic signal has a forty
a series
and we express the for a series
coefficients if this
as samples all an envelope function
the envelope function is what I indicate
on the curve below
so this is the envelope above the 40 a
series coefficients
for example if the period t0
was four times t1 in the 4a series
coefficients
that we would end up with is this set
samples of the and below if
instead we double that period
then the Fourier series coefficients
that we end up with
are more finally space
and as t0
continues to increase we get more and
more
finally space samples love this envelope
function
and as t0 goes to infinity in fact what
we get
is every single point on the envelope
and that provides is
with the representation for
the a periodic sick let me just to
really emphasize the point
show this example once again but now
let's look at it dynamically on the
computer display
so here we have the square wave in below
it
the for a series coefficients we now
want to look at the for a series
coefficients
as the period at the square wave starts
to increase
and what we see is that these look
like samples love an envelope
and in fact the envelope for the Fourier
series coefficients
is shown in the bottom trace and
emphasize in fact that it is the
envelope
let's superimpose it on top of the
Fourier series coefficients that we've
generated so far
okay now let's increase the period
even further and we'll see the for a
series
coefficients billion under that
envelope function even more and in fact
as the period gets large enough what we
begin to get a sense love is
that we're sampling more and more
finally
this and below and in fact in the limit
as the period goes off to infinity
the samples basically will represent
every
single point on the envelope well this
is about as far as you want to go
let's once again plot the envelope
function
and again to emphasize that we've
generated samples a bad
let superimpose that on the forty a
series coefficients
okay so what we have then is
now are forty-a transform
representation the continuous time
Fourier transform
with the synthesis equation
expressed as an integral as they've
indicated here
and this integral is what
the four th series some went to
as we let the period go to infinity
where the frequency go to zero the
corresponding
analysis equation which we have here the
analysis equation
being the expression for the on below
up to 40 a series coefficients for the
periodically
replicated signal and in shorthand
notation
we would think affects if T
and its Fourier transform as a pair
as i've indicated here and the Fourier
transform
as will emphasize in several examples
and certainly
as is consistent with the forty a series
is
a complex value function even when
accepting israel's so would accept the
real
we end up with the 48 transform which is
a complex function
just as the for you series coefficients
were complex
for real value time function
so we could alternatively as with the 4e
a series
express the Fourier transform it turns
love its real part an imaginary part
or alternatively interns
love its magnet to and its angle
all right now let's look at an example
love a time function and its Fourier
transform
and so let's consider
an example which in fact is an example
worked out in the tax that's
example 4.7 tax and missus are all
familiar friend
the exponential
its Fourier transform is the integral
from minus infinity plus infinity X
thirty
either the minus J Omega TDT and
so if we substitute in exit to the and
combine these two exponentials together
these two exponentials
combined are he to the minus the
times a-plus jail mega and
if we carry out the integration
love this we end up with the expression
indicated here and provided
now in this is important provided
that a is greater than 0
and at the upper limit this exponential
become 0
at the lower limit of course it's one
and so
what we have finally is the for the
Fourier transform expression one over a
plus
jail make
okay now this Fourier transform as i
indicated
is a complex valued function let's just
take a look at what it looks like
graphically
we have
the expression the Fourier transform
pair
either the minus eighty times a step and
its forty-eight transformers one over
a place J Omega and I indicated
dead that's true for a greater than 0
now in the expression that we just
worked out
if a is less than 0 in fact the
the expression doesn't converge the
to the -84 a negative
as he goes to infinity blows up
and so in fact the 48 transform doesn't
converge
in the case except for the case were a
is greater than 0
and in fact there's a more detailed
discussion of convergence issues in the
tax
the convergence issues are very much the
same
the Fourier transform as they are for
the four th series in fact that's not
surprising because
we develop the Fourier transform out of
consideration
for you series so the convergence
conditions as you'll see as you refer a
detailed
tax relate to whether the time function
is
absolutely integral under one set of
conditions
and square integrable under another set
of conditions
okay now if we plot the Fourier
transform
let's first consider the shape at the
time function
and as i indicated way restricting the
so that the exponential factor is
positive in other words you the -80
detainees as he goes to infinity the
magnitude
or the for EA transform
is as i indicate here and
the phase below it and
think there are a number of things that
we can see about
the magnitude and phase
the 48 transform for this example which
in fact we'll see
in the next lecture are properties that
apply more generally
for example the fact that the 48
transform magnitude is an even function
frequency and the phase is an odd
function of frequency
now let me also draw your attention
so the fact there'd on this curve we
have
both positive frequencies and negative
frequencies
in other words in our expression for the
48 transform
we've it requires both or make a
positive
and Omega negative this of course was
exactly the same in the case
the for a series and the reason you
should
recalling keep in mind is related to the
fact that we're building our signals
out of complex exponentials which
require both
positive values have Omega and negative
values Omega alternatively if we chose
another representation which turns and
occasionally to be much more difficult
namely sines and cosines that we would
in fact
only consider positive frequencies so
it's important to keep in mind
that in our case both with the for a
series in the 48 transform
we deal and require both positive and
negative frequencies
in order to build their signals
now in the graphical representation that
I shown here
I've chosen a linear amplitude scale
and a linear frequency scale and thats
one
graphical representation the Fourier
transform
that will typically use is another one
that very commonly arises and
which all just briefly indicate for this
example
and that is was referred to
as a boat imply in which the
magnet to is displayed on a large
amplitude in like frequency scale
in the phase is displayed on a lock
frequency scale
let me show you what I me here is
the general expression for the boat
reply body plot
expresses 4s the amp with two interns
the longer them to the base 10 the
magnitude
and it also expresses the angle in both
cases
express as as a function
love a logarithmic speak with yes so
here is the amplitude
as i've displayed at and
this is a log magnitude scale a
logarithmic
frequency scale as indicated by the fact
that as we move
include equal increments along this axis
we change
frequency by a factor 10 and
similarly what we
have is a display for the phase again
on a light frequency scale and I
indicated
dead there is a symmetry to the Fourier
transform
and so in fact we can infer from this
particular picture
what it looks like to the negative
frequencies as well as for the positive
returns
okay now
what we've
done so far is to develop
the for EA transform on the basis
the Fourier transform it a periodic
signal on the basis
periodically repeating it and
recognizing
that the for a series coefficients are
samples of an envelope
on an envelope and that these become
more finally space
as frequency increases and in fact
we can go back to are
original equation
in which we developed an envelope
function
and what we had indicated
is dead the 4e a series
coefficients where samples of this
envelope
we then
to find this envelope as
the Fourier transform all this a
periodic signal so
that provided us with the way and it was
a mechanism
for getting a representation for a
periodic sick
now suppose that we have instead
a periodic signal are there in fact
some statements that we can make about
how the Fourier series coefficients
that are related to the Fourier
transform of something well
in fact this statement tells us
exactly how to do that what this
statement says
is that in fact the forty a series
coefficients
our samples all the four EA transform
up one period so if
we now consider
a periodic signal weekend in fact
get before a series coefficients that
periodic signal
by considering the Fourier transform
above one period said another way the 4e
a series coefficients
are proportional samples on the Fourier
transform
one period so if we consider this
a periodic signal computer its Fourier
transform
and selected these
samples that I indicate here
namely samples equally spaced in omega
in by multiples are integer multiples
love Omega 0 then in fact
those would be the story a series
coefficients
so we can go back to
are example previously
with that involved the
square wave and now
in this case we could argue that if in
fact
it was the periodic signal that we
started with
we could get the 40 series coefficients
that by thinking about
the four EA transform above one period
which I indicate here and then
the 48 series coefficients other
periodic signal
in fact are the appropriate set
samples of this envelope
alright now we have away
love getting the for a series
coefficients
from the Fourier transform one period we
originally derived
the Fourier transform one period from
the 48 series
what would in fact be nice
is if we could incorporate before a
series
in the Fourier transform within a common
framework
and in fact it turns out dead there
is a very convenient way of doing that
almost by definition
essentially
if we consider what the equation
for the synthesis looks like in both
cases we
can in effect define of four EA
transform
for the periodic signal which we know is
represented by its for a series
coefficients we can define
48 transform and the definition of the
Fourier transform
is as an impulse train where the
coefficients in the impulse train
are proportional with the
proportionality factor
25 for more less a bookkeeping reason
proportional to the forty a series
coefficients
and the validity of this is
more or less can be seen
essentially by substitution specifically
here is then the
synthesis equation for the four EA
transform
if we substitute this definition for the
four th chance for the periodic signal
into this expression then when we do the
appropriate bookkeeping
and interchange the order some Asian and
integration
the in polls integrates out to
the exponential factor that we want so
we have the exponential factor we have
the for a series coefficients
the two pies take care of each other and
what we're left with
is the synthesis equation for
a periodic signal in terms of the
Fourier transform foreign it interns
love it's for a series coefficients
right now
we can just see this interns
love a simple example if we
consider the example love a symmetric
square wave
then in effect what we're saying is that
for this symmetric square wave this has
set up for a series coefficients which
we work that previously
and which I indicate on this figure
with a bar graph and really all that
were saying
is there whereas these free a series
coefficients our index
on an integer variable K and their bars
not impulses
if we simply redefine or define
the Fourier transform love the periodic
signal
as an impulse train where the weights at
the impulses
are to Paul II times the
correspondent for a series coefficients
and
this in fact is what we would use as the
four EA
transform love the periodic sick
okay now we've kind of gone back and
forth
on and maybe even it might seem
likely going around in circles so let me
just
try to summarize the various
relationships
and steps that we've gone through
keeping in mind that
one of our objectives was first to
develop
representation for a periodic signals
and then attempt to
incorporate within one framework both
periodic
in a periodic signals
we began with
and a periodic signal
and the strategy was to develop
for your representation by constructing
periodic signal for which that was one
period
in and then we let the period go to
infinity as
I indicate here so we have and a
periodic signal
we construct a periodic signal
extol dirty for which one period
is the a periodic signal X still dirty
the periodic signal has a forty a series
and as its period increases
that approaches the a periodic signal
and
the forty a series of that approaches
the 48 transform
all the original a periodic sick so
that was the first step that we took
now the second thing that we recognize
is dead
once we have the concept to the 48
transform
we can in fact relate the Fourier series
coefficients
to the 48 transform one period
so the second statement that we made was
dead
if in fact we're trying to represent a
periodic signal
we can get the 40 series coefficients
have that
by computing the for EA transform
one period and then
samples that for EA transform are
in fact the 4e series coefficients for
the periodic sick
okay then the third step that we took
was
to inquire as to whether they're is a
Fourier transform
that can appropriately be defined for
the periodic signal in the mechanism for
doing that
was to recognize that if we simply to
find the Fourier transform
the periodic signal as an impulse train
where the in polls
fights or areas for proportional to the
for a series coefficients
then in fact the Fourier transform
synthesis equation reduced to
before you see recent this equation so
the third step
then was with a periodic signal
the 48 transform that periodic signal
defined as an impulse train with the
heights or areas the impulses are
proportional to the forty a series
coefficients
provides us with the mechanism for
combining together the concepts war
notation love before you a series and
Fourier transform so
if we just took I E very simple example
here is an example in which
we have and a periodic signal
which is just an impulse and its
for EA transform is just a constant
we can think other periodic signal
associated with this which is this
signal
periodically replicated in with the
spacing t0
the Fourier transform love this is a
constant
and this of course has a forty a series
representation
so the Fourier transform or
the original in polls is just a constant
the Fourier transform
love the periodic signal is
an impulse train where the heights at
the impulses
are proportional to the forty a series
coefficients
and of course we could previously have
computed
the forty a series coefficients to that
imposed strain
and those for a series coefficients are
as I've shown here
so on both these cases these in effect
represent just a change in notation
we're here we have a bar graph in here
we have been imposed strain
and both at the is simply represent
samples of what we have above
which is the for EA transform
love the original a periodic sick
okay now once again I suspect that kinda
moving back and forth and and trying to
straighten out when we're talking about
periodic in a periodic signals
may require a little mental gymnastics
initially
basically what we try to do is
incorporate within one framework
representation for both
a periodic and and periodic signals in
the Fourier transform
provides us with a mechanism to do that
in the next lecture I'll continue with
the discussion
or the continuous-time for EA transform
in particular focusing
on a number of its properties summer
which we've already seen namely the
symmetry properties
we'll see lots of other properties that
relate
of course both to the 48 transform and
to the for users
thank you