the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU Horan
the
the in
in
the
are in
for in discussing the sampling theorem
we saw date for a ban limited signal
which is sampled
at a frequency that that is at least
twice the highest frequency
we can implement exact reconstruction
of the original signal by low-pass
filtering
an impulse train whose areas are
identical to the sample values
well essentially this low pass filtering
operation provides for us and
interpolation
in between the sample values in other
words the output to the low-pass filter
in fact
is a continuous curve which
fits between a sample values some
continuous function
now I'm sure that many have you are
familiar with other kinds of
interpolation that we could potentially
provide
in between sample values and in fact in
today's lecture
why I would like to do is first the ball
develop the interpretation
all the reconstruction as an
interpolation process
and then also see how this
exact interpolation using a low-pass
filter
relates to other kinds of interpolation
such as linear interpolation that you
may already be familiar with
well to begin let's again review
what the overall system is for exact
reconstruction
sampling and reconstruction and so let
me remind you that
the overall system for sampling and D
sampling a reconstruction is as i
indicate here
the sampling process consists love
multiplying by an impulse train and then
the reconstruction process
corresponds the processing that impulse
train with
a low-pass filter so if the
spectrum of the original signal
is what I indicate in this diagram
then after sampling with an impulse
train
that spectrum is replicated and
this replicated spectrum for
reconstruction
is then processed through a low-pass
filter
and so in fact if this frequency
response
is an idea low-pass filter as i
indicated on the diagram below
then multiplying the
spectrum of the sample signal by this
extracts 4s
just the portion all
the spectrum centered around the origin
and what we're left with then is the
spectrum finally of the reconstructed
signal
which for the case of an idea low-pass
filter
is exactly equal to the spectrum of the
original signal
now that is the
frequency domain picture
all the sampling and reconstruction
let's also look at
basically the same process but let's
examine it now
in the time domain well in the time
domain
what we have is are original signal
multiply it by an impulse train and
this then is the sampled
signal or the impulse train whose areas
are equal to the sample values
and because it the fact that this is an
impulse train
in fact we can take this term
inside the summation
and of course what counts about except
Ian this expression
is just as bad use at the sampling
instants
which are displaced in time by capital T
and so
to what we can to quietly right is the
expression for the impulse train samples
or
imposed strain of samples as i've
indicated here
simply an imposed strain whose areas are
the sample bad
now in the reconstruction we process
that impulse train with a low-pass
filter that's the basic notion of the
reconstruction
and so in the time domain be
reconstructed signal
is related to the imposed strain of
samples
through a convolution with the filter
impulse response
and carrying out this convolution since
this is just the train of pulses in
effect what happens in this convolution
is dead this impulse response gets
reproduced at each of the locations 0
the impulses index a PFD with the
appropriate area
and finally then in the time domain the
reconstructed signal
is simply a linear combination
love shifted versions of the impulse
response
with amplitudes Witcher the sample
values
and so this expression in fact and is
our basic
reconstruction expression in the time
domain
well in terms of a diagram
we can think of the original waveform
as I've shown here and
the red arrows denote be
sampled waveform or the train
love impulses whose amplitude are
the sample values up the original
continuous-time signal and
then I've shown here it what might be a
typical impulse response
particularly typical in the case where
we're talking about reconstruction with
an ideal 0 pass filter
now what happens in the reconstruction
is that the convolution love these
impulses with this impulse response
means that in the reconstruction
we superimpose wanted these impulse
responses whatever the filter IPO's
response happens to be
at each of these time instants and in
doing that
then those are added up and that gives
us the total reconstructed signal
of course for the case in which the
filter is an ideal
low-pass filter then what we know is
that in that case
the impulse response is on the form of a
sync function
but generally we may want to consider
other kinds of impulse responses and so
in fact
the interpolating impulse response
may have and will have is this
discussion goes along some different
shapes
now what I'd like to do is illustrator
demonstrate this process
love all affectively doing the
interpolation
by replacing each of the impulses
by an appropriate interpolating impulse
response and adding the stop
and I'd like to do this with a computer
movie that we generated
and what you're seeing the computer
movie is
essentially original way for which is a
continuous curve
and then below that in the movie
is a train samples
and then below that will be the
reconstructed signal and the
reconstruction
will be carried out by showing the
location of the impulse response as it
moves along in the way form
and then the reconstructed kurt is
simply the summation of those is that
impulse response moves along
so what you'll see then is an impulse
response like this for the particular
case
love and idea low-pass filter for the
reconstruction
an impulse response like this place
successively at the locations love
these impulses and that is the
convolution process
and below that then will be the
summation if these
and the summation up those will then be
the reconstructed signal
so let's take a look at first of all
that reconstruction
where the impulse response corresponds
to the impulse response
have an idea low-pass filter shown here
first
is the continuous-time signal which
we want to sample and then reconstruct
using
fan limited interpolation or
equivalently
idea low-pass filtering on the set of
samples
so the first step then is the sample
this continuous time signal
and we see here now the set of samples
and superimposed on the samples are the
original continuous 5 signal
to focus on the fact that those are
samples are the top curve
let's now remove the continuous-time
envelope with the samples and it's this
set of samples that we then want to use
for the reconstruction
the reconstruction process interpreted
as interpolation
consists of replacing each sample with a
sin x over X function
and so let's first consider the sample
at equal 0 and here is the
interpolating sin x over X function
Associated
with that sample now the more general
process then is to
place a sin x over expulsion at the time
location of each sample and superimpose
those
let's begin that process at the
left-hand and
the set of samples and in the bottom
curve
will build up the reconstruction as
those sin x over X functions
are added together so we begin with the
left hand sample and we see their the
sin x over X function
on the bottom curve then is the first
step in the reconstruction
we now have the sin x over X function
associated with the second sample
let's add that in now we move on
to the third sample and that sin x over
X function
is added in
continuing on the next
sample generates a sin x over X function
which is superimposed on the result that
we've accumulated
so far and now let's just
speed up the process will move on to the
fifth sample
add that in the sect sample add that in
and continue on through the set of
samples and
keep in mind the fact that basically
what we're doing explicitly here
is the convolution up the impulse train
with a sin x over X function
and because the set of samples that we
started with
where samples haven't exactly been
limited function
what we are reconstructing exactly
is the original continuous-time signal
that we have on the top trace
okay so that then
kinda gives you the picture above doing
interpolation by replacing the impulses
by a continuous curve and that's the way
we're fitting
a continuous curve to the original
impulse train and let me stress
that this reconstruction process
by putting the impulses through
a filter the reconstruction process
follows this relationship whether or not
this impulse response in fact
corresponds to an ideal ok pass filter
what this expression always says is dead
reconstructing this way
corresponds to replacing the impulses
by a shift in impulse response with an
effort to
dead is an amplitude corresponding to
the sample value now
be kinda reconstruction dead we've just
talked about and the ideal
reconstruction
is often referred to as band limited
interpolation because for interpolating
in between the samples
by making the assumption that the
signals ban limited
and using the impulse response for an
idea low-pass filter
which has a cutoff frequency consistent
with
the soon band with for the signal so if
we look
here for example at the impulse train
then in the demonstration that you just
saw
we built up the reconstructed curve by
replacing each of these impulses
with the sync function and the some of
those
built up the reconstruct the curve well
there are lots of other kinds of
interpolation
dead are perhaps maybe not as exact
by often easier to implement and what
I'd like to do is focus our attention on
to appease
one of these the first that I want to
mention is what's referred to as a
zero-order hold
where in effect we do the interpolation
in between these
sample values by simply holding the
sample value
until the next sampling instant and the
reconstruction
that we end up with in that that case
will look something like this:
it's a staircase or boxcar kinda
function
where we've simply held the sample value
until the next sampling instant and then
replaced by that value held until the
next sampling instant et cetera
now that's one kinda interpolation
another kinda very common interpolation
is
what's referred to as linear
interpolation we simply fit
a straight line between the sample
values and in that case
the cut be type reconstruction that we
would get
would look something like I indicate
here where we take a sample value
and the following sample value and
simply fit interpolated curve between
them
which is a straight line now
interestingly in fact both the
zero-order hold
and the linear interpolation which is
often referred to as a first-order hold
can also
be either implemented or interpreted
both implemented interpreted
in the context of the equation that we
just develop
in particular the processing I'll the
imposed strain of samples by
a linear time-invariant filter
specifically
if we consider a
system where the impulse response
is a rectangular function
then in fact if
we processed the train if samples
through a filter with this impulse
response exactly
the reconstruction that we would get is
what I've shown here
alternatively if we chose an impulse
response
which was a triangular
impulse response then
what in effect happens is that each of
these impulses
activates this triangle
and when we add up those triangles at
successive locations in fact
what we generate is this linear
interpolation
so what this says in fact is dead
either a zero-order hold
which holds the value or linear
interpolation
can likewise be interpreted as a process
love convolved thing the impulse trainer
samples
with inappropriate filter impulse
response
well what I'd like to do is demonstrate
as we did with the ban limit
interpolation or
these sink interpolation is sometimes
called interplay with a sin x over axe
let me now show the process first the
ball
where we have a zero-order hold
as corresponding to this impulse
response
in which case we'll see basically the
same process as we saw your
in the computer-generated movie
previously
but now rather than a sync function
replacing
each of these impulses will have a
rectangular function
that will generate then are
approximation which is a zero-order hold
and following that will do exactly the
same thing with the same way form
using a first-order hold or a triangular
impulse response
in which case well we'll see again is
that as the triangle moves along here
and we build up the running some or the
convolution
then will in fact fit the original curve
with a linear curve soul now let's
again look at that remembering that at
the top will see
the original continuous curve exactly
the one that we had before
below it the set of samples together
with
the impulse response moving along and
then finally below that
the accumulation of those impulse
responses work with only
the convolution or equivalent Lee the
reconstruction
so we have the same continuous-time
signal that we use previously with
ban limited interpolation and in this
case
now we want to sample and then
interpolate first for the zero-order
hold
and then with the first-order whole so
the first step then
is the sample the continuous-time signal
and we show here at the set of samples
once again
superimposed on which we have the
continuous-time signal
which of course is exactly the same
curve as
we have in the top well let's
remove that envelope so that we focus
attention
on the samples that were using to
interpolate
any interpolation process consists love
replacing each sample
by a rectangular signal
whose amplitude is equal to the sample
size
so let's put one first of all at equal 0
Associated
with that sample
and that then would be the interpolating
rectangle associated with the sample at
equal 0
now to build up the interpolation what
will have is one of those that each
sample time and those are
added together will start that process
as we did before
at the left hand and that the set of
samples
and build the interpolating signal on
the bottom so
with the left hand sample we have first
the rectangle associated with that that
shown
now on the bottom curve we now
have a senator plating rectangle with
the second
sample that gets headed into the bottom
curve
similarly and interpolating rectangle
for the zero-order hold
with the third sample we had bad in to
the bottom curve
and as we proceed we're building a
staircase approximation
on to the next sample that gets added in
as we see the air and now lets speed up
the process
and we'll see the staircase
approximation
building up and notice in this case
as in the previous case that what we're
basically watching dynamically
is the convolution love the imposed
strain of samples
with the impulse response the
interpolating filter
which in this particular case is just a
rectangular Paul's
and so this staircase approximation that
we're generating
is the zero-order hold interpolation
between the samples I love the
ban limited signal which is at the top
now let's do the same thing with the
first-order whole so in this case
we want to interpolate using a
triangular impulse response
rather than the sin x over X or
rectangular impulse responses that we
showed previously
so first let's say with the sample it
equals 0
we would replace that with a triangular
interpolating function and more
generally
each in polls or sample is replaced with
a triangular
interpolating function of the height
equal to the sample height
and these are superposed to generate the
linear interpolation
will begin this process with the
leftmost
sample and will build the superposition
below and the bottom curve so here
is the interpolating triangle for the
leftmost sample and now it's reproduced
below
with the second sample we have an
interpolating triangle which is added
into the bottom
curve and now on to the third sample
and again that interpolating triangle
will be added onto
the curve that we've developed so far
and now on to the next sample
we had that in there will speed up the
process
and as we proceed through
we are building basically a linear
interpolation
in between the sample points
a sexually corresponding to if one wants
to think of it this way connecting the
dots
and what you're watching once again is
essentially the convolution process
involving the impulse train with the
impulse response
the interpolating filter and what we're
generating then
is a linear approximation
to the fam limited continuous-time curve
at the top
okay so what we have then is
several other kinds of interpolation
which
fit within the same context as
exact ban limit interpolation one being
interpolation in the time domain with an
impulse response which is a rectangle
the second being interpolation in the
time domain
with an impulse response which is a
triangle
and in fact its interesting to also
look at the relationship between at and
ban limit interpolation
look at it specifically in the frequency
domain
well in the frequency-domain
what we know of course is dead for exact
interpolation
what we want as our interpolating filter
is an ideal Lopez filter
now keep in mind by the way that an idea
low-pass filter is an abstraction is a
stress several times in the past an idea
low-pass filter
is a9 causal filter and in fact infinite
extent which is
one of the reasons why in any case we
would you some approximation to it
but here what we have is the
exact interpolating filter
and that corresponds to an ideal 0 pass
filter
if instead we carried out the
interpolation
using the zero-order hold the zero-order
hold has a
rectangular impulse response and that
means in the frequency domain
its frequency response is of the form
love
a sync function or sin x over iraq's
and so this in fact when we're doing the
reconstruction
with a zero-order hold is The Associated
frequency response
now notice that it does some approximate
Lopez filtering but of course
it has significant it permits
significant energy
outside the pass band at the filter
well instead the zero-order hold if we
use the first-order hold corresponding
to the triangular impulse response
in that case then in the frequency
domain The Associated
frequency response would be the forty a
transformer the triangle
and the Fourier transform a triangle is
a sin squared
X over X where'd kinda function
and so in that case what we would have
for the frequency response associated
with the first-order hold
is a frequency response as I show here
and the fact dead that there's somewhat
more attenuation
outside the pass band at the ideal
filter
is what suggests in fact dead the
first-order hold or linear interpolation
gives us a somewhat smoother
approximation to the original
signal then the zero-order hold does
and so in fact just to compare these two
we can see that here is
the ideal filter here is
the zero-order hold corresponding to
generating a boxcar kinda reconstruction
and here is the first order hold
corresponding to a linear interpolation
now in fact in many sampling systems
in any sampling system really we need to
use some approximation
to the low-pass filter and very often in
fact
what is done in many sampling systems is
the first to use
just a zero-order hold and then follow
the zero-order hold
with some additional 0 pass filtering
well to illustrate some with these ideas
and the notion love doing reconstruction
with a zero-order hold a first-order
hold and then in fact
are ending to that some additional 0
pass filtering
what I'd like to do is is demonstrator
illustrate
sampling and interpolation in the
context love some images
image of course is a two-dimensional
signal the
the independent variables are spatial
variables not time variables
and of course we can sample in both or
the spatial dimensions both in X&Y
and were chosen as so
a possibly appropriate choice for
an image is again our friend and
colleague JBJ 48
so let's begin with the original image
which we then
want to sample and reconstruct and a
sampling is done by
effectively multiplying by appalls both
horizontally and vertically
the sample picture is then the next one
that I show and as you can see this
corresponds in effect
to extracting small brightness elements
I did the original image in fact
let's look in a little closer and what
you can see essentially is that
well we have of course tonight impulses
spatially but
small spatial pillars dead
implement the sampling for us okay now
going back to the original sample
picture
we know that a picture can be
reconstructed by low-pass filtering from
the samples and in fact
we can do that optically in this case by
simply d focusing the camera
and when we do that what happens is that
we smear out the picture
or affectively convolved the impulses
with the point spread function of the
optical system
an this then is not too bad a
reconstruction
so thats a an approximate reconstruction
and focusing back now
what we have again is the sample picture
now these images are in fact a can often
of
a computer display and a common
procedure in
computer-generated are displayed image
is is in fact
the use of a zero-order hold and if the
sampling rate is high enough
then that actually works reasonably well
so now
let's look at the result of applying a
zero-order hold
to the sampled image that I
just showed
the zero-order hold corresponds to
replacing the impulses by
rectangles and you can see that what
that generates
is a mosaic affect as you would
expect and in fact let's going a little
closer and
emphasize the mosaic affect you can see
that essentially where they were
impulses previously
there are now rectangles with those
brightness values
a very common procedure with
computer-generated images is the first
20 order holders we've done here
and then follow that with some
additional ok pass filtering and in fact
we can do that low pass filtering now
again by D focusing the camera
and you can't begin to see
dead with the zero-order all plus the
low-pass filtering the reconstruction is
not that bad
well let's go back to the full
image with the zero-order hold
and again now the effective low pass
filter I will be
somewhat better and let's tee focus
again year
and you can begin to see that this is
a reasonable reconstruction with the
mosaic
in fact with this back in focus you can
apply your own low-pass filtering to it
either by squinting
or if you have the right or wrong kind
of my classes either taking them off for
putting them on
now in addition to the zero-order hold
weekend of course apply a first-order
hold and that would
correspond to replacing the impulses
instead of with rectangles as we have
here
replacing them with triangles an
so now let's take a look at the result
all a first-order hold applied to the
original samples
and you can see now that the
reconstruction is somewhat smoother
because the fact that we're using an
impulse response
that somewhat smoother or a
corresponding frequency response that
has a sharper cut off
i emphasize again that this is a
somewhat low pass filtered version of
the original because
we have under sampled some what
spatially
to bring out the point that I want to
illustrate
okay to emphasize these effects
even more what I'd like to do is go
through
basically the same sequence again but in
this case what we'll do
is double the sample spacing both
horizontal horizontally and vertically
this of course means there will be even
more highly under sampled been
in the ones that I preview show
previously showed and so the result of
the reconstructions with some low pass
filtering
will be a much more low-pass filtered
image
so we now have the sample picture but
I've now under sampled considerably
more and you can see the effect of the
sampling
and if we now apply is zero-order hold
to this picture we will again get a
mosaic and lets
look at that and that mosaic of course
looks
even block here than the original and
again emphasizes the fact that the
zero-order hold
simply corresponds to filling in squares
or replacing the impulses
by squares with the corresponding
brightness
values finally if we instead of a
zero-order hold
use a first-order hold corresponding to
two-dimensional triangles in places
in place at these original blocks what
we get is
the next image and that again is a
smoother reconstruction consistent with
the fact that the triangles are smoother
than the rectangles
again i emphasize that this looks so
highly low-pass filtered
because of the fact that we've under
sampled so severely
to essentially emphasize the effect
as I mentioned the images that we
just looked at were taken from a
computer although
because the original images were
continuous-time
images or more specifically continuous
space that is the independent variable
is a spatial variable
now computer processing
love signals pictures speech or whatever
the signals are
is very important and useful because
it offers a lot of flexibility and in
fact the kinds of things that I showed
these pictures
would have been very hard to do without
in fact doing computer processing
well in computer processing %uh any kind
of signal
basically what's required is dead
we do the processing in the context of
discrete-time signals and discrete-time
processing
because it the fact dead a computer is
run off the clock
and essentially things happen in the
computer
in a as a sequence of numbers and as a
sequence of events
well it turns out dead the sampling
theorem in fact as i've indicated
previously
provides us with a very nice mechanism
for converting are continuous-time
signals
into discrete-time signals for example
for computer processing
or in fact if it's not a computer for
some other kind of discrete-time or
perhaps digital processing
well the basic idea as i've indicated
previously
is to carry out discreet I processing
of continuous-time signals by
first converting the continuous-time
signal
to a discrete-time signal carry out
the appropriate discrete-time processing
love the discrete-time signal and then
after we're done with that process
saying
converting from the discrete-time
sequence
back to a continuous-time signal
corresponding to the output that we have
here
well in the remainder this lecture what
I'd like to analyze
is the first step in that process namely
the conversion
from a continuous-time signal to a
discrete-time signal
and understand how the
to relate both in the time domain in the
frequency domain
and in the next lecture will be
analyzing and demonstrating
the overall system including some
intermediate processing
so be first step in the process
is the conversion from a continuous-time
signal
to a discrete-time signal and that can
be thought of as a process that involves
two steps although in practical terms it
may not be implemented specifically
as these two steps the two steps are
to first convert from the
continuous-time
for continuous-time continuous signal
to an impulse train through a sampling
process
and then to convert
that impulse train to a discrete-time
sequence
and the discrete-time sequence exit then
is simply then a sequence a bad news
which are the samples all the
continuous-time signal
and as we'll see as we walk through this
basically this step
going from the impulse train to the
sequence
corresponds principally to worry
labeling staff where
we pic of the impulse bad news
and use those as the sequence values
up for the discrete-time signal so
what I'd like to do as a first step in
understanding this process
is to analyze it in particular with our
attention focused on trying to
understand
what the relationship is in the
frequency domain
between the discrete-time Fourier
transform
love the sequence discrete-time signal
and the continuous-time 48 transform
love the original on sampled and then
the sampled signal so let's go through
that
and in particular
what we have is a process where the
continuous-time signal
is of course modulator multiplied
by an impulse train and that gives us
then
another continuous-time signal we're
still in the continuous time domain
it gives us another continuous-time
signal which is an impulse train
and in fact we've gone through this
analysis
previously and what we have is
this multiplication or taking this term
inside
the summation and recognizing that the
impulse train
is is simply an impulse train
with areas above the impulses which
are the samples above the
continuous-time function
we can then carry out the analysis in
the frequency domain
now in the time domain we have a
multiplication process so in the
frequency domain
we have a convolution above the Fourier
transform
love the continuous-time signal the
original signal
and the Fourier transform of the impulse
train which is itself an impulse train
so in the frequency domain then the 48
transform
of the sampled signal which is an
impulse train
is the convolution %uh the Fourier
transform up the sampling
function PFT and the Fourier transform
of the sampled signal
since the sampling signal is a periodic
imposed strain
its Fourier transform is an impulse
train
and consequently carrying out this
convolution
in effect says that this for EA
transform
simply gets replicated at each of the
locations of these impulses
and finally what we end up with an
is a 48 transform after
the sampling process which is
the original for EA transform love the
continuous
signal but and it to itself
shifted by integer multiples
above the sampling frequency and so this
is the basic equation then
that tells us in the frequency domain
what happens
through the first part all this two-step
process
now I emphasize that is a two-step
process the first process
is sampling where we're still
essentially
in the continuous-time world the next
step
is essentially a relabeling process
where we convert that impulse train
simply to a sequence
so let's look at the next step
the next step is to take the impulse
train and converted
through a process to sequence
and the sequence values are simply then
samples 0 the original continuous signal
and so now we
can analyze this and what we want to
relate
is the discrete-time Fourier transform
love this and the continuous 540 a
transformer
this or in fact that continues type for
a transformer affects up to you
safety okay
well we have the imposed strain
and its Fourier transform we can
get by simply evaluating for EA
transform
and since the Fourier transform love
this
since this corresponds to an impulse
train the 48 transformed by the time we
change them something in it rolls
will then have this in paul's replace
524 e a transformer the shift in polls
which is this exponential factor so this
expression
is before a transformer the impulse
train
the continuous time Fourier transform
and alternatively
we can look at the Fourier transform all
the sequence and this of course is
a discrete-time Fourier transform
so we have the continuous time Fourier
transform the imposed strain
we have the discrete-time Fourier
transform the sequence
and now we want to look at how those to
relate
well it pretty much falls out of just
comparing these two summations
in particular this term and this term
are identical that's just the relabeling
Nov all what the sequence values are
and notice that when we compare these
exponential factors
they're identical as long as we
associate capital Omega
with little or may get times capital T
in other words
if we were to replace here capital may
go by a little Omega
times capital T and replace exhibition
by excessive see a venti in this
expression
would be identical to this expression
so in fact these two are equal
where a relabeling or with the
transformation between small Megan
capital make
and so in fact then the relationship
that we have
is that the discrete-time Fourier
transform are
the sequence of samples
is equal to the continuous time Fourier
transform
all the impulse strain of samples
where we associate the continuous-time
frequency variable
and the discrete-time pic script
frequency variable through
a frequency scaling as i indicate here
or said another way
the discrete-time spectrum is the
continuous I spectrum of the samples
with capital mate with small Omega
replaced by capital Omega
divided by capital T
fight so we have then this two-step
process
the first step is taking the
continuous-time signal
sampling with it sampling it with an
impulse train
in the frequency domain that corresponds
to
replicating the four EA transform
all the original continuous-time signals
the second step is relabeling Matt
in effect turning it into a sequence and
what that does in the frequency domain
is provide us
with a rescaling if the frequency axis
or as we'll see
a frequency normalization which is
associated with the corresponding time
normalization
in the time domain well let's look at
those statements a little more
specifically
when I show here it is the original
continuous-time signal
and then below it is
the sampled signal and these two
are signals in the continuous-time
domain
now what is the conversion from this
impulse train
to a sequence well it simply taking
these in polls areas are bad news the
sample values
and relabeling them in effect is a show
below
relabeling them as sequence values
and essentially I'm now replacing
the impulse by the designation of a
sequence value
that's one step but the other important
step to focus on
is dead whereas in the impulse trainees
impulses are spaced
by integer multiples of the sampling
period capital T
in the sequence of course because if the
way that we
label sequences these are always space
by
simply integer multiples of 1
so in effect you could say that the step
in going from here
to hear corresponds to normalizing out
in the time domain
the sampling period capital T
to stress that another way if the
sampling period were doubled
so there'd in this picture this spacing
stretched out by a factor of two
nevertheless in the discrete-time
for the discrete-time signal the spacing
would remain as one
and essentially its the
envelope of those sequence values
that would then get contracts compressed
in time
so you can think all the step in going
from the impulse train to the samples
as a sexually a time normalization
now let's look at this in the frequency
domain in the frequency domain
what we have is the Fourier transform of
our original continuous
signal after sampling with an impulse
train
this spectrum retains its shape
him but is replicated at integer
multiples of the sampling frequency to
pry over capital T
as i indicated here now
we know that a discrete-time spectrum
must be periodic and frequency with a
period of two pi
here we have the periodicity but it's
not periodic with period have to pry
its periodic with period which is equal
to the sampling frequency
however in converting from the samples
to the sequence values and we go through
another step
what the other step the other step is a
time normalization
where we take the impulses which your
space by the sampling period
and we rescale at essentially in the
time domain
to a space in which is unity so we're
dividing out
in the time domain by a
by a factor which is
equal to the sampling period well
dividing out in the time domain by
capital T would correspond to
multiplying in the frequency domain the
frequency axis by capital T and indeed
what happens is dead in going from the
imposed strain
to the sequence values we now rescale
this axis so that in fact
the axis gets stretched by capital T
and the frequency which corresponded to
2pi over capital T
now gets re normalized 22 part
so just looking at this again and
perhaps with the overall picture
in the time domain we've gone from a
continuous curve
two samples relabel those and in effect
implemented a time normalization
correspondingly in the frequency domain
we
have replicated the spectrum through the
initial sampling process
and then rescale the frequency axis
so that in fact now this periodicity
corresponds to a periodicity here which
is to Popeye
and here which is the sampling frequency
so very often in fact and will be doing
this next time
very often when you think
love continuous-time signals which have
been converted to discrete-time signals
when you look at the discrete-time
frequency axis
the frequency to pie is Associated
with the sampling frequency
as it will it was applied to the
original continuous-time signals
now as i indicated what will want to go
on to from here
is understanding I'll
what happens when we take a
continuous-time signal
converted to a discrete-time signal as I
just going through
do some discreet I processing with the
linear time-invariant system
and then carry that back into the
continuous-time world
that is a procedure that will go through
and
analyze and in fact illustrate in some
detail
next time in preparation for that
what I would be eager to encourage you
to do
using the study guide and in reviewing
this lecture
is to begin the next lecture
with a careful and thorough
understanding love
the arguments that I just going through
in particular
understanding the process that's
involved in going from a continuous-time
signal
through sampling to a discrete-time
and what that means in the frequency
domain interns to taking the original
spectrum
replicating it because if the sampling
process
and then sry scaling that so that
the periodicity gets rescaled so that
its periodic
with a period of two part so will
continue with that next time focusing
now
on the subsequent steps
in the process thank you