the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU hard
the
the in
the norm
are
the in the last two lectures
and we saw how periodic not periodic
signals could be represented as linear
combinations a complex exponentials
and this led to the Fourier series
representation
in the periodic case and it led to the
Fourier transform
representation in the a periodic case
and and then in fact
what we did was to incorporate the 4e a
series
within the framework of the Fourier
transform what I'd like to do in today's
lecture is
look at the 4-yard transform more
closely
in particular with regard to so this
property's
so let me begin by reminding you
love the analysis and synthesis
equations for the four th
transform and as I summarize them here
the synthesis equation being a
an equation that tells us how to build
the
time function outta in essence a linear
combination
a complex exponentials and the analysis
equation
telling us how to get the amplitudes
love those complex exponentials
from the Associated time function
so essentially in the decomposition
affect safety as a linear combination of
complex exponentials
the complex amplitudes if those are in
effect
the 48 transform scaled by
the differential and scaled by one over
two-part
now as
I indicated last time the 48 transform
is a complex function of frequency in
and in particular the complex function
of frequency
has an important and very useful
cemetery property
the symmetry love the Fourier transform
when X if T is real is
what is referred to as conjugate
symmetric in other words if we take the
complex
function after Omega and and its complex
conjugate
that's equivalent to replacing Omega
by minus Omega and a consequence if that
if we think interns love the real party
the Fourier transform
the real part is and even function of
frequency
and the magnet to is an even function of
whereas the imaginary part is an
odd function of frequency and the phase
angle
is an odd function of frequency so
we have this symmetry relationship that
for except the real
if we think I've either the real part or
the magnitude of the Fourier transform
its even symmetric and the imaginary
part
or the phase angle either one it is
fought symmetric in other words if we
flip it we multiply by a minus sign
let's didn't look at an example
in the context love an example that we
worked last time
for the Fourier transform we took
the case both a real exponential
love the form eat to the -80 times this
step
and the 48 transform as
we found was other algebraic form one
over a plus J Omega
and incidently the 48 transform into
grow only converged
for a greater than 0 in other words
for this exponential became and I
illustrated
the magnitude and angle and what we see
is that
you the minus 8c is a real
time function therefore its magnitude
should be an even function of frequency
and indeed it is
and its phase angle shown below
is and odd function of frequency
so in fact in although
I stressed last time that
the complex exponentials required to
build the time function
require exponentials both positive and
negative frequencies
for except the real what we see is that
because if the symmetry properties
either for the real and imaginary or
magnitude and angle
we can specify a before you transform
for let's say only positive frequencies
and asymmetry then implies are tells us
what the Fourier transform then will be
for the negative frequencies
okay now this same example the cause
the decaying exponential demonstrates
another important and often useful
property the Fourier transform
specifically let's rewrite algebraically
this example
as I indicate here so we have
again the exponential was 48
transformers one over a plus J Omega
and if I A just simply divide numerator
and denominator by a
I can rewrite it in the form shown here
and what we notice is dead in the time
function
we have a term of the form eight times
TV
and in the frequency function we have a
term for the form Omega
divided by a or
equivalent Lee we can't think all the
time function which I show here
and as the pram enter a gets smaller
the exponential gets spread out in time
whereas s04e08 transform
or the magnitude of its Fourier
transform has the inverse property
that as a get smaller in fact
this scales down in frequency
well this is a general property love
the Fourier transform namely the fact
that a a linear scaling a time
generates the infers linear scaling a
frequency
and the general statement love this time
frequency scaling is what
I show at the top above the transparency
namely the equation
that if we scale the time function in
time
then we apply and infers scaling a
frequency
now her this in fact is probably a
result
that you're already possibly familiar
with in
somewhat of a different context
essentially you can think of this
as an example poor generalization rather
up the notion that if let's say I A
had a signal that was recorded on a tape
player
and if I play the tape back and let's
say twice the speed which means that I'm
compressing the time axis
linearly by a factor of two then in fact
what happens is that
the frequencies that we observe get
pushed up by a factor of two
and effect let me illustrate that
I have here a glockenspiel
and anyone who loves a parade certainly
knows what I each
blockage feel as and
this particular glockenspiel has
3 eighties separated each by an active
there's a middle way
a high a us and a low a
and what I've done is to record
the middle a on a tape
at seven and a half inches per second
and
what I'd like to demonstrate is that as
we play that back either a cloister
half-speed
the effective note gets moved down or up
by a doctor
so let me first play the note at
the speed at which was recorded and so
what we'll hear
is the middle a as i've recorded it and
let me just start
the tape player
okay let me stop it and hopefully what
you heard is the
same note from the tape recorder as
the note that I played on the
glockenspiel okay well now
a rewind the tape and we go back to the
beginning
love that portion and
now if I change the tapes the to
half the speed so from seven and a half
inches per second
a change the tape speed 233 quarter
inches per second and now
when I play the tape back because effect
because
love the inverse relationship between
time and frequency scaling we're now
scaling in time by stretching out we
would expect the frequencies to be
lowered
by a factor of two we should now expect
the
taped no to be an octave lower
matching the slower a so let's just play
that okay let me stop it
and again will rewind the tape
go back to
the beginning and now will play this at
twice the speed so I change from three
and three-quarters
to 15 inches per second and now and I
play it we would expect that
to match the upper no and let's just do
that Ste
us
us okay well
although thats a result that intuitively
probably
makes considerable sense in fact what
that is
is an illustration love the inverse
relationship between
time scaling frequency scaling and also
by the way it was finally my opportunity
to play the glockenspiel on television
okayed now
in in addition their is another
very important relationship between the
time and frequency domains
namely what is referred to as a
duality relationship and
the duality relationship between time
and frequency
falls out more less directly from
the equations the analysis and synthesis
equations in particular if we look at
the
synthesis equation which I repeat here
and the analysis equation which I repeat
below it
what we observe is dead in fact
these equations are basically identical
except for the fact that in the top
integral we have things as a function of
Omega in the bottom integral as a
function of T
and there's a factor of 10 ver tu Pai
and by the way a minus sign
well you can look at the algebra
more carefully at your leisure but
especially with this says
is that if excessive Omega is
the Fourier transform over type function
exit see
then in fact except Amy
is very much like the Fourier transform
affective Omega
in fact it's the Fourier transform
attacks have minus Omega
to account for this minus sign and by
the way there's just an additional
factor
one over 25 so the duality relationship
which
follows from these two equations in fact
says that if x50
an ex vivo maker are a4e a transformed
pair
if little accent capital XR Fourier
transform pair
then capital lacks in fact has a $4 EA
transform
which is proportional a little lax
turned around well
this to outdo ality in the continuous
time Fourier transform
is very important it's very useful it by
the way is not
duality that surface in a forty a series
because as you recall the 48 series
begins with a continuous-time function
and in the frequency domain generates a
sequence
which with just naturally have the
proper have
problems associated with it if we
attempted to
interpreted to ality and we'll see also:
that in a discrete-time case one of the
important differences between
continuous-time and discrete-time
Fourier transforms
is the fact that in continuous-time we
have to our the
in discrete-time for then the
discrete-time Fourier transform we don't
well
let's indicate illustrate this with an
example
in here are in fact two examples
a Fourier transform pairs taken from
examples in the text
to the top one being example
four-point 11 from the tax and it's a
time for action
which is a sin 0 X over X type a
function
and its Fourier transform
corresponds to a
rectangular shape in the frequency
domain there's also
another example in the text the example
the preseason this one
which is example four-point 10 and an
example four point 10
we begin with a rectangle
and its Fourier transform is love the
form
all a sin x over X function
so in fact if we look at these to
examples together what we see is
the duality very evident in other words
if we take this time function and
instead think i've a frequency function
that has the same form
then we simply interchange the rolls a
time-frequency
in the other domains so the fact that
these to correspond
means that these two cars find
course and in this particular example
we because it the fact that we picked a
symmetric function even function
in fact the additional twist love the
time axis being reversed didn't show up
in her in duality with this example
now one thing he says of course is that
essentially
anytime you've calculated
the 48 transform a one-time function
then you actually calculate the Fourier
transform
to type functions another one being
the dual example to the one that you
just calculated
now also somewhat related to do our the
is what is referred to as parce balls
relation for the continuous-time Fourier
transform
and essentially what parts are false
relationship says
is that as kind of a a summary other
it says dead the energy
in a time function and the energy
in its Fourier transform are
proportional the proportionality factor
being a factor of two pi
it well that summarized here what's
meant by the energy
is course the ago the magnitude squared
effect City
and the statement apart the balls
relation and is dead
that in a brawl the energy and accept T
is proportional to this integral which
is the energy
indexable Megan now
although we've incorporated the 4e a
series
within a framework for the Fourier
transform parcels relation
needs to be modified slightly for
for a series because the fact that
periodic signal
has an infinite amount of energy and its
and essentially
that former parcels relationship for the
periodic case would say
infinity equals infinity which isn't too
useful
however can be modified so that part's a
false relationship for the periodic case
says essentially that the energy E
in one period other periodic time
function
in is proportional with this is the
proportionality factor
proportional to the sum %uh the
magnitude squared
up the coefficients in other words the
energy in one period
is proportional to the energy in the
sequence
that represents the four EA series
coefficients
now okay there are lots of other
properties
and there developed in the text in the
study guide
a number a properties that we want to
make particular you so
during this lecture and in later
lectures
are ones that I summarize here and
I won't demonstrate the proves but
a principally focus on some with the
interpretation is the lecture goes on
well in the first property that I have
listed here's what's referred to as the
time shifting property
and the time shifting property says if I
have a time function
with a Fourier transform mexico maker
if I shift that time function in time
dan that corresponds to multiplying
the 48 transformed by this factor
now as you examine this factor what you
can see is that
this factor has magnitude unity
and it has a phase which is linear with
frequency
and is slow %uh minus 20
so a statement to remember that will
come up
many times throughout the cores
is that a timeshare after a displacement
in time
corresponds to linear phase
or change in linear phase earlier change
in phase and frequency
another property in and in fact a pair
of properties
that will make reference to as we turn
our attention toward the end of this
lecture to
solving differential equations using the
Fourier transform
is hit was referred to as the
differentiation property
and its companion which is the
integration property
the differentiation property says again
if we have
a time function whose with Fourier
transform mexico maker
the Fourier transform up the time
derivative that
is in corresponds to multiplying the
Fourier transform
by a linear function of frequency so
here it's a linear able to change dead
that corresponds to differentiation
now at first glance what you might think
is that
the integration property is just the
reverse if that if
for the differentiation property you
multiply by J Omega then
for integration you must abide by jail
maker and thats almost correct
except not quite and the reason for the
not quite
is that recall that if you differentiate
what happens of course is that you lose
a constant
and if we have a time function thats
some fun and energy signal plus a
constant
differentiating will destroy the
and integration the immigration property
in essence tries to bring that back
so the integration property which is the
inverse
of the differentiation property says
that we divide
the transformed by J Omega and then
if in fact their was a constant added to
accept T
we have to account for that by inserting
an impulse
into the Fourier transform and
the file property that I want to draw
your attention to
on this you graph is the linearity
property
which is very straight forward to
demonstrate from
the analysis and synthesis equations
which simply said is
if X 100 maker is the Fourier transform
X 1ft
and x2 Omega is the Fourier transform X
2ft
then the Fourier transform a linear
combination is
a linear combination love the Fourier
transforms
now let me emphasize also that these
properties for the most part
apply both 240 a series and Fourier
transforms
because in fact and what we've done is
to incorporate
the forty a series within the
framework of the Fourier transform
okay now will be using a number of these
properties shortly when we turn our
attention to
near-constant coefficient differential
equations however before we do that I'd
like to
focus on two additional
major properties and
these are what are referred to as the
convolution property and the modulation
property
and in fact the convolution property as
I'm about
to introduces forms the
mathematical and conceptual basis for
the whole notion of filtering which in
fact will be
a topic by itself in a set of lectures
and
and in fact is a chapter by itself in
the textbook
similarly what i'll refer to as the
modulation property
again well occupy its own set
have lectures as we go through this
scores and in fact has its own
a chapter in the textbook
let me in just indicate what the
convolution property is
and and what the convolution property
tells us is that
the 48 transform of the convolution
a two-time functions is the product
all therefore yea transforms
so it says for example dead
if I have a linear time-invariant system
and in I have an input exits the an
impulse response HFT
and the output of course being the
convolution
then in fact if I look at this in the
frequency domain
the Fourier transform up the output
is the for EA transform the input
times the Fourier transform the impulse
response
now you can demonstrate this property
algebraically by essentially taking the
convolution integral
and applying to 48 transforming doing
the appropriate
in a changing the order integration et
cetera
but who what I'd like to draw your
attention to is a
somewhat more intuitive interpretation
of the property
and the intuitive interpretations stems
from
the relationship between the Fourier
transform at the impulse response
and what we refer to as the frequency
response
now recall dead wanna have
the things that lettuce to use complex
exponentials as building blocks
was the fact that there I can functions
linear time-invariant systems in other
words
if we have linear time-invariant system
and I have an input which is a complex
exponential
the output is a complex exponential the
same frequency
multiplied by what we call the frequency
response
and in fact the expression for the
frequency response
is identical to the expression for the
four EA transform the impulse response
in other words the frequency response is
the Fourier transform of the impulse
response
now in that context how can we
interpret the convolution property well
remember what I said at the beginning
the lecture 1 I've pointed
to the synthesis equation and I said in
in essence the synthesis equation tells
us
how to decompose x50 as a linear
combination a complex exponentials
what are the complex amplitudes are
those complex exponentials
well interns love our notation year
the complex amplitude of those complex
exponentials
is Xserve Omega or proportional taxable
make in particular taxable make a deal
maker
and then a factor two-part well
as this signal goes through this linear
time-invariant system
what happens to each of those
exponentials is
it each one gets multiplied by the
frequency response
at The Associated frequency
what comes out is the amplitude
all the complex exponentials that are
used
to bill the output
so in fact the convolution property
simply is telling us
that interns have a decomposition the
signal
enters a complex exponentials as we push
that signal through linear
time-invariant system
were separately modifying with the
frequency response were multiplying
by the frequency response the amplitudes
love the exponential comp phones used to
build the input
and that song intern is
the decomposition of the output in terms
of complex exponentials
now and I I understand that kinda going
through that involves
a little bit of sorting out and I
strongly encourage you
to try to understand and interpret the
convolution property
in knows conceptual terms rather than
simply by
applying the mathematics to the
convolution integral and seeing that
terms match up on both sides
now as i indicated the convolution
property
forms the basis for what's referred to
as filtering
and this is a topic that will be
treating a
considerable amount of detail and after
we've also gone through a discussion
love the discrete-time Fourier transform
in the next several lectures however
what I'd like to do is just
just indicate now a little bit love
the conceptual ideas involve
essentially conceptually what filtering
as its
typically referred to corresponds to
is modifying separately
the individual frequency components in a
signal
the convolution property told us that if
we
look at the individual frequency comp
points they get multiplied by the
frequency response and so what that says
is that we can amplify or it anyway
any of those comp own it separately
using a linear time-invariant system
for example what I've illustrated here
is
the frequency response what is commonly
referred to
as and ideal Lopez filter what an ideal
0 pass filter does
is to pass exactly
frequencies in one frequency range
and eliminate totally frequencies
outside that range
another filter which is not so ideal
might for example
attenuate sit com phone it's in this
band but not
I rather attenuate conference in this
band but not totally eliminate them
now interns a filtering we can think
back
to the differentiation property and in
fact interpreter
differentiation or differentiator as a
filter
recall that the differentiation property
said
that the Fourier transform all the
differentiated signal
is the for a transformer the original
signal multiplied by J Omega
so what that says then
is dead if we have a differentiator
opened the frequency response to that
is J Omega in other words the Fourier
transform of the output is Jay Omega
times the Fourier transform the input
and so the frequency response a
differentiator
looks like this and turns its magnitude
and what it does
of course is it amplifies high
frequencies
and attenuates low frequencies
well let me just to kinda cement summer
these ideas
illustrate them in a context 0
one kind of signal namely signal which
in fact
is the spatial signal rather than a time
signal
and this also gives me an opportunity to
introduce you
to our colleague JBJ for EA's
so if we could look at our colleague
mister four EA
who by the way is on
not only person who had tremendously
brilliant insights
and his insights in fact have led to
the developments really for the
foundation the developments that
is the basis for this course he was also
a very interesting fascinating person
and there's a certain amount of
historical discussion
about for EA and his background which
you might enjoy reading in the text
in any case what you're looking at a
course is a signal
and the signal is a spatial signal and
it has high frequencies and low
frequencies high frequencies
corresponding to things that are varying
rapidly
spatially and low frequencies barings
very slowly spatially it so
for example we could low-pass filter
this picture simply by asking
the video crew if they could slightly
defocus
and what you see as the picture is the
focus if you can hold it there
is dead we've lost edges which
is the rapid variation and what we've
retained is the broader
slow variation and now let's take out
the d focusing low-pass filter and go
back
to a focused image
okay now what
and we can also consider is what would
happen if we look
at the differentiated image and their
are several ways that we can think about
this
one is that a differentiator of course
the output of a differentiator
is larger where the discontinuity
or where the variation is faster
and so we would expect the edges
to be enhanced if in fact we
differentiated the image
or if we interpret differentiation in
the context
love our filter then what we're saying
if hey what we're saying is that in
effect
what's happening is that the
differentiator is
accentuating the high frequencies
because if the frequency shape the
differentiator now recall that this all
kinda fits together is a nice package
be expected to actively the
differentiation will enhance ages
when we talked about square waves and we
so I have a for a series built up a
square wave
we saw that it was the high frequencies
that were required in order to build up
the sharp
edges and so either viewed as a filter
or viewed intuitively
we would expect that the differentiated
image would in fact
get would in fact it anyway the slowly
varying background and amplify
the rapidly varying ages so let's look
again at
our original image just to remind you
love the fact that there are edges of
course and their
is more slowly varying backgrounds
and now let's look at the
result love passing that through
a differentiator and as i think is
very evident in that in the resulting
image
clearly is the edges that a retained and
the slow back to slower background
variations
are destroyed which is consistent with
everything we've said
okay now i've emphasized the her will be
returning
to a much broader discussion a filtering
at
a later point in the cores right now
like to comment on another
property which here is also as i
indicated a topic I've
in its own right and which really is the
dual
property to the convolution property and
in fact could be argued directly from
duality
and that is what's referred to as the
modulation property
now the convolution property told us
that
if we convolved in the time domain we
multiply in the frequency domain
and we know the time and frequency
domains are interchangeable because it
to our the
so what that would suggest is dead
if we multiply in the time domain
that would correspond to convolution in
the frequency domain
and in fact head that is exactly what
the modulation property is
I have a summarized here that if we
multiply
a time function by another time function
then
in the frequency domain week involved
whereas the convolution property is just
the duel at that
namely convolved being in the time
domain corresponds to
multiplication in the frequency domain
the convolution property is the basis as
i indicated for filtering
the modulation property as I've
summarized it here
in fact is the entire basis
for amplitude modulation systems issues
almost universally in communications and
wait
the modulation property is we'll see
when we explored in more detail
tells us is that if we have a signal
with a certain spectrum
and we multiply by a sinusoidal
signal whose for EA transformers said
impulses
then in a frequency-domain week involved
and that corresponds
to taking the original spectrum and
translating it
shifting it in frequency up to
the frequency love the carrier namely
the sinusoidal signal and as I said will
come to that in much more detail in a
number of lectures
okay now we've seen a number of
properties
and I indicated sometime earlier when we
talked about
and differential equations that in fact
it's the properties are the 48 transform
that providers with a very useful
an important mechanism for solving
linear constant coefficient differential
equations
and but I'd like to do now
is illustrate the procedure the basis
for that
and I think what we'll do is illustrated
simply in the context of several
examples
okay well in what i've indicated is
a system
with her a an impulse response HFT
or frequency response teachable nigga
and of course we know that in the time
domain it's just right to convolution
in the frequency domain its described
through multiplication
and I in essence
am assuming that we're talking about a
linear time-invariant system
and we're also going to assume that it's
characterized by a win here comes the
coefficient differential equation
where we're going to oppose the
condition
that its causal linear and
time-invariant
or equivalent Lee that the initial
condition conditions
are consistent with initial rest
and it's because it the fact that we're
assuming
that is a linear time-invariant system
that
we can describe it in the frequency
domain through the convolution property
and we can use the properties love the
forty a transfer
so let's take as our example a
first-order differential equation
as I indicate here so the derivative the
output plus eight times the output is
equal to the input
and now we can use the differentiation
property
if we for EA transform mystic entire
expression
the differentiation property tells us
that
the forty a transformer the derivative
of the output
is the for a transformer the output
multiplied by J Omega
and Lenny arity well let us
right the Fourier transform love this as
eight times while Omega
and since these are added together and
since we have the linear
linearity property these are added
together
and XOM Omega is and the Fourier
transform affect safety
so what we've used is the
differentiation property
and reviews the when the arity property
right now weekend solve this equation
for y Omega the forty a transformer the
output
in terms of Xserve Omega the Fourier
transform
the input and a simple algebraic step
gets s to this expression so the for a
chance for the output is one over
Jamaica plus a
ties the forty a transformer the input
and I just simply repeated
that equation appear
now so far this is algebra
and and question is now how do we
interpret this
well we know that the for a transformer
the output
is the forty a transformer the input
times the Fourier transform
are the impulse response to the system
namely the frequency response
so in fact if we think love
a chip tanh Omega as a Fourier transform
pair
then is the convolution property that
lets us
quaid this term with
H Omega so here
were using the convolution property
and so we know what the 48 transform
or the impulse responses they only one
over
J Omega plus a now
in we may have for example what is in
our problem
instead of getting the frequency
response to get the impulse response
and there are a variety of ways that we
can't do this we can attempt to go
through the inverse Fourier transform
expression
but in fact one of the most useful ways
is their formally called
the inspection method informally
its called if you work that out going
one way
then you ought to remember the answer so
that you know how to get back
method so what that says is
remember dead we worked an example and
in fact I showed you the example
earlier in the lecture that
the Fourier transform a view to the
minus eighty times a step
is one over J Omega plus a
so what is the inverse Fourier transform
a 1-over J Omega plus a
well ants need to the minus eighty
times unit step
and that's just simply remembering in
essence this particular transformed pier
well I've drawn graphically
the magnitude of the Fourier transform
here
and below it we have the impulse
response
the apostle spines is as I just
indicated either -80
times you see now let's go back up and
look at
the magnitude over the frequency
response
and given just a little bit of
discussion that we had
previously about filtering you should be
able to
in for something about the filtering
characteristics
love this simple first-order
differential equation
in particular if you look at that
frequency response
the frequency response falls off with
frequency and so it tends to do
is attenuate high frequencies and
retain low frequencies so in fact
you could think of the defocus saying
that we did on
the imager for EA you could think if
that approximately as
similar to the kind of filtering action
that you would get
by passing a signal through a
first-order differential equation
okay now just illustrate in one
additional step in both evaluating
inverse transforms and using Fourier
transform properties
to solve a near constant coefficient
differential equations
let's take this same example and rather
then finding the impulse response let's
find the response
to another exponential input
now we could of course do that using the
convolution integral we just got the
impulse response so we can put that
through the convolution integral to get
the response to this input
but let's do it instead by going back to
the differential equation
and so here i'm taking a differential
equation
all choose just to have some numbers to
work with
a equal to 2 and now
I'll choose an exponential on the right
hand side either minus tee times you
have t
and again we for EA transform the
equation
and we can remember
this particular Fourier transform pair
it's just the one who worked out
previously now with a equal to 1 clearly
we're getting a lot of mileage out of
that example
and now if we wanted determine what the
output why if he is
we can't do that by solving for Y Omega
and then generating the inverse Fourier
transform
well what's all this algebraically for y
Omega
and and that gets us to this expression
and this is not a Fourier transform that
we've worked out before
and this is have the second part to the
inspection procedure what we have is a
forty a transform which is a product
of two turns each of which we can
recognize
and what we can consider doing is
expanding that out
in a partial fraction expansion namely
as a summer turns
because the lady arity property
associated with the 48 transform
the inverse transform is then the song
the inverse transform movie to those
terms
okay so if we expand this out in a
partial fraction expansion
and you can just verify that
if you add these two together you get
back to where we started
we now have the sum of two terms
and if we now recognized by inspection
the inverse Fourier transform love this
we see that it simply
minus either -2 TV times the unit step
this one is plus either the minus the
times a unit step
and so in fact it's the summer these two
terms
which are the inverse transforms up the
individual turns in a partial fraction
expansion
that then give us the for EA transform
all y ft
her I'm sorry for her rather the output
so this is a gypsy that this is why if
the
which is the summer these two
exponentials and this
is the inverse Fourier transform
love y Omega as we calculated it
previously
okay well hopefully you're beginning to
get some sense now
love how powerful and also beautiful
the 48 transform is we've seen already
that
a glimpse or how it plays a role in
filtering modulation how its properties
helpless with linear constant
coefficient differential equations et
cetera
what we will do
beginning with the next lecture is
develop
a similar set of tools for the
discrete-time case and there are
some very strong similarities to what
we've done a continuous-time also some
very important differences
and then after we have the
continuous-time and discrete-time
Fourier transforms
will then see how the concepts
involved in the properties involved
leads to
very important powerful notions love
filtering
modulation sampling and other
signal processing ideas thank you