ha the the
the norm
well
the I'm out oppenheim
and I'd like to welcome you to this
video tape course on signals and systems
signals at least
as an informal definition are functions
one or more independent variables that
typically carry some type information
systems in
are setting with typically be used the
process signals
one very common example of a signal
might be let's say speech signal and you
might think
love the air pressure as a function of
time
or perhaps the electrical signal effort
goes through the microphone
transducer is a function of time as
representing the speech signal
and we might see a typical speech signal
looking something like i've indicated
here
its a function time
in this particular case and the
independent variable
being time is in fact continuous
and so a signal like this we will
typically be referring to
as a continuous-time signals now
it also for this particular example is a
function
one independent variable and
that will be referred to as
the one dimensional signal
corresponding to the fact that there's
only
one independent variable several
independent variables
so the speech signal is an example
a continuous-time one-dimensional signal
now signals can of course
be multi-dimensional and they may not
have as their independent variables time
variables
one very common example are
the examples represented by images
images
as signals we might think I'll as
representing brightness as it varies
in a horizontal and vertical
direction and so the brightness as a
function
these two spatial variables is then
a two-dimensional signal and
it the independent variables
would typically be continuous but of
course they're not time variables
and incidently it's worth
just commenting very often simply for
convenience
will have a tendency to refer to the
independent variables when we talk about
signals
as time variables whether or not the
really represent time
well let me illustrate
one example all image and
this is a picture jpg for EA
who perhaps more than anyone else
is responsible for the elegance and
beauty
a lot of the concepts we'll be talking
about throughout this course
and when you look at this in addition to
c4a himself you should recognize that
what you're looking at
is basically a signal which is
brightness as a function
the horizontal and vertical spatial
variables
as another example
an image as a signal let's look at an
aerial photograph
this is an aerial photograph taken
over a setter roads which
you can more less recognized in the
picture and
wanted the difficulties with this signal
is that it
the road system is somewhat obscured by
cloud cover
and well wanna show later
as an example what a system
might do to such as signal in terms of
processing is an attempt to
at least compensate some way for the
cloud cover represented in the
photograph following terms a
the detailed analysis we go through
during the course are
focus of attention is pretty much
restricted to
one-dimensional signals in fact we will
be using
two-dimensional signals more
specifically images
very often to illustrate a variety
concepts now
speech in images are examples
what we refer to as continuous-time
signals
in that they are functions
continuous variables equally
important classes signals will be
concentrating on
in the cores are signals are
discrete-time signals
where by discrete-time we mean
is that the signal is
a function integer variable
and so specifically only takes on values
at in nature values the argument
so here is a graphical illustration
the discrete-time signal and
discrete-time signals arise
in a variety of ways one very common
example
it seems fairly often is discrete-time
signals in the context
economic time series and for example
stock market analysis
so what I show here is one
very commonly occurring example the
discrete-time signal
it represents the weekly stock market
index
the independent variable in this case is
the week number and we see what the
stock market is doing over this
particular period
as a function or the number of the week
and
course along the vertical axis is the
weekly index incidently
this particular period was not chosen
random in fact captures very interesting
aspect
stock market history namely the
stock market crash in 1929
which in fact is represented by behavior
this discrete time signal or sequence
in this particular area so this dramatic
dip in fact
is the stock market crash 1929
well the dow jones weekly average is an
example
all a one-dimensional discrete-time
signal
and just as with continuous time
we had not just one-dimensional
multi-dimensional signals
likewise we have multi-dimensional
signals
in the discrete-time case where
in that case then the discrete-time
signal that we're talking about a
sequence
is a function love to integer variables
and is one example this might let's say
represent a spatial
antenna array where this is
array number in let's say the horizontal
direction and this is array number in
the vertical direction
both classes signals continuous-time and
discrete-time
as i've indicated are very important and
it should be emphasized
dead the importance I'll discrete-time
signals associated processing
continues to grow in large part because
I'll the current and emerging
technologies
that permit basically the processing
or continuous-time signals by
first converting to discrete-time
signals
and processing them with discrete time
systems
and that in fact is a topic that we will
discuss in a fair manner detail later on
in the course
let's now turn our attention to systems
and as they indicated a system
basically processes signals
and they have of course inputs
and outputs and depending on
whether we're talking about
continuous-time for discrete-time
the system maybe a continuous-time
system
or a discrete-time system so in the
continuous-time
case I indicate here in input: accept T
and an output y ft if we were talking
about discrete-time system I would
represent
the the input in terms a discrete-time
variable and of course the output
interns a
discrete-time variable also
now in very general terms systems are
hard to deal with
because is they are defined very broadly
a very generally
and in dealing with systems and
analyzing
what we will do is attempt to exploit
some very specific and as we'll see
very useful system properties
to indicate what I mean and how things
might be split up
we could talk about systems and we'll
talk about systems
that are linear and we could
divide systems basically into systems
that are either linear
or nonlinear and we will
or and also devices turns into systems
that are
what we refer to as time-invariant
or time-varying systems and these aren't
turns that
we've defined yet of course but we will
be defining
in the course very shortly and while
in some sense this division represents
all systems and this those two
the focus of the course is really going
to be principally
on linear time-invariant systems
so in its basically the system's
that we will be focusing on and
will be referring to those systems as
linear
time-invariant systems
well as a free clip said some other
kinds of things that systems can do
let me illustrate first in
I a one-dimensional continuous-time
context and then later with a
discrete-time example
one example I'll some processing
I'll signals with an appropriate system
the particular example that I want to
illustrate
relates to the restoration or old
recordings
and missus some work that was done by
Professor Thomas stocker who
is at the University Utah and work that
he had done a number of years ago
relating to the fact day in all
recordings
for example in caruso recordings
the recording was done through
mechanical morning
and the characteristics love the horn
tended to vary from day to day
and because if the characteristics of
the horn
the recording tended to have a muffled
quality something like
yes sorta the sense that you would get
if you were speaking through a megaphone
what professor stock and it was
developed a system
to process these old recordings
in such a way dead a lot or
the characteristics and distortion do
to that recording system was removed so
I'd like to
illustrate that as one example some
signal processing with an appropriate
continuous-time system and what you'll
hear
is a to track recording
on the first track is the original on
restored
caruso recording and on the second track
is the result of the restoration and so
as I switch back and forth
from channel one to channel two will be
switching from
the original to the restored will begin
the tape
by playing the original and
day and as it proceeds will switch
so we begin on channel one
low pS The Regent
switch now process middle
him home
his back 0 hit
back to the original p
I read
back to the restoration
mine yard
home
and once again back to the rigid
mid
and presumably and hopefully what you
heard
was dead in the restoration in fact a
lot of the muffled
characteristics the original recording
were compensated for or remove now
one of the interesting things that
happened in fact in the work that
lesser Stockham did is that in the
process of the restoration and perhaps
you've heard this
in the process of the restoration in
fact some other background noise on the
recording
was emphasize and so he processed
this the signal further in an attempt to
remove that background noise and with
that particular processing the
processing
was very highly nonlinear a very
interesting thing happened
which was that not only in at processing
was the background noise removal but
somewhat surprisingly
also the orchestra was and let me just
plain bad
now as an example love some very
sophisticated processing
with the nonlinear system what you'll
hear on channel one
0 is the restoration as
we just plated when I switch to chat
to will the Hampton
processing him home
and acted one now
0 would im
hell
now inside
back
why did
well
him
finally once again world
okay so
that's an example love processing Ave
continuous-time signal with a
corresponding continuous-time
system now I'd like to illustrate an
example
some processing discrete-time signal and
I'd like to do that in the context that
the example
ratio before a discrete-time signal
which was
the dow jones industrial weekly stock
market index
I head shown it before as
I've shown it here again over a period
of slightly more than a year where this
is the number of weeks and this is the
weekly index and to illustrate
some of the processing what I'd like to
do
is show the stock market index
weekly index over a much longer time
period a particular
the weekly index over a ten year period
and that's what I show here so
what this covers is roughly 1927
to 1937 and
in this case although this is still a
discrete-time signal
just simply for the purposes display
what we've done
is to essentially connect the dots and
draw continuous curve through the points
so that this picture isn't filled up
with a lot of vertical lines
so this is the discrete-time sequence
represents the weekly Dow Jones
Dow Jones index over a 10-year period
and
here by the way again is the crash of
it's interesting to note by the way day
actually the disaster in the stock
market wasn't so much the 1929 crash
but the long downward trend that follow
that and you can see that here
by kinda filtering through by I
the rapid variations in the index and
what you see is this
smooth downward trend followed
eventually by upward trend now
this issue love looking at something
like this looking at a sequence
and following the smoother parts if it
namely
the long-term trends is in fact
something
that is done quite typically with
economic time series like this
and in particular what's done is to
smooth it
or average over some time period
to emphasize the slow variations and
de-emphasize the rapid variations
and that in fact is processing that is
done
with discrete-time system solos when you
hear referred to let's say
in stock market reports fifty one day
moving average
that in fact is processing the stock
market index
with a particular discrete-time system
the result
up doing that on this particular example
generates a smooth version the curve
which I overly here
and the overlay
than is really attempting to track the
smoother variations and deemphasized
more rapid variations let me just
slightly offset that so that the
different stands out a little more
and so here you see what is
the original weekly index and
this is the result processing that
sequence
with inappropriate system
to apply smoothing and in fact
what it is is a moving average and so
here again
you can see the in the smooth occurred
this general downward trend
up until this time period followed by
eventually
recovery I well we've seen
example with a continuous-time signals
caruso recording an example with the
discrete-time signal
this stock market index and what I'd
also like to show
is 30 example which is
the result some processing on an image
in particular
the image that we talked about before
which was the aerial photographs
that had the problem some cloud cover
so once again what we see here
is the original aerial photograph
with the cloud cover and
some processing was applied to this
using a system
which in fact was both nonlinear
and quote time-varying or in the case
these independent variables would refer
to it as spatially varying
and the result applying that processing
is shown in the joining
picture and what we see the air is
hopefully a reasonable attempt
to compensate for the cloud cover and
this by the way was some work was done
by Professor
them MIT and has been
very successful type processing were
aerial photographs I should say also
that this particular example is one
where although the original signal
was a signal dead is continuous time
that is
the independent variables are continuous
as they are in a spatial
aerial photograph in fact for the
processing
that picture was first converted to a
sequence
through a process called sampling which
will be talking about later
and then the processing in fact was done
on a digital computer
okay well these then are some examples
all the use I'll some
systems to process
some signals both in continuous-time
in discrete-time for one-dimensional
signals
and for multi-dimensional signals
and as I kinda refer to systems we've
thought of them as kinda one big block
with appropriate
or associated input and output and
as will be getting into in the first
part of the course
very often systems are interconnected
together
for a variety of reasons some other
kinds of interconnections that will talk
about
are connecting systems
in what are called series are cascaded
connections
parallel interconnections feedback
interconnections and feedback
interconnections
in fact are very interesting very
important
for useful and will be major topic
toward the end of the course feedback
as you may or may not know
comes into play in a variety of
situations
for example an amplifier design is we'll
talk about
the black feedback plays an important
role
in a situation where you have
a basically unstable system feedback is
often used to stabilize the system
and feedback interconnections systems in
that sense
are very often used in high-performance
aircraft
which are inherently unstable and are
stabilized
this kind in action
just two give you a little sense this
without going into any of the details
what i'd like to show you is and excerpt
from a lecture day
we'll be seeing toward the end of the
course relating to
feedback analysis a feedback systems and
uses a feedback
and this is in the context what's
referred to
as the inverted pendulum which is
system that's basically unstable
feedback
interconnections are used to stabilize
the idea
as you'll see in this brief clip is that
there is a cart that's moving on a track
with a ride its pivoted at the base
and so that system in the absence
anything
is unstable in that the ride attend for
and as we going to in detail in the
lecture
later use feedback to
position the card under the pendulum to
balance it
and in fact that balancing can be done
even
when we modify the system in a variety
of ways
as you'll see in this clip so let's take
a look at that
remembering that this is just a brief
excerpt
from a longer discussion I can change
the
overall system even further by
let's say for example pouring a liquid
and now let me also comment that
change the physics of a little bit
because the
the liquid can slash around a little bit
comes a little more complicated
system but as you can see it still
remains balance
as you'll see when we get to it by the
way that demonstration was a lot of fun
to do
now in talking about signals and systems
as we go through the course
their are several domains to in
particular
that we will find convenient for
the analysis and representation signals
and systems
one is the time-domain
which is what we tend to think
and which we have kind of been focusing
on
in the discussion so far in this lecture
by equally important is what's referred
to
as the frequency-domain
as representation for signals
and as a means for analysis for systems
and in the context or the
frequency-domain representation
some old the kinds a ideas on topics
that will be exploring
are the Fourier transform and
the le plus transform and
a discrete-time counterpart the
apostrophe is for which is the sea
transport
the Fourier transform discussion will
get into fairly early in the course
and the La Paz transforming z transform
represent extensions the 48 transform
and will be getting into
that later in the course just kinda
initially
to think about the time domain and
frequency domain
you might think for example over No
being played
and the time-domain representation would
be
how let's say the
sound pressure as a function of time
would change
and the frequency domain representation
would
correspond to representation the
frequency content
the No and in fact what I'd like to do
is
illustrate that and those two domain
simultaneously
by playing a glockenspiel
no which'll here is the No
repeated several times over and at the
same time
you'll see to displays one on the left
representing the time domain display a
representation
the signal and the one on the right
representing the frequency
me so let's look at that and
you'll hear the note and simultaneously
see these two displays
there's the No on the left time
ways and on the right what we see
is frequency content in particular
indicating the fact dead there are
several harmonics
lines tell
okay well what I've gone thru
in this lecture represents a brief
overview
signals and systems and beginning with
the next lecture we will be
much more specific and precise first
discussing some basic signals and then
talking about systems and system
properties and how to exploit
as one final comment that I'd
like to making this lecture I'd like to
emphasizes at the out said
dead the taped lectures
represent only one com- ponent the cores
and equally important will be
both the textbook and the video course
manual in particular
it's important not only to reviewing the
tapes
but simultaneously or in conjunction
with that
doing the appropriate reading in the
textbook and
also working through the problems
carefully
in the video course manual in a course
like this
you basically only get out a bit as much
as you put into it
the hope is dead if you put the
right amount of time and effort into it
you'll find the course to be
educational and interesting and I
certainly hope that will be the case
thank you