the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT ided you
home
in
the No
for in the last lecture
I introduced an illustrated the kinds of
signals and systems that will be dealing
with
throughout this course in today's
lecture I'd like to
be a little more specific and in
particular talk about
some the basic signals both
continuous-time and discrete-time
that will form important building blocks
as
the course progresses let's begin
with one signal the continuous-time
sinusoidal signal which perhaps you're
already
somewhat familiar with mathematically
the continuous-time sinusoidal signal is
expressed as i've indicated here
there are three parameters
a Omega 0 and see the parameter a is
referred to as
the ample to the parameter Omega 0
as the frequency and the parameter fee
as the face and
graphically the continuous-time
sinusoidal signal has the form
shown here now
the sinusoidal signal has a number love
important properties that will find it
convenient to exploit as the
course goes along one of which is
the fact that the sinusoidal signal
is what is referred to as periodic what
I mean by periodic
is that under inappropriate time shift
which I indicate here
as t0 the signal replicates
or repeats itself force it another way
if we shift the time origin by an
appropriate amount
t0 the smallest value t0 being referred
to as the period
then X 50 is equal to itself shifted and
to demonstrate that we can demonstrated
mathematically
by simply substituting into the
mathematical expression for the
sinusoidal signal
see plus capital T zero
in place if T when we carry out the
expansion
we then have for the argument the
sinusoid
Omega 0t plus Omega 0
capital T zero plus P now
one of the things that we know about
sinusoidal functions
is dead if you change the argument by
any integer multiple
to pie and the function has the same
value
and so we can exploit that here in
particular
with Omega 0t0 and integer multiple
up to par i then the right hand side of
this equation
is equal to the left hand side of the
equation so
with Omega 0t0 equal to two part times
an integer
or t0 equal to two part times an integer
divided by Omega 0 the signal repeats
the period is defined as the smallest
value if t0 and so the period is to pie
divided by Omega 0 and going back to
are sinusoidal signal we can
see that and
i've indicated here then the period
as to pie over Omega 0 and that's the
bad you
under which the signal repeats now
in addition a useful
property above the sinusoidal signal is
the fact that
a timeshare all a sinusoid
is equivalent to a phase change and we
can demonstrate
that again mathematically in particular
if we put the sinusoidal signal under
a timeshare i've indicated that the
probe the time shift that i'm talking
about. by small t0
and expand this out then
we see that that is equivalent to
a change in phase and important thing to
recognize
about this statement is that not only is
a timeshare
generating a phase change but in fact
if we inserted a phase change
there is always a value if t0
which would correspond to
an equivalent I'm ship said another way
if retake Omega 0t0
and think of that as are change in phase
for any change in phase we can solve
this equation for timeshift
or conversely for any value timeshare
that
represents an appropriate face
so a time shift corresponds to a phase
change
and a phase change likewise corresponds
to it I'm ship
and so for example if we
look at the sinusoidal signal
the general sinusoidal signal that we
saw previously in effect changing the
phase
corresponds to moving this signal in
time
one way or the other for example if we
look at the sinusoidal signal with
a phase equal to 0 that corresponds
to locating the time origin at this p
and i've indicated that on
the following grass
so here we have illustrated a sinusoid
with zero phase or cosine with zero
phase
corresponding to taking a general
picture and shifting it
shifting it appropriately as i've
indicated here
this of course still has the property
that it's a periodic function
since we simply displaced in time
and by looking at the graph what we see
is that it has another very important
property
a property referred to as even and
that's a property that will find it
useful in general
to refer to in relation to signals a
signal is said to be even
if when we reflected about the origin it
looks exactly the same so it's a metric
about the origin and looking at
this sinusoid that in fact has that
property
and mathematically this statement that
it's even is equivalent to the statement
that if we replace the time argument
by its negative the function itself
doesn't change
now this corresponded to a phase shift 0
in our original
cosine expression if instead we had
chosen a phase shift love let's say
minus pie over to
then is that a a cosigner so it'll
signal
well we would generate is a sinusoid
with the appropriate phase or
said another way if we take are
original cosine and
substitute in for the phase minus pie
over to
then of course we have this mathematical
expression
using just straight for trigonometric
identities
we can express that alternately as
signed Omega 0t
the frequency and amplitude of course
haven't changed and
that you can convince yourself also is
equivalent
to shifting the cosine by
and a mountain time that I've indicated
here namely
a quarter of the period so illustrated
below
is the graph now when
we have a phase of mine espy over to an
arc cosine
which is a sinusoidal signal of course
it's still
periodic its periodic with a period of
two pi
over Omega 0 again because all that
we've done
by introducing a phase change is
introduce the timeshare now
when we look at the sinusoid in
comparison with the Cosi namely with
this particular choice a phase
this has a different symmetry and
that symmetry is referred to as odd what
ought symmetry means
graphically is that when we flipped the
signal
about the origin
but I margin we also multiply it by a
minus sign
so thats in effect antisymmetric
it it's not the mirror image but it's
the mirror image flipped over
and will find many occasions not only to
refer to signals more general and
sinusoidal signals as
even in some cases and odd in other
cases
and in general mathematically
on signal is one which
has satisfy is the algebraic expression
that exit see when you replace
TE by its negative is equal to
minus exit -2 so replacing the argument
by its negative
corresponds to time River I A
an algebraic sign rivers
okay so in this is the class of
continuous-time
sinusoids will have a little more to say
about it later
but I've now like to turn to
discrete-time sinusoids what we'll see
is that discrete-time sinusoids
are very much like continuous-time ones
but also
with some very important differences and
we want to focus not only on the
similarities
but also on the differences well let's
begin
with the mathematical expression a
discrete-time sinusoidal signal
mathematically
is as i've indicated here a cosine
Omega 0 and plus the and just says
in the continuous-time case the
parameter
a is what we refer to as the airport to
Omega 0 as the frequency and see
as the face
and I've illustrated
here several discrete-time
sinusoidal signals and they kinda
look similar in fact if you sort of
track what you might think of is the
envelope
it looks very much like what a
continuous-time sign outside so it might
look like
but keep in mind day at the independent
variable in this case
isn't integer variable and so
the sequence in fact only takes on bag
use
at integer values up the argument and
we'll see
that that has a a very important
implication and will see that shortly
now
one of the issues that we addressed in
the continuous-time cases periodicity
and I want to refer or return to that
shortly because that is in fact one of
the areas where there is an important
distinction
let's first
though examine the statement similar to
the one
the week salmon for continuous-time
namely the relationship between the time
shift in a phase change
now in continuous-time
course we saw that a timeshare
corresponds to a phase change in
vice versa let's first look at
the relationship between shifting time
and generating a change in phase
in particular for discrete-time if
in fact I implement a timeshare that
generates a phase change and we can see
that
easily by simply inserting a timeshare
employs an 0 and if we expand at this
argument we have
Omega 0 and plus Omega 0n0
and so I've done that on the right hand
side of the equation
year and the
Omega 0n0 then simply corresponds to
a change in phase so clearly
a shift in time generates
a change in phase and
for example if we take a particular
sinusoidal signal let's say we take the
cosine signal
at a particular frequency and with a
phase equal to 0
a sequence that we might generate is
one that I've illustrated here so
when I'm illustrating here is the cosine
signal with 0 theta is
and it has a particular
behavior to it which will depend someone
on the frequency
if I now take this same sequence
and shifted so that the time origin
shifted a quarter of a period away then
you can convince yourself and it's
straightforward
to work out that that timeshare
corresponds to a phase shift
of pie over to so
in that case with the cosine
with a phase minus pie over to
that will correspond to the expression
that I have here
we can alternately right that using a
get a trigonometric identity as sin
as a sign function and that I've stated
is equivalent to a timeshare
namely this shift the pirate to is equal
to an
a certain time share and the timeshare
for this particular example
is in fact the quarter the period
so here we have
the sinusoid previously we had the
cosine
the cosine was exactly the same sequence
but with the Argent located here
and in fact that's exactly the way we
drew this graph namely
we just simply took the same values and
change the time origin
now looking at this sequence which is
the
sinusoidal sequence the phase
-5 over to that has a certain symmetry
and in fact what we see is that
it has an oximetry just as in the
continuous-time case
namely if we take that sequence flip it
about the axis
and flip it over and sign then we get
the same sequence back
whereas with zero phase corresponding
to the cosine that I show previously
that hasn't even symmetry
namely if I flipped about the time
margin
and don't do it sign reversal then the
sequences maintain
so here we have
and on symmetry expressed mathematically
as i've indicated namely
replacing the independent variable by
its negative
attach is a negative sign to the whole
sequence
whereas in a previous case
what we have is 0 phase
and and even symmetry
and that's expressed Mac mathematically
as exit and
equals X -8
okay now one of the things I said so far
about discrete-time sinusoids is dead
a timeshare corresponds to a phase
change
and weekend then ask whether
the river statement is also true and we
knew that the river statement was true
in continuous-time
specifically is a true
that a phase change
always corresponds with time shift
now we know that that is true namely
that this statement works both ways
in continuous-time does it in
discrete-time
well the answer somewhat
interestingly are surprisingly into you
sit down and think about it
is no dead it is not
necessarily true and discrete-time that
any phase change
can be interpreted as a simple
time-shifted the sequence
and let me just indicate what the
problem is
if we look
at the relationship between the left
side on the right side of this equation
expanding this out as we did previously
we have that Omega 0n
plus Omega 0n0 must correspond to Omega
0n plus
p and so on make 0n0
must correspond to the phase-change now
which you can see pretty clearly is
there'd depending
on the relationship between see an Omega
n0 may or may not come out to be an
integer
now in continuous-time
the amount of time shift did not have to
be an integer a map
indiscreet time when we talk about a
timeshare the amount of time shift
obviously because the nature
discrete-time signals
must be an integer so the face changes
related to time shifts
must satisfy this particular
relationship
namely that Omega 0n0
were n0 is an integer is equal to the
changing face
okay now that's one distinction between
continuous-time and discrete-time
let's now focus on another one namely
the
issue of periodicity and what we'll see
is that again whereas in continuous-time
all continuous-time sinusoids our
periodic
in the discrete-time case that is not
necessarily true
to
explore that little more carefully let's
looked at the expression again for a
general sinusoidal signal with
an arbitrary effort to frequency and
phase
and for this to be periodic
what we require is that there be some
value capital and
under which one we shift the sequence by
that amount
we get the same sequence back again and
the smallest value capital and
is what we've defined as the period now
when we try that on a sinusoid we've
core substitute in
for and little and little and plus
capital and
and when we expand out the argument
here we'll get
the argument that I have on the right
hand side
and in order for
this to repeat in other words in order
for a press in effect
to discard this term Omega 0 times
capital and where capital is the period
must be an integer multiple a two-part
and
in that case its periodic as long as
Omega 0 times capital and capital in
being the period
is to provide times an integer just
simply dividing this out
we have capital in the period is to pie
am
divided by Omega 0 well
you can say okay what's the big deal a
whatever capital and happens to come out
to be when we do that a little bit about
your bro that's the period
but in fact capital and or 2 p.m.
divided by Omega 0
may not ever come out to be an integer
or may not come out to be the one that
you thought it might
for example let's look at
some particular sinusoidal signals
but say we have the first one here
which is a sinusoid as I've shown
and it has a frequency what i've
referred to as the frequency
Omega 0 equal to two pi divided by 12
and what we'd like to look at
is to pry divided by Omega 0
in effect then find an integer to
multiply that by
in order to get another manager let's
just try that here
if we look at to prioritize make a zero
to pry over Omega 0 for this case is
equal to 12
well that's fine 12 is an integer
so what that says in fact is that this
sinusoidal
signal is periodic and in fact this
period periodic with period of 12
all right let's look at the next one
the next one we would have to pile for
Omega 0
again and that's equal to 31 fourths
so with that says
is that the period is 31 forts wait a
minute
30 1/4 isn't an integer we have to
multiply that by an injured
to get another integer well we multiply
that by four
so to pile from a guys there are ties
for is 3131 is an integer
and so what that says is this is
periodic not with the period up to par
over make a zero
by with a period love to pie
over Omega 0 times for namely with the
period
I'll 31 finally
let's take an exam the example where
Omega 0z call to a6
as shown here that actually looks if you
track it with a ride like its periodic
to pile over Omega 0 in that case
is equal to 12 pie well
what integer can I multiplied 12 pie
by and get another integer the answer is
none
because pi is an irrational number so in
fact
what that says is that if you look at
this sinusoidal signal it's not periodic
at all
even though you might for yourself into
thinking it is
simply because the envelope looks
periodic namely the
continuous-time acquittal with this is
periodic
the discrete-time sequence is not
okay well we've seen then some
important distinctions between
continuous-time sinusoidal signals
and discrete-time sinusoidal signals the
first one
is the fact that in the continuous-time
case
a time-shifted phase change are always
equivalent
where's the discrete-time case in effect
that works one way
but not the other way we've also
seen that for a continuous-time signal
the continuous-time signal is always
periodic
whereas the discrete-time signal is not
necessarily
in particular for the continuous-time
case
if we have a general expression for the
sinusoidal signal
that i've indicated here that's periodic
for any choice Omega 0 whereas
in a discrete-time case its periodic
only air Omega 0 is to Poway
well the only if
to pie over Omega 0 can be multiplied by
integer
to get another injured now another
important and as it turns out useful
distinction
between the continuous-time and
discrete-time case
is the fact that in the discrete-time
case as we very what I've called the
frequency Omega 0
we only see
distinct signals as omega 0
varies over a two-party interval and if
we let Omega 0
very outside the Rangers let's say mine
despite a pirate 0 to 2pi
will see the same sequences all over
again
even though at first glance the
mathematical expression might look
different
so in the discrete-time case
this classes signals
is identical for values Omega 0
separated by two pi whereas
in a continuous-time case that is not
true
in particular if I consider the
sinusoidal continuous-time signals
as I very Omega 0
what will happen is that I will always
see
different sinusoidal signals namely
these won't be
and in in effect we can justify
that statement algebraically and
I will take the time to do it carefully
but
let's look first the mall at the
discrete-time
case and a statement that I'm making is
that
if I have to discrete-time sinusoidal
signals
at two different frequencies and if
these frequencies
are separated by an integer multiple to
Pine namely
if Omega to is equal to Omega one-plus
to pie times in integer when
I substitute this into this expression
because it the fact that n is also an
integer
all have am times and as an integer
multiple a two-part
and that term of course will disappear
because the periodicity
the sinusoid and these two sequences
will be equal
on the other hand in the continuous-time
case
since this is not restricted to be an
integer variable
since T is not restricted to be an
for different values I'll Omega wanna
make it to
the sinusoidal signals will always be
different
okay now many of the issues that I
praise
so far in relation to sinusoidal signals
are elaborated on
in more detail in the text and of course
you'll have an opportunity
to exercise so this
as you worked through the video course
manual
let me stress that
sinusoidal signals will play an
extremely important role
for us as building blocks for general
signals
and descriptions systems and leaves the
whole concept
all four EA an ala Cys which is very
heavily exploited
throughout the course
what i'd now like to turn to in is
another class love important building
blocks
and in fact will see that under certain
conditions these relate strongly to
sinusoidal signals
namely the Class A real in complex
exponentials
let me begin first the ball with
the real exponential and
in particular in the continuous-time
case a real continuous-time exponential
is mathematically expressed as I
indicate year X if T all to see
you to the eighty where for
the real exponential C&A
are real numbers and that's what we mean
by the real exponential
up shortly will also consider complex
exponentials where these numbers can
then
become complex so this is an exponential
function and for example
if the parameter a is positive
that means that we have growing
exponential function
if the parameter a is negative than
that means dead we have a decaying
exponential function now
some weight as an aside its kinda
interesting to note
that for exponentials a timeshare
corresponds to a scale change which
is somewhat different than what happens
with sinusoids
in the sinusoidal case we saw that a
timeshare
corresponded to a phase change the real
exponential a timeshare
as it turns out corresponds to simply
changing the scale
there's nothing particularly a
crucial or exciting about that and in
fact
perhaps stressing it is a little
misleading for general functions of
course
about all that you can say about what
happens when you
implement a timeshare is that implements
a time ship
okay so here's the real exponential
just CE to the eighty let's
look at the real exponential now in the
discrete-time
case and in the discrete-time case
we have several alternate ways
love expressing it we can
express the real exponential in the four
see be to the beta N or
as will find more convenient in part for
reason at all indicate shortly
we can rewrite this as see time's alpha
to the end where course
alpha is equal to me to the beta
more typically in a discrete-time case
will express
the exponential as see times
alpha to the end so for example this
becomes
essentially a geometric series a
progression
as an continues for certain values about
for here for example we have
for alpha greater than 0
first the ball on the top the case where
the magnitude about the
is greater than one so that
this the sequence is exponentially
geometrically growing on the bottom
again without the positive
but now with its magnitude less than 1
we have a geometric progression
that is exponentially or geometrically
became okay so this
in both these cases is with alpha
greater than 0
now the functional were talking about is
alpha to the N
and of course which you can see is that
if al Phys negative is that a positive
then when in is even
that minus sign is gonna disappear when
is Eid
there will be a minus sign it so for
alpha negative
the sequences good alternate positive
and negative ads
so for example here we have
alpha negative
and with this magnitude less than one
and you can see that
again its envelope the case
geometrically
and the values alternate in sin
and here we have the magnitude about the
greater than one
without the negative again they
alternate in signing of course
its growing geometrically
now if you think about alpha positive
and go back to the expression that I
have at the top
namely see times alpha to the end
with alpha positive
you can see a straightforward
relationship between
alpha and beta family beta is
the logarithm natural logarithm a valve
something to think about is what happens
if alpha is negative which is of course
a very
important and useful class love real
discreet I'm exponentials also
well it turns out that without the
negative if you try to express it as see
me to the beta and then fag beta comes
out to be an imaginary number
and bad is one but not the only reason
why in the discrete-time case its of the
most convenient
to phrase real exponentials
in the for alpha to the end rather than
you to the beta and in other words to
express them
in this form rather than in this for
okay now let's those are real
exponentials continuous-time and
discrete-time
now let's look at the continuous-time
complex exponential and
what I mean by a complex exponential
again is an exponential the for
see you to the eighty him but in this
case
we allow the parameters C&A to be
complex numbers and let's just track
this throughout your break Lee
CNA a complex numbers let's write see in
polar form so it has
a magnet to an angle let's write a and
rectangular form so it has a real part
in an imaginary part and when we
substitute these two
in here combined some things together
I'll actually having combined yet I have
this
for the amplitude for the effort to
factor
and this for the exponential factor I
can now put a lot of this
the term corresponding to eat to the RT
and combine the imaginary parts together
and I come down to the expression that I
have here
so following this for their
a an exponential this form you to the J
Omega were either the JC
using Oilers relation can be expressed
as the some Ave cosine
was GA times assign
and so that corresponds to this factor
and then their is this time varying
amplitude factor on top of that
finally putting those together we end up
with the expression
that I show on the bottom and what this
corresponds to
are to sinusoidal signals
ninety degrees out of phase as indicated
by the fact is a cosine and sine
so there's a real part in an imaginary
part
with sinus or does comp on its ninety
degrees out of phase
and a time varying amplitude factor
which is a real exponential so it's a
sinusoid
multiplied by real exponential in both
the real part in the imaginary part
and let's just see what one of those
terms might look like
but i've indicated at the top
is a sinusoidal signal
with and exponential time very
exponential
on below or an envelope which is a real
exponential and in particular which is
growing namely with are greater than 0
and on the bottom i've indicated
the same thing with are less than zero
and
this kinda sinusoidal signal by the way
is typically referred to as a damped
sinusoids in
so what are negative what we have in the
real and imaginary parts
are damped sinusoids and
the sinusoidal compliments at that are
ninety degrees out of phase
in the real part and in the imaginary
part okay now
in the discrete-time case we have more
or less
the same kinda outcome in particular
what will make reference to
are complex exponentials in a
discrete-time
case the expression for the complex
exponential
looks very much like the expression for
the real exponential
except that now we have complex
factors so see an alpha
are complex numbers and again
if we tracked through the algebra
and get to a point where we have
a real exponential multiplied by a
factor
which is a purely imaginary exponential
apply Oilers relationship so this
we then finally come down to a
sequence which has a real exponential
ample to multiplying
once I saw it in the real part and in
the imaginary part
exit exactly the same kind of
exponential
multiplying a sinusoid thats
ninety degrees out of phase from that
and so if we look at what why these
factors might look like
its what we would expect given
kind of the analogy with the
continuous-time case
namely its an exponential or rather a
sinusoidal
sequence with the a
real exponential on below in the case
were alpha
is positive then is a growing on below
in the case were out there is negative
I'm sorry
where the magnitude of alpha mang to
ralph is greater than one
is a growing exponential are below with
a magnitude about the
is less than 1 its a decaying
exponential are below and so I
demonstrated that here
here we have the magnitude about the
greater than one
and here we have the magnitude about the
less than 1
in both cases sinusoidal sequences
underneath the envelope
and then an envelope and is dictated
by what the magnitude about its
okay now in the discrete-time
case then we have results similar to the
continuous-time case
namely comp own it's a real or imaginary
part
that have a real exponential factor
times
a sinusoid of course
if the magnitude of alpha is
less than 1 I'm sorry the main to mouth
is equal to 1
then this factor disappears
always equal to one in this factor is
equal to 1
and so we have sinusoids in both the
real and imaginary parts
now one can ask whether
in general the complex exponential
with the magnitude about the equal to
one is periodically not periodic
and a clue to that can be inferred
by examining this expression
in particular in the discrete-time case
with the magnitude about equal to 1
we have pure sinusoids in the real
part in an imaginary part
and in fact in a continuous-time case
with are equal to 0
we have sinusoids in the real party
imaginary part
in a continuous-time case we have a pure
complex exponential
in fact so that so the terms are
exponentially growing your DK
back those exponentials are always
periodic because
the course the real and imaginary
sinusoidal Cup on its superior
in the discrete-time case we know that
the sinusoids may or may not be periodic
depending on the bad you love Omega 0
and so in fact
in the discrete-time case the
exponential
eat to the J Omega 0n
that i've indicated here may or may not
be periodic
depending on what the value Omega zeros
okay now to summarize
in this lecture I introduced and
discussed
a number of important basic signals
in particular sinusoids an real
and complex exponentials one of the
important outcomes
the discussion emphasize further in the
text is that
there are some very important
similarities between them
but there are also some very important
differences
and these differences will surface when
we exploit
sinusoids and complex exponentials
as basic building blocks for more
general continuous-time
in discrete-time signals in the next
lecture
what I'll discuss are some other very
important building blocks
namely what are referred to as
step signals an impulse signals and
does together with the sinusoidal
signals and exponentials as we've talked
about today
will really form the cornerstone
for essentially all love the signal and
system analysis
there will be dealing with for the
remainder the course thank you