the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home
the
the new the last time
we began the development love the
discrete-time
for EA transform and
just days with the continuous-time case
we first
treated the notion a periodic signals
this led to the forty a series
and then we generalize that to the
Fourier transform
and finally incorporated within the
framework for the four th
transform both a periodic and periodic
signals
in today's lecture but I'd like to do
is expand on some other properties
love for EA transform and indicate how
those properties are used for a variety
of things
well let's begin by reviewing the
Fourier transform
as we develop did last time it of course
involves
a synthesis equation and and analysis
equation
the synthesis equation expressing X a
van
the sequence in terms of the Fourier
transform
any analysis equation telling us how to
obtain
the Fourier transform from the original
sequence
and I draw your attention again to
the basic point that the synthesis
equation
essentially corresponds to decomposing
the sequence as a linear combination
of complex exponentials with amplitude
said are in effect
proportional to the 48 transport now
in the discrete-time Fourier transform
just as the continuous-time
for a transform has a number all
important and useful properties of
course
as i stress last time it's a function 0
a continuous variable and it's also a
complex-valued function
which means dead when we represented in
general
requires a representation in terms of
its
real part an imaginary part or in terms
of magnitude and angle
also as i indicated last time
the Fourier transform is
a periodic function of frequency
and the periodicity is
with a period up to par i and
so it says in effect dead the Fourier
transform if we replace the frequency
variable
by an integer multiple to pie
the function repeats and I stress again
that the underlying basis
for this periodicity property is the
fact
that its the setup complex exponentials
that are inherently periodic in
frequency
and so of course any representation
using them would
in effect generate a
periodicity with this period of two pi
just an is
in continuous-time the Fourier transform
has
important symmetry properties and in
particular
if the sequence x7 is
real value an the 4e
transform is conjugate symmetric
in other words if we replace Omega by
minus Omega
that's equivalent to applying complex
conjugation to the 48 transport and
as a cock consequence this conjugate
symmetry
this results in asymmetry
in the real part that is an even
symmetry
or the magnitude has an even symmetry
whereas the imaginary part or the phase
angle
is are are both art summit and these are
symmetry properties again
that are identical to the symmetry
properties that we saw in
continuous-time
well let's see this in the context I'll
an example that we worked last time and
that
will want to draw attention to
in reference to several issues is this
lecture goes along
and that is the Fourier transform all
a real damp expanding exponential
so the sequence that we
are talking about is a to the end you
have an
and let's consider a to be positive
we saw last time that the Fourier
transform from the for this sequence
algebraically is up this form
and if we look at its magnitude and
angle
the magnet to I show here
and the magnitude as we see has the
properties that we indicated
is and even function of frequency
course it's a function of a continuous
variable
and it in addition is periodic
with a period of two part
on the other hand if we look at the
phase angle below it
the phase angle has a symmetry which is
ought symmetric
and that's indicated clearly in this
picture
and of course in addition to being eyed
symmetric it naturally has to be
again a periodic function of frequency
with the period up to par
okay so we have some symmetry properties
we have this inherent periodicity in the
48 transform which
arms stressing very heavily because it
forms
the basic difference between
continuous-time and discrete-time
in addition to these properties have the
four EA transform
there are a number of other properties
day are particularly useful in
the manipulation of the 48 transform and
in fact
using the Fourier transform to for
example
an ally systems represented by when
you're past the coefficient difference
equations
bear in the text is a
longer list the properties but let me
just draw your attention
to several of them one
is the time shifting property
and the time shifting property tells us
dead
if Xserve Omega is the Fourier transform
objective and then the Fourier transform
are x7 shifted in time
is that same for EA transform multiplied
by
this factor which is a with your face
fact
so time-shifting introduces
a linear phase turn and by the way I
recall
that in the continuous-time case we had
a similar situation namely that a
timeshare
corresponded to a linear phase
there also is a dual to the time
shifting property
which is referred to as the frequency
which tells us dead if we
multiply a time function by a complex
exponential
that in effect generates
a frequency share and will see this
frequency shifting property
surface in a slightly different way
shortly
when we talk about the modulation
property in the discrete-time case
another important property that will
want to make you so
shortly is Lenny arity which follows in
a very straightforward way from
the Fourier transform definition
and the linearity property says simply
that the 48 transform of Assam
or linear combination is the same with
your combination the Fourier transforms
again that's a property that we saw in
continuous-time
and also among other properties
there is a parser balls relation for the
discrete-time case
then in effect says something similar to
continuous-time
specifically dead the energy E
in the sequence is proportional
to the energy E in the 48 transform
the energy over one period or said
another way
in fact or another way that it can be
said is
that the energy in the time domain is
proportional to the power
in his periodic for a transport
okay so these are some other properties
in and are the as i indicated parallel
somewhat properties that we saw in
continuous-time
two additional properties their will
play important roles
indiscreet I'm just as they did in
continuous-time
are the convolution property and the
modulation property
the convolution property is the property
that tells us
how to relate the Fourier transform
all the convolution two sequences
to the Fourier transforms of the
individual sequences
and not surprisingly what happens and
this can be
demonstrated algebraically not
surprisingly
the four EA transform above the
convolution
is simply the product of the Fourier
transforms
so Fourier transform maps
convolution in the time domain the
multiplication in the frequency domain
now convolutional courses arises in the
context of linear time-invariant systems
in particular if we have a system with
an impulse response a true fan
input excessive and the output is the
convolution
the convolution property then tells us
dead
in the frequency domain for EA transform
is the product love the Fourier
transform
the impulse response and the forty a
transformer the input
now we also saw
and have talked about a relationship
between
the Fourier transform the impulse
response and what we called
the frequency response
in the context love the response to the
system
to a complex exponential specifically
complex exponentials are I can functions
have linear time-invariant systems
wanna be's into the system gives us as
an output
a complex exponential with the same
complex frequency
multiplied by what you referred to as
the eye can value
and as you saw in the
video course manual this I can value
this constant multiplier
on the exponential is in fact
the 48 transform up the impulse response
evaluated at that frequency
now we saw exactly the same statement
in continuous-time and in fact we use
that statement the frequency response
interpretation
love the 48 trance for the impulse
response
we use that to motivate and intuitive
interpretation
of the convolution property now formally
the convolution property can be
developed by
taking the convolution some applying the
Fourier transforms into it
doing the appropriate substitution
variables in a changing order summations
Center in all the algebra
works out to show that it's a product
but as I stressed
when we discussed this with continuous
time the interpretation the underlying
interpretation
is particularly important to understand
so let me review it again
in the discrete-time case and it's
exactly the same
for discrete-time for continuous-time
specifically the argument was that the
Fourier transform
all a sequence or signal
corresponds to decomposing it into a
linear combination of complex
exponentials
what the airport to those complex
exponentials its
basically proportional to the four EA
transport
if we think a pushing through the system
that linear combination
then each love those complex
exponentials
gets the airport to modified are
multiplied
by the Fourier transform all up by the
frequency response
which we saw is the Fourier transform
love the impulse response
so the airport to up the output complex
exponentials
is then the amplitudes of the input
complex exponentials
multiplied by the frequency response
and the Fourier transform the output in
effect
is an expression its expressing the
summation
or integration of the output as a linear
combination of all of these exponentials
with the appropriate complex amplitudes
so its important in thinking about
the convolution property to think about
it in terms
a nothing more then the fact that we
decompose the input
and we're now modifying separately
through multiplication scaling
the airport to or each of the complex
exponential company
now what we saw in continuous time is
that this interpretation
and the convolution property
lead to an important concept namely the
concept the filtering
kind of the idea that if we decompose
the input as a linear combination of
complex exponentials
we can separately attenuator amplify
each of those compounds and in fact
we could exactly pass some center
frequencies and totally eliminate other
center frequencies
so again just as in continuous-time
we can talk about an ideal filter
and what I show here is the frequency
response
love idea low-pass filter
the idea low-pass filter of course
passes
exactly with a gain of one
frequencies around zero and eliminates
totally other frequencies
however an important distinction here
between continuous-time and
discrete-time
is the fact that whereas in continuous
time when we talked about an ideal
filter
we passed a band of frequencies and
totally eliminate everything else out to
infinity
in a discrete-time case the frequency
response
is periodic so obviously
the frequency response must periodically
repeat
the low low-pass filter and in fact we
see that here
if we look at the low-pass filter
then we've eliminated some frequencies
but then we passive course frequencies
around to pie and also frequencies
around minus 25 for that matter around
any multiple
to pie although it's important to
recognize
that because of the inherent periodicity
at the complex exponentials
these frequencies are exactly the same
frequencies
as these frequencies so
its low-pass filtering interpreted in
terms of frequencies over a range
from minus buy the pie
well just as we talk about a low-pass
filter we can also talk about
a high pass filter and a high pass
filter course with
past high frequencies
in a continuous-time case high
frequencies man frequencies that
go out to infinity in the discrete-time
case
course the highest frequencies we can
generate our frequencies up the pie
and wants are complex exponentials go
past pie
then in fact we start seeing the lower
frequencies again might be
indicate what I mean if we think
in the context of the low-pass filter
these are low frequencies
as we move along the frequency axis
these become high frequencies
and as we move further along the
frequency axis
what we'll see when we get to for
example frequency
to pie are the same low frequencies
that we see around zero a particular
then
a and i do. high pass filter in the
discrete-time case
would be a filter that eliminates these
frequencies
and passes frequencies around pie
okay so and we've seen the
convolution property and its
interpretation in terms of filtering
more broadly the convolution property in
combination
with a number of the other properties
today introduced in particular the time
shifting and when the arity property
allows us to generator analyzes
the an ally systems that are described
by linear constant coefficient
difference equations
and this again pareles very strongly
the discussion that we carried out in
the continuous-time
case their particular let's
think I love a discrete-time system
there is described by when your car is
the coefficient difference equation
and will restrict the initial conditions
on the equation
such that it corresponds to linear
time-invariant system
and recall that in fact in our
discussion
when your constant coefficient
difference equations
is the condition of initial rest
there on the equation that guarantees
4s that the system will be causal linear
and time-invariant
okay now let's consider
a first-order difference equation system
described by first-order difference
equation and we've talked about the
solution of this equation before
essentially we run the solution recur
simply
let's now consider generating the
solution by
taking advantage the properties the
forty a transport
well just as we did in continuous time
we can consider
applying to 48 transformed to both sides
of this equation
and the Fourier transform are why I have
been
courses y Omega and then using the
shifting
property the time shifting property the
Fourier transform why event -1
is y Omega multiplied by
you to the minus jail make and so we
have this
using the when the arity property we can
carry down the scale factor in and these
two together as they read it here
and forty a transformer victim and is XO
make
well Wii console this equation
the Fourier transform of the output in
terms of the Fourier transform
up the input and a
inappropriate complex scale factor and
simply solving this
for y Omega yields what we have here
now what we've used in going from this
point to this point
is both the shifting property
and we've also used the linearity
property
at this point we can recognize that
here the Fourier transform the output is
the product
the Fourier transform of the input and
some complex function and from the
convolution property
then that complex function must in fact
correspond to the frequency response
or acquittal atlee the 48 transform
love the impulse response so if we
wanted to determine the Fourier
transform
or the or where the impulse response to
the system
let's say for example then it becomes a
matter
love having identified the 4e a
transformer the impulse response which
is the frequency response
we now want to inverse transform to get
the impulse response
well how do we inverse transform of
course we could do it by attempting to
go through the synthesis equation
for the Fourier transform or we can do
is we did
in a continuous-time case which is to
take advantage
I love what we know and in particular
we know dead from an example that we
work before
this is in fact the 48 transform
all a sequence which is
a to the N times
you then and so in essence by inspection
very similar to what has going on can
in continuous-time essentially by
inspection
we can then solve for the impulse
response to the system
okay so that procedure follows very much
the kind of procedure that we've carried
out in continuous-time
and this is the course is discussed in
more detail
in the text well let's
a look at that example
then here we have the impulse response
for that for associated with the system
described by that particular
difference equation and to the right of
that
we have the Associated frequency
response
and one other things that we notice and
this is drawn for a
positive between 0&1 what we noticed in
fact is that
it is an approximation to
a low-pass filter because it tends to
attenuate
the high frequencies and retain and in
fact
amplify the low-frequency now
if instead actually the impulse response
was such that we picked a to be negative
between minus 10
and the impulse response in the time
domain looks like this
and the corresponding frequency response
looks like this and that becomes an
approximation
to a high pass filter
so in fact a first-order difference
equation
as we see has a frequency response
depending on the value obey
dad either looks approximately like a
low-pass filter for a positive or a high
pass filter for a negative
very much like the first order
differential equation
looked like a low-pass filter in the
continuous-time
case and in fact I'd like to illustrate
is the filtering characteristics
for example love filtering using
first-order difference equation
and the example that a lil astray
is filtering over sequence that in fact
is filtered very often
for a very practical reasons namely a
sequence which represents the Dow Jones
Industrial Average
over a fairly long period and
will process the Dow Jones Industrial
Average first
through first-order difference equation
where if we begin
with a sequel 0 then referring to the
frequency response
that we have here equal 0 would simply
be
passing all frequencies as a as positive
we start to retain mostly low
frequencies
and the larger a gets but still less
than 1
the more it attenuates high frequencies
at the expensive low frequencies
so let's watch the filtering first
with a positive and we'll see if behave
as a low pass filter and then
with a negative and we'll see
the difference equation behaving as a
high pass filter
what we see here is the Dow Jones
Industrial Average over
roughly a five year period from 1927 to
1930 to
and in fact that big dip in the middle
is the famous stock market crash of 1929
and we can see that following that in
fact the market continued
a very long downward trend and
what we now want to do is process this
through a difference equation
above the Dow Jones average we show the
impulse response to the difference
equation here
we've chosen the parameter a equal to 0
and the impulse response will be
displayed on
in expanded scale in relation to
the scale love the input and for that
matter the scale of the output
now with the impulse response shown here
which is just an impulse
in fact the output shown on the bottom
trace
is exactly identical to the input
and what will want to do now is increase
first the parameter a and the impulse
response
will begin to look like an exponential
with a duration: that's longer and
longer as
a moves from 0 to 1
correspondingly we will get more and
more low pass filtering as the
coefficient a
increases from 0 toward one so now
we are increasing the parameter a we see
that
the bottom trace in relation to the
middle trace in fact is
looking more and more smooth or
low-pass filtered and here now we have
a fair amount of smoothing to the point
where the stock market crash of 1929
is totally lost in fact I'm sure there
are many people who
wish that through filtering we could in
fact have avoided the stock market crash
altogether
now let's decrease
a from one back toward zero
and as we do that we will be taking out
the low-pass filtering and when they
finally reaches
0 the impulse response to the filter
will again
be in in polls and so the output will be
once again identical to the input
and that's where we are now
right now we want to continue to
decrease
a so that it becomes negative moving
from zero toward -1 and what we will see
in that case
is more and more high-pass filtering
on the output in relation to the input
and this will be particularly evident in
again
the region a pipe frequencies
represented by sharp transitions which
of course
the market crash goodnight 1929 would
represent
so here now a is decreasing
toward -1 we see that the high
frequencies
or rapid variations are emphasize
and finally let's move from -1
back toward zero taking out the
high-pass filtering
and ending up with
equal to 0 corresponding to an impulse
response which is an impulse
in other words and identity system and
let me stress once again that
the time scale on which we displayed the
impulse response
is an expanded time scale in relation to
the timescale
on which we displayed the input and the
output
okay so we see that in fact a
first-order difference equation is
a filter and in fact it's a very
important class the filters and its use
very often to do
approximate low-paying some high-pass
filtering
now in addition to
the convolution property another
important property that we had in
continuous-time and that we have in
discrete-time
is the modulation property the
modulation property tells us
what happens in the frequency domain
when
you multiply signals in the time domain
in continuous-time the modulation
property corresponded to the statement
that if we multiply in the time domain
we convolved the 48 transforms
in the frequency domain and in
discrete-time
we have very much the same
kinda relationship
the only real distinction between the
is is that in the discrete-time case
in carrying out the convolution its
integration
only over a two-party interval and
what that corresponds to is what's
referred to as
a periodic convolution
as opposed to the continuous-time case
where what we have is a convolution
that is a periodic on pollution
so again we have a convolution property
in discrete-time
that is very much like the convolution
property in continuous-time
the only real difference is that here
work involving
periodic functions and so
its a periodic convolution which
involves integration only over to pie
and herbal
rather than in immigration from minus
infinity the question
well let's and take a look at the
example love the modulation property
which will then
leave to one particular application and
a very useful application
love the modulation property in
discrete-time
example that I 12 pic is
example in which we consider modulating
a signal
with a signal with another signal
X evander x1 event as i indicated
here which is -1 to the end
essentially with that says is that
any signal which I modulate with this
effect corresponds to taking the
original signal
and then going through that signal
alternating
the algebraic sign
now we in in applying the modulation
property of course
what we need to do is develop the 48
transform
this signal this signal which I
rewrite I can ride either is -1 to the
air to rewrite is you DJ pie and since
you the J pie
is equal to -1 is a periodic signal
and if the periodic signal that I show
here
and recall that to get the 48 transform
other periodic signal
one way to do it is to
generate the forty a series coefficients
for the periodic signal
and then identify the Fourier transform
as an impulse train
where the heights of the impulses in the
impulse train
are proportional the proportionality
factor to pry
proportional 240 a series coefficients
so let's first workout what the for a
series is it for this example
in fact it's fairly easy here is
the general synthesis equation for
the forty a series and
if we take our particular example
where if we look back at the curve above
what we recognize is that the period
is equal to 2 merely repeat after two
points
then capital in is equal to two
and so we can just write this out with
the two turns
and the two terms involved are x1 a van
is a0
0 go fishin as cake 0
in a1 and this is with
cake was one we substituted in capital
an equal to two
right well we can do a little bit about
to bring here obviously
cross of the factors to and what we
recognize
if we compare this expression with
the original signal which is you the
j-pop I N
then we can simply identify the fact
dead
80 0 coefficient is zero that's the DC
term
and call fish in a1 is equal to 1
so we've done it simply by essentially
inspecting the for EA
series synthesis equation
okay now if we want to get the Fourier
transform for this we take those
coefficients
an essentially generate
an impulse train where we
chooses values for the impulses to pie
times the forty a series coefficients
so before a series coefficients array0
sequel to zero in a one is equal to 1
so noticed that in
the plot that I shown here above the 40
a transform
love x1 a band we have the zeroth
coefficient which happens to be 0
and so I haven't indicated impose
there we have the
coefficient a one and the coefficient a1
occurs at a frequency which is
Omega 0 and Omega 0 in fact is equal to
hi
because the signal is the the j-pop I N
well in what's this impulse over here
well any polls is ace
corresponds to the four-day series go
fishin a sieve -1
and of course if we drew this out
over a longer frequency axis we would
see lots of other impulses
because it the fact that the four th
transform periodically repeats
or equipment leader for a series
coefficients periodically
p so this is the coefficient
80 this is the coefficient
a one with a factor to pie this is 25
times a zero
and two pi times they won
and then this is simply an indication
that is periodically repeated
right now let's consider what happens if
we take a signal
and multiplier modulated by
-1 to the end well in the frequency
domain
that corresponds to a convolution
let's consider a signal x2 a van
which has a $4 EA transform as i've
indicated here
then the Fourier transform the product
affects 1 event next to %uh van is the
convolution
up these two spectra and
recall that if you can fall something
with an impulse train is this is that
simply corresponds to taking the
something
and placing it at the positions love
should the impulses so in fact
the result the convolution this with
this
would then be the spectrum their I
indicate here
namely this spectrum shifted up to pie
and of course two-minus by and then
of course to not only Piper three pie in
five
by et cetera et cetera and
so this spectrum finally corresponds to
the Fourier transform -1 to the end
times X to have an where x2 event is the
sequence
spectrum was x2 make
okay now this is in fact important
useful and interesting point what it
says is
I have a signal with a certain spectrum
and if I
modulate multiply that signaled by -1 to
the end
meeting that I alternate the signs then
it takes the low frequencies in effect
the ship's the spectrum by pie
so it takes the low frequencies and
moves them up the high frequencies
and will incidently take the high
frequencies and movement the low
frequency
so in fact we in essence saw this when
we
so or twenty talked about the example
love
a sequence which was aided the end times
you have an
notice let me draw your attention to the
fact dead
when a is positive we have
this sequence and its Fourier transform
is as II show on the right
for a negative
the sequence is
the identical to a positive but with
alternating signs
and the Fourier transform it that you
can now see
and verify also algebraically
if you'd like is identical to this
spectrum
simply shifted by pie
so it says in fact that multiplying
that impulse response or if we think
I've a positive and a negative
that is algebraically similar to
multiplying
the impulse response by -1 to the end
and in the frequency domain
the affected that essentially is
shifting the spectrum by pie
we can interpret that in the context
that the modulation property
now it's interesting that
what that says is there
if we have system which corresponds to
a low-pass filter as i indicated here
with an impulse response a true fan
and its it can be any approximation to a
low pass filter and even an idea Lopez
filter
if we want to convert that to a high
pass filter
we can't do that by generating a new
system
whose impulse response is -1 to the end
times the impulse response the low-pass
filter
and this modulation
by -1 to the end will take the frequency
response
this system and shifted by popeye
so that what's going on here at low
frequencies
will now go on here at high frequency
this also says incidently dead if
we look at
the a and idea low-pass filter and i do.
high pass filter
and we choose the cutoff frequencies for
comparison
for the band with the filter to be equal
since this ideal high pass filter is
this idea low-pass filter with the
frequency response shifted
by popeye the modulation property tells
us
that in the time domain with that
corresponds to
is an impulse response multiplied five
minus one to the S
so it says that the impulse response
love the high-pass filter or quently the
inverse Fourier transform
love a high pass filter frequency
response
is -1 to the end times the
impulse response to the low-pass filter
that all follows for the modulation
property
now there's another way interesting and
useful way
that modulation can be used to
implement or convert from low pass
filtering the high-pass filtering
the modulation property tells us about
multiplying the time domain is shifting
in the frequency domain
and the example that we happen to pick
said if you multiply
or modulate by -1 to the end that takes
low frequencies and ship them to
high-frequency
what that tells us it as a practical and
useful
notion is the following suppose we have
a system
that we know is a low pass filter and
it's a good luck this
how might we use it as a high pass
filter
well one way to do it instead of
shifting its frequency response
is to take the original signal
shift its low frequencies the high
frequencies and its high frequencies the
low frequencies
by multiplying the input signal the
original signal by -1 to the yen
process that with the low-pass filter
we're now with sitting at the low
frequencies with a high frequencies
and then unscramble it all at the output
so that we put the frequencies back
where they belong
and I summarize that here let's suppose
for example that
this system was a low-pass filter in and
so it low pass filters whatever comes
into it
down below I indicate taking the input
and first interchanging
the high and low frequencies through
modulation with -1 to the end
doing a low-pass filtering which and
what sitting at the low frequencies here
with a high frequencies
this signal and then after the low-pass
filtering
moving the frequencies back where they
belong
by again modulating with -1 to the end
and that in fact turns out to be a very
useful
a very useful notion for
applying a fixed low pass filter
to do high-pass filtering and vice versa
okay no
what we've seen and what we've talked
about
are the for a representation for
discrete-time signals and prior to that
continuous-time say and we've seen some
very important similarities and
differences
and what I'd like to do is conclude
this lecture by summarizing
those various relationships kinda ball
in one package
and in fact drawing your attention to
both the similarities and differences
and comparisons between
well let's begin in this summary
by first looking at the continuous-time
for a series in a continuous time for a
series
we have a periodic time function
expanded as a linear combination of
harmonically related complex
exponentials
and there are an infinite number these
that are required to do the
decomposition
and we saw and analysis equation which
tells us
how to get these four EA series
coefficients
through an integration on the original
time
and notice in this that what we have
is a continuous periodic timer function
what we end up with
are in the frequency domain is a
sequence a Fourier series coefficients
which in fact
is an infinite sequence namely requires
all values
K in general
we had then generalized that to the
continuous time for EA transform
an ineffective doing that what happened
is that
the synthesis equation in the four EA
series became
integral relationship in the Fourier
transform
and we now have a continuous-time
function which is no longer periodic
this was for the a periodic case
represented as a linear combination up
infinite has only close and frequency
complex exponentials with complex
amplitudes given by Eq civil make it the
Omega divided by two pi
and we had of course the corresponding
analysis equation the told us how to get
exe below me here
we have a continuous-time function which
is a periodic
and a continuous function of frequency
which is a periodic
the conceptual strategy in a
discrete-time case
was very similar with
so differences resulting in the
relationships because of some inherent
differences between
continuous-time and discrete-time we had
we began with the discrete-time for you
series
corresponding to representing a periodic
sequence
through a set of complex exponentials
where now we only required a finite
number of the
is because the fact that in fact with
there are only a finite number of
harmonically related complex
exponentials
that's an inherent property
discrete-time complex exponentials
and so we have a discrete
periodic type function and we ended up
with a set of 48 series coefficients
which of course are discrete as for a
series coefficients are
and which periodically repeat because it
the fact
that the Associated complex exponentials
periodically
repeat we then
used in arguments similar to the
continuous-time case
for going for periodic time fortunes a
periodic time
functions and we ended up with a
relationship
describing representation for a periodic
discrete-time signals in which now
the synthesis equation went from a
summation to an integration
says the frequencies are now if it
hasn't we close
involving frequencies only over to pry
interval
and for which the amplitude factor Xa
bomb-maker
well the apathy factors X will make it
the Omega divided by two pi
and this term Mexico may go which is the
48 transform
is given by this some Asian
and course involves all of the values
affects a bit
and so the important difference between
the continuous-time and discrete-time
case kinda rose in part to the fact that
discrete I miss discrete-time
continuous-time is continuous time
and the fact the complex exponentials a
periodic
in discrete-time the harmonically
related ones periodically repeat
whereas they don't in continuous time
now this among other things has an
important consequence for duality
and let's go back again and look at this
equation
despair equations clearly their
is no duality between these two
equations
this involves a summation this involves
an integration
and so in fact if
we make reference to to our the
their isn't the reality in the
continuous-time
for a series however
for the continuous-time for EA transform
we're talking about a periodic timer
functions in a periodic frequency
functions
and in fact we look at these two
equations we see very definitely duality
in other words the time function
effectively
is the Fourier transform the four th
transport
little time reversal in there but
basically that's the result
and in fact we had exploited that
duality property
when we talked about the continuous-time
for EA transport
with the discrete-time Fourier series
we have a duality
indicated by the fact that we have a
periodic time function
and a sequence which is
periodic in the frequency domain and in
fact if you look at these two
expressions
you see the duality very clearly and so
ants the discrete-time Fourier series
that has to do our D and
finally the discrete-time Fourier
transform loses the duality
because the fact among other things then
in the time domain
things are inherently discrete whereas
in the frequency domain
they are inherently continuous so in
fact here
there is no do well
okay now that says that there's a
difference in the duality
continuous-time and discrete-time and
there's one
more very important peace to
the duality relationship and we can see
that
first algebraically by comparing
the continuous-time for a series
and the discrete-time for EA transport
the continuous time for a series
in the time domain is a periodic
continuous function
in the frequency domain is in a periodic
sequence
in the discrete-time case in
the time-domain we have
and a periodic sequence
and in the frequency domain we have a
function as a continuous variable
which we know is periodic and so in fact
we have in the time domain here a
periodic sequence
in the frequency domain we have to
continue with periodic function
and in fact if you look at the
relationship between these two
and and what we see in fact is
a duality between
the continuous-time for EA series
and the discrete-time for EA transport
one way of thinking if that is to kind
of think
this is a little bit at a time twister
which you might want to get straightened
out
slowly but
the Fourier transform a discrete-time is
a periodic function of frequency
that periodic function has a forty a
series representation
what is this for you series what are the
for a series coefficients
that periodic function well in fact
except for an issue with time reversal
what it is
is the original sequence for which
that's the 48 Reitz
and that is the duality that I'm trying
to emphasize
you
okay well so what we see is that these
four sets a relationship all tied
together in a whole variety of ways
and we will be exploiting as the
discussion goes on the
interconnections a relationship that
i've talked about
also as we've talked about the 48
transform both continuous-time and
discrete-time
two important properties that we focus
on among
many other properties by the convolution
property in the modulation property
we've also shown that the convolution
property
the so very important concept
namely filtering the modulation property
leads to an
an important con- concept namely
modulation
we've also very briefly indicated
that how these properties
and how these concepts have practical
implications
in the next several lectures will focus
and more specifically
first on filtering and then on
modulation
and as we'll see the filtering and
modulation concept
form really the cornerstone %uh many
many
signal processing ideas thank you