the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home for the
in
the
the in
in
the
are the
in the last lecture we begin
the discussion love modulation and in
particular what we focused on
was the continuous-time case and in
talking about continuous-time modulation
we covered a number of topics we talked
about
the properties and analysis love
modulation when we had a complex
exponential
carrier signal we talked about the
properties and analysis in the case of a
sinusoidal carrier
and in that context and related to
the application associated with
communications
we talked about synchronous modulation
a synchronous modulation and
also the notion love single sideband
modulation in
the lecture today there are to issues
that I'd like to address broad topics
one is Acer parallel discussion
particularly is associated with complex
exponential sinusoidal modulation
for discrete-time signals and
the second is the introduction and
analysis
love a another kind of carriers
specifically a post kind of carrier
in continuous time leading to the
notions of pulse amplitude modulation
and eventually a very powerful theramin
result called the sampling there
well let me begin the lecture though
focusing on
the discrete-time modulation to
essentially
draw your attention to the fact dead the
analysis and discrete-time
very much parallels the analysis in
continuous-time
well let's consider in the discrete-time
case just as we had in continuous-time a
signal modulating a carrier signal
and the resulting modulated signal
is why event and it was
in continuous-time the modulation
property
Associated with the four EA transform
dead
provided the basis for the analysis and
exactly the same thing is true in a
discrete-time
case in particular what we have in
is the modulation property as it relates
to the Fourier transform
which tells us that the four EA
transform of the modulated signal
is the convolution all the
for a transformer the carrier and the 48
transform or
the modulating signal and the only real
difference in issue here
is that in the discrete-time case
what we're talking about is a periodic
convolution because the specter of
course a periodic
whereas in a continuous-time case it was
an a periodic convolution so let's
parallel the discussion and in
particular what will focus on
is first a complex exponential
carrier and second a
sinusoidal carrier and we'll see how
this parallels our discussion in
continuous-time
and will make fairly brief reference as
we introduce
the post carrier for continuous-time
will bring make very brief reference to
the post carrier for discrete-time
indicating that again the analysis and
discrete-time and continuous-time
is very parallel soul let's first
consider
complex exponential and sinus all
carriers
for the discrete-time case emphasizing
the very strong parallel and similarity
between
discrete-time and continuous-time well
we have once again the modulation
property
and the modulation property tells us
that the spectrum
all the modulated signal is the periodic
convolution love the two spectra
and let's consider for example
an input for modulating spectrum as i've
indicated here
and since we what to consider first the
fall
a complex exponential carrier
will consider the case of CNN
equal to each to the J Omega subsea
n and let me stress by the way as
I did in the continuous-time case
dead out 10 to suppress the phase angle
which of course can be associated with
the carrier also
alright so we have then the spectrum
%uh the modulating signal the spektr the
carrier signal
if this is the carrier then its spectrum
is an impulse train
and then imposed strain I've indicated
here and let me stress also that in
the discrete-time case of course the
spectra
and all of the spektr involved are
periodic with period of two pi
so this then is the spectrum of the
carrier signal
this is the spectrum the input signal
the periodic convolution if these two
is the spektr on the modulated signal
and the result
is then this spectrum shifted
to center frequency which is the carrier
frequency
Omega subsea so
the result love modulation with a
complex exponential
is a straightforward shifted the
spectrum
to a carrot to so that what occurred
around
zero frequency now occurs around the
frequency Omega subsea
now in the continuous-time k sweetie
modulated
with the case when we had a complex
exponential carrier weedy modulated
by essentially just shifting the
spectrum back
and he in fact in the discrete-time case
were able to do exactly the same thing
so if we work to replace
see a van which is huge and make a
subsidy and
by see a very cozy the minus J Omega
CN the resulting spectrum
would be an impulse train
as i indicate here and
the result all multiply why I have an
by that new carrier
in the frequency domain is a convolution
if these two
and its relatively straightforward to
verify that
if you can follow these for the periodic
convolution
then that will get us back to the
original spectrum that we started with
so what's happened in the discrete-time
case for the complex exponential
is exactly the same as in
continuous-time
namely we might too late that
corresponds to shifting the spectrum
weedy modulate by multiplying by the
complex conjugate
the original modulating care the
original carrier
and that shifts the spectrum back to
where it was originally
okay now let's consider the case of a
sinusoidal carrier in discrete-time
and again things very much parallel
what we saw in continuous-time
and again as we look at the specter
I will choose a phase angle 0
mainly for notational an analytical
convenience
so in this case now rather than
a carrier signal which is a single
complex exponential
it's now a sinusoidal carrier and the
sinus or carrier is the summer too
complex exponentials
and so if we consider a modulating
spectrum that is the specter affects a
van
as something are the type that I
indicate here
and the spectrum of the carrier
now since the carrier is sign a soil
rather than
a complex exponential consists of two
impulses
wanted pasta makers see and one at minus
Omega subsea
convolved ing this spectrum with this
spectrum
gives us a replication affective Omega
around plus and minus Omega subsea
and incidently with an ample to change a
hair
so again things have
worked as they did in continuous-time
in continuous time or in discrete-time
modulating with a sinusoidal carrier
with then correspond to a replication of
the spectrum
around plus the carrier frequency and
replication the spectrum
around minus the carrier frequency in
both cases
as long as the carrier frequency is
large enough compared with the band with
the signal
so that those two replications don't
overlap
then its reasonable to suppose
that we should be able to recover the
original signal
well in fact to d modulate
in the discrete-time case we would again
follow very much the strategy that we
did in continuous-time
in particular let's consider the
modulating
by taking the modulated signal
and again putting it through modulator
again
with a carrier which is co-signed Omega
CN
if we do that we have a the modulator
or what will turn out to be part of the
modulator as i indicate here
the spectrum or the import signal
is as I had just developed a replication
up the original spectrum around plus and
minus Omega subsea
with an amplitude of the hair when this
is again convolved with the spectrum
love the carrier then
we get a replication of the original
spectrum
first around zero frequency as i
indicate here
and then around twice the carrier
frequency
and minus twice the carrier frequency
and as long as the carrier frequency
is large enough compared with the
with of the original signal day and as
you can see
by extracting this part of the spectrum
with the low-pass filter we can in
principle
recover the spectrum associated with the
original signal
and again justice in continuous-time
because this amplitude is a half
we would want to choose for scaling
purposes
a low-pass filter ample to which is
to to compensate for this factor in the
hair
so once again things work at basically
the same way as they had in
continuous-time
we have sinusoidal modulation
which consists love using a sinusoidal
carrier
and we have the the modulator
which consists of taking the modulated
signal
multiplying by the carrier and then
processing Matt with a low-pass filter
to extract the portion of the spectrum
which is around zero frequency as i
indicate in the spectra below
and the result then with this low pass
filter having a gain of two
is that we've recovered the original
spectrum
exit Omega which is the spectrum
that we started now
several other things to stress this is a
fairly quick
to we're through sinusoidal modulation
for discrete-time
in there are very similar issues that
arise in
the discrete-time case in terms of love
having faced synchronization
and frequency synchronization between
the modulator and demodulator
and we had discussed that in a fair
amount of detail for the continuous-time
case in some sense in practical terms
that becomes much more than issue in
continuous-time
than it does in discrete-time in part
because
synchronization between a modulator and
demodulator
is often much harder in a
continuous-time
system which is essentially an analog
system
as compared with a digital system
another
very important reason and it's important
to stress this at the outset
is that whereas the theory involving
the use of complex exponentials
sinusoidal modulation
parallels very strongly in the
continuous-time
and the discrete-time case in practical
terms
it has much more significance in
continuous-time
than it does in discrete-time that is
the notion
love sinusoidal modulation in the
context of communication systems
is extremely important for
continuous-time systems
and less so in discrete-time systems
now kinda as a preview of a point to be
raise later on
I should modify that slightly with the
statement
that one very important plays in which
sinusoidal modulation in a discrete-time
context the rises
is in a class of systems called trance
multiplexers or trans modulation systems
and this surface is basically because
so many communication systems are now
becoming digital and specifically
discrete-time although the actual
transmission is continuous time
the signal processing manipulation
switching
is discrete-time it so in fact it turns
out
to be very important and useful to take
a discrete-time representation I love
the analog signals a continuous-time
signals
and in a discrete-time or digital
representation
convert them from one modulation scheme
41 multiplexing scheme to another and
although I said a lot there that
really requires much more detail to
to develop in any in any sense at all
you should come to get the notion that
that discrete-time
modulation systems become very important
in part because or implementation Elis
use
okay now there is another application
dead we have discussed for both
continuous time actually previously for
discrete-time
amplitude modulation with sinusoidal or
complex exponential carriers
and let me just remind you that because
in fact it becomes a very important one
in the case love discrete-time systems
and that is the notion love using
modulation together with fixed filtering
to implement a filter which is
which either has a variable cut off or
converts let's say a low-pass filter to
a high pass filter
we originally talked about this when we
introduce the modulation property
in the context of converting a low-pass
filter
to a high pass filter and the notion was
that if we modulate the signal
with a carrier which is -1 to the end
and that's just simply complex
exponential
or sinusoidal carrier with a carrier
frequency of pie
than that in effect interchanges the low
frequencies in the high frequencies
and if and after modulation
that is processed with a low pass filter
and then the result is d modulated
using exactly the same carrier namely a
carrier which is
-1 to the end
then the effective that is equivalent
to high-pass filtering on the original
signal
and a generalization a bad would involve
instead a
this specific choice if -1 to the end
would involve a choice in general or the
e to the J Omega sed CNN
that is a more general carrier frequency
and
d modulator which is either the minus J
Omega subsea and and as i've represented
here
and as we had talked about it when we
talked about the modulation property for
discrete-time signals
we had specifically chosen the
conversion of a low pass to a high pass
filter
well let me continue the review of that
just by reminding you of the details of
what happens with the spectra
and specifically the notion
if we take this particular case omega-6
equal
to pie or covertly a carrier signal
which is -1 to the end
then if we have the original spectra
and the specter all
specter of the carrier signal the
spectrum of the carrier signal
convolved with this spectrum
will then in effect shift this by
pie and so after
modulating the result that we have is
shifted that spectrum so that what
happened at low frequencies now happens
at high frequencies namely around pie
and what happens at what happened at
high frequencies now happens
at low frequencies well if thats process
now
with a low pass filter and this dashed
line indicates the low-pass filter
then the result that we get is shown
here
where we've extracted the low-frequency
portion of the modulated signal
and now when we modulate or D modulate
back
then this spectrum is shifted back to
where it belongs
namely its shifted back to be centered
around
minus pie and around plus Park
so if we just compare this spectrum
with the original spectrum at the top
what we can see is that in effect what
we've done
is to extract a portion of the spectrum
acquittal and the processing with a high
pass filter
and again this is very similar to what
we did in continuous-time
and all of the kinda analytical
processes and
and convolutions involved are very much
the same
really the biggest difference between
continuous-time and discrete-time
has to do not so much with the details
of the analysis but
perhaps has more to do with issues
love are practical applications
okay well so what we've done
so far for continuous-time and
discrete-time
is to talk about modulation amplitude
modulation
with complex exponential and sinus or
carriers
we saw that the analysis is very similar
although
applications are slightly different and
now what I'd like to turn to
is a different choice love
carrier signal and the carrier signal in
this particular case
is a post rain rather than
a sinusoidal signal now
the idea is the following
in general of course the modulator
it consists all multiplying x50
by whatever the carrier signal is and
previously we've talked about a carrier
signal which is sinusoidal
the carrier signal that we want to
consider now
is a carrier signal which in fact is
a pulse train and so in fact
what we want to do is multiply the input
signal
by a Paul strain and in effect then
the modulated signal consists
of the original signal simply with time
slices pulled out a bit as i've
indicated in the bottom Kurt
so what we have now
is a modulated signal
that is a chopped or sliced version
love the original waveform and
think that is what's referred to as
pulse amplitude modulation
now it seems like it's kinda crazy idea
any ideas
search opt-out slices away form and
the hope that you can kinda put things
back together again
and the amazing thing about it is we'll
see is that in fact
under fairly broad general and
applicability
conditions you really can put the way
for back together again
if you just have these times places
not only that but that basic notion
as we'll see is independent in fact
up with the with the those time slices
or effect the with can go to zero
and in fact we're going to make the with
go to zero and really only dependent
on what the frequency love the polls
trainers
so let's explore that in some detail
and what we want to look at is the
analysis but let me
let me first just comment very briefly
there
all the analysis we go through as has
been true in the case a sinusoidal
modulation all the analysis that we go
through
holes just as well with
especially minor analytical
modifications to
discrete-time pulse amplitude modulation
as it does to
continuous-time pulse amplitude
modulation
and so will really only go through this
in terms of tracking the way for
inspector for the continuous-time
case but bear in mind that the results
are basically similar
for discrete-time okay well
let's see how we get the basic result
that we want to get
what we have is a
modulating signal which is a pulse train
basically a square wave
and as we've seen in previous lectures
the spectra
or Fourier transform associated with
that is an impulse train
and the envelope that impulse train
is over for over sin x over X function
the four th transform is impulses and
the spacing of the impulses
is Associated with the fundamental
frequency
all the Paul strain and thats Omega
Sappi so make it appears to pride
divided by the period
the pulse train and at the
amplitude and shape but this envelope is
dictated
by that parameter Delta
which has to do with how wide the pulses
are
okay so we have a time function
it's multiplied by this post rain now
we're talking continuous-time
so in the frequency domain
we have the Fourier transform the time
function convolved with
this Fourier transform for the pulse
train and let's see what that looks like
if we were to consider let's say
a Fourier transform which I A kinda
chosen is more or less a general one
then in fact when we can follow this
with this simple strain what we end up
with
is a replication all
this spectrum at
the places in the frequency domain
where the individual impulses occurred
so we can see that this spectrum is
replicated at each's
these locations and as long as
the frequency
above the post-training is large enough
compared
with a maximum frequency in the
original single X if T so that there is
no overlap between these triangles
then what you can see in fact somewhat
amazingly
is dead simply by low-pass filtering the
result
we can get back except for an amplitude
factor
we can give get back to the original
signal
now it's amazing it really is amazing
dead all that this depends on
is the original signal being banned
limited
and the frequency the post-training be
high enough
so that when you replicate the spectrum
in the frequency domain
is no overlap between these individual
replications and will
have a dress that a little more in a few
minutes
but let me first the ball point out that
this has a whole variety a very
important implications
one is in the context of communications
it leads to another very important
multiplexing scheme for communications
we talked last time about
frequency division multiplexing where
individual signals were put into
individual frequency slots
by choosing different carrier
frequencies for sinusoidal modulated
signal
what this suggests is that what we can
do
is put the
sons put different signals into
non-overlapping time slots
and in fact be able to recover the
original signals back again
so in particular suppose that
I had a signal which I modulated with a
pulse train
and I i chose another signal modulated
with another poll strain
where the time slot was different and I
continue this process
and after the after i'd done this with
some number of channels
simply and it all those together
as i indicate here then as long as I
knew what time slots to associate with
what signal
I could get the original a
modulated signals back again
and then as long as the frequency 0
the impulse train was such that
I was able to do this reconstruction
by simply low-pass filtering then
I would be able to be my Julie so it's a
very different very important modulation
scheme call time division
multiplexing in contrast to frequency
division multiplexing as we talked about
last time
I made reference earlier the concept of
Trance multiplexing and in fact
what happens in many communication
systems
is dead the signals are represented in
fact
in discrete-time the analog continues
time signals are represented in
discrete-time
and very often the conversion from
frequency division multiplexing to time
division multiplexing and back
is done in fact in the discrete-time to
me
okay so what we have then
is the notion
dead we can
multiply a time function
by a poll strain as i indicated here
and from the output I can
if the frequency this post rain is high
enough in relation to this band with
from the output which consists of both
time slices from those times places
I can recover the original signal
stressing again the reason it relates
to the spectra and
the reason is dead the original spectra
is simply replicated at
multiples all the fundamental frequency
upholstery
now is a very important thing to observe
here
which is dead the ability to do the
reconstruction
is associated with the notion of whether
we can extract that
kinda central triangle light happened
choose a triangular shape but
obviously I could be talking about any
shape as long as it's been limited
the ability to extract at and notice
that in this modulated output spectrum
the ability to recover this is totally
independent
all what the value of Delta is in other
words
if we look back at
the modulator then
in fact we can make Delta
the with these pulses arbitrarily small
and in theory that doesn't affect
our ability to do the reconstruction now
in practical terms it might
looking back once more at the specter of
the output
noticed that this sample to is
proportional to Delta
and what that suggests is that as we
make
Delta smaller and smaller which we
might in fact want to do if you want to
time division multiplexed last two
channels
in principle in theory you could make it
an infinite number channels just by
making an infinitesimally small
the smaller it is in some sense the less
energy there is and again
in practical terms this one of those
things if you push down here pops up
there
namely you eventually run into issues
such as noise problems
so more more typically what's done is
to in fact eliminate the scale factor a
delta
and the way that that's done is very
simply
it's done by choosing
the with I love the pulses
and the height %uh the pulses in such a
way
dead the area is constant even as
we make Delta get arbitrarily small so
and we can just modify our argument
so that what we're referring to is a
modulating post rain
which is a pulse train with positive
with Delta
and height one over Delta in that case
as Delta gets arbitrarily small
then in fact what these rectangles
become
are impulses in which case what we're
talking about
is a carrier signal
which in fact is an impulse train
and the resulting modulated signal
is and imposed strain for which the
amplitudes
of the impulses are proportional to
the original input waveform at
the times at which these impulses occur
okay well let's look at the analysis a
bat
and so now what we're talking about
is a spectrum
dead up
consists all the result
love the spectrum we talked about before
the sin x over X envelope except
that now is Delta goes to zero that
becomes
flat in other words the modulating
signal is an impulse train
and so as we look at the spectrum
the modulating signal that is then
and impose train in the frequency domain
the high
is proportional to the frequency
up the impulse train and Omega the best
now denotes
the frequency the impulse train and
the resulting output the modulator
has a spectrum which is
this original spectrum again replicated
around
each love these impulses in other words
replicated in multiples
or the sampling frequency now
this is very much identical to the more
general case we have
this replication the spectra
and as long as
this sample the the frequency of the
impulse train is
large enough compared with the band with
the signal
so that these triangles don't overlap
I can extract this
portion of the spectrum by low-pass
filtering
which in fact with then give us back
the original signal now
if instead this frequency Omega sed am
is greater than Omega best minus Omega
sed am
we would have a spectrum that looked
something more like this and what's
happened
in this case is that because
we have an overlap here we've destroyed
the ability
to recover the original signal from the
impulse train
and that would be true also in general
in a more general case
love pulse amplitude modulation with
pulses that up 90 with
this effect by the way is one that will
be
exploring in considerably more detail in
the next lecture and
it's a phenomenon or distortion referred
to as a leasing which
in fact is important and interesting
topic but
going back to the case in which we've
chosen the frequency of the upholstery
in high enough
then we would recover the original
signal
by processing it through
a low-pass filter
and in in that case
what this says is dead if we have a
signal
and we modulated with an impulse train
if we then process that impulse train
through an ideal ok pass filter
given the right conditions on Sat on the
frequency the impulse train and the band
with the signal
we can recover the original signal back
again
now let me stress just going back to
the picture in which we have done this
modulation
that this process where the modulation
where the carrier signal involves an
impulse train is
often referred to as sampling and
what that mean specifically is dead
if we notice this resulting in polls
train
is in fact a sequence
all samples all
the original continuous-time signal in
other words
what we've done in effect is taken
instantaneous samples at this way form
and the implication is that if we do
that
at a rapid and afraid in relation
to the band with the signal then
we can in fact recover the original
signal back again
and finally to remind you
I'll the argument once more
we have an original signal
and we have its spectrum when we've
sampled it and this is now the sampled
signal it's an impulse train whose
instantaneous values
are samples at the original waveform the
spectrum a bad
is the original one replicated
and when that is processed through a
low-pass filter to extract this part of
the spectrum
then after the low-pass filter we can
recover the original signal back again
okay well in fact me although
a if you kinda follow through
the specter and the waveforms this all
seems fairly
straightforward and perhaps
or perhaps not obvious
it's really worth reflecting on how
amazing
the result really is what it says we
begin this discussion
by talking about modulation and in fact
modulation and sinusoidal modulation is
important in its own right
we ended the discussion by talking
about first pulse amplitude modulation
and then showing how under the right set
of conditions
you can in fact take away form and
sample it with a set of instantaneous
samples
and that said instantaneous samples in
fact
are sufficient totally represent and
reconstruct the signal
what in fact the formal statement that
is
is referred to as the sampling theorem
very powerful their own that says
if were given equally spaced samples
over time function
and if that time function is band
limited
and if the band with
or is or if this if this sampling
frequency is
chosen in the right way in relation
to the
band with then in fact
the original time function is
uniquely recoverable with a low-pass
filter
now the sampling theorem is kinda
I would say a watershed a cornerstone
love a lot of the discussion we've been
having
for a whole variety of reasons if first
of all crops out almost as kind as
straightforward obvious statement but
more importantly
what it says is dead
if I have a continuous-time signal which
satisfies the right-center conditions
I can represent it by what it does
at sampling instance or acquittal only
at discrete
is this a time
now what that leads to
is a whole host of things wanna which
is the statement that says if we have a
continuous-time signal
I could in fact represented
as a discrete-time signal and I could
even think
love processing a continuous-time signal
using discrete time concepts
and when I'm all done converting back
through
the power the sampling theorem
converting back to a continuous-time
sick
so the sampling theorem provides this
with a very major important bridge
between
continuous-time and discrete-time
implementations and ideas
in the next several lectures we will be
exploring so this in considerable detail
first the focus in more next time
on some with the specific issues and
distortions associated with sampling and
following that
a discussion are what is referred to as
discrete-time processing of
continuous-time signals
thank you