the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU ha
in
the norm
are
the
in the last lecture we discussed
sinusoidal
and real in complex exponential signals
both
for continuous-time and discrete-time no
signals will form very
important building blocks when we
return to the discussion love Fourier
analysis and later lectured
in today's lecture I'd like to introduce
some additional basic signals
specifically
the unit step and unit impulse signal
let's begin
with discrete-time and the discrete-time
units that
in unit in polls the discrete-time unit
step
is a sequence is a indicated here
specifically
a sequence which is zero for
negative values if its argument and
equal to 1
for positive values up its argument and
so mathematically
the unit step sequence is one
for in greater than or equal to 0 and 0
for and less than zero the unit impulse
sequence
likewise is defined in a straightforward
way
the union Paul sequence is a sequence
which
is 0 for all values if its argument
except for an equal 0 so
the unit step in unit impulse sequence
are defined in a straightforward way
mathematically and in fact in they are
also related
to each other in a straightforward way
mathematically
specifically the unit in paul's
can be related to the unit step
through the relationship that i've
indicated here
Beltre van the unit impulse
equal to units that minus the unit
stepped away
so mathematically the relationship
is what is referred to as a first
difference
and to see the validity love this
expression
we can simply looking at the unit step
and it's the late version so
here we show the unit step you then
here we show the unit step delayed
by one so it 0 for and less than or
equal to 0
and clearly if we subtract that the late
step
from the original unit step everything
subtract out except at
an equal 0 which at which point the
difference is equal to 1
and so the difference between you have
an
and you then -1 is simply the unit
impulse sometimes incidently also
referred to as the unit sample
now
in a similar way we can
express the unit step in terms of the
unit impulse and there are several ways
of doing this
one-way is through a relationship
referred to as a running start
what I mean by that is
the following expression: if we
think love morning
some from minus infinity
up to some bad UN
all a unit in paul's
our unit sample then this running some
in fact is equal to the unit step
and we can see that in a
fairly straightforward way by simply
observing
dead in this expression when and is less
than 0
is nothing accumulated in the some
and we can see that graphically as
they've shown here
so for and less than zero we accumulate
no turns into some
whereas for an greater than
0 we cumulate one non-zero value in the
some
namely the value of the unit sample at
an equal 0
so we have then
one expression for the relationship
between the unit step in the unit sample
we can also develop another relationship
by observing
in essence there if we look at the unit
step sequence
as I've returned to hear weekend
in effect think the unit step sequence
as a six-session love unit
impulses one following another so
if we consider
forming Assam
all the lady impulses as i indicate
mathematically here
and as i indicate graphically down below
we have an impulse here at an equal 0
and an impulse here and any calls one
and impose here at any cost to et cetera
and when we continue to add these up
then what they add up to is the
unit step sequence and so mathematically
then
that would correspond to and im polls
that an equal 0
plus an impulse to 10 equals 1 was an
impulse
at any calls to et cetera now in this
in continuous-time we have a very
more or less similar situation we
will find it equally useful to talk
about a
unit step continuous-time signal and
the unit impulse continues time signal
let's begin
with the continuous-time unit step be
continuous-time unit step function is
graphically
indicated as I've shown here it's a time
function
which is 0 party less than zero
and it's one for T greater than 0
and so mathematically what it
corresponds to
is you if he defined as
a time function which is zero for T less
than zero
one pretty greater than 0
now an obvious question is what happens
at Evil zero and the difficulty here
which is not a difficulty that arises in
the discrete-time
case is that act equal 0
the unit step function is in fact
discontinuous
which generates a variety mathematical
problems
and one can define the units that
at equal zero in a variety ways
but the essential point is that the unit
step function
is discontinuous so in effect
what we need to do is think if the unit
step function
as the limit all a continuous function
and so we can define a function which I
specify here
as use a delta see
and used to build the T is a time
function
which is 0:40 less than zero
linearly increases to time Delta
which would correspond to this
breakpoint and then
one following that and so
we can think then love the discontinuous
units step
as the limiting form use a delta at:
as Delta goes to zero
now we also wanted to find a
unit impulse function and it had a
fairly straightforward definition
in discrete-time in continuous time
things get
slightly more difficult and to motivate
the definition
let me return to the discrete-time
definition
all or the rather the discrete-time
relationship between
the unit step and the unit impulse
function
in discrete-time we saw
dead the unit impulse function
is the first difference all
the unit step function
well similarly in continuous-time
we can talk about and impulse function
which is the first derivative love
a unit step function
so the unit impulse as we wanted to find
it
is the derivative of the units that
course we just finished discussing the
fact that
the unit step function is in fact
discontinuous it equals 0
but we can't think love its derivative
as related
to this approximation to the units there
and specifically we will think love
the continuous-time in polls as
the derivative %uh use a belt 50
as Delta goes to zero so
to define the unit in polls we think
I've the derivative
love this approximation to the unit step
and then observe what happens as Delta
goes to zero
we have then the definition love
the unit impulse function
more or less formally to find as
the first derivative of the units step
or thought I love as the limiting form
love the derivative love
the approximation to the unit step
in the limit as Delta the
the duration love the discontinuity goes
to zero
well let's look at that if we
think about the derivative love
used to build the T the derivative of
course is 0 for T less than zero
its equal to a constant during this
linear slow
and then it 0 pretty greater than Delta
so
the derivative abusive Delta 50 will
then
be as i've indicated here and
is simply a rectangle with a height
which is one over Delta and with which
is equal to Delta and observed that no
matter what the value of Delta is
the area is always equal to 1
now as we let Delta go to zero
what happens is that the width of the
rectangle get smaller
the height of the rectangle gets bigger
the area still remains one
as Delta goes to zero of course the with
goes to zero
and the height goes to infinity
and graphically we choose to depict that
as an arrow where
the arrow indicates the fact dead we
have
and im polls occurring at equal 0 and
and the height of the in polls is used
to represent
what the area above the impulses and in
this case
since we took the derivative of the
units that the
quite is people to want
so the impulse has 0 with
infinite hi area one its
mathematically not terribly comfortable
because
what we've done is taking the derivative
of the unit step which has a
discontinuity at the origin
and there's a mathematical difficulties
with doing that
well in fact return to another
interpretation
%uh the in polls later up
can't emphasize sum up the sir
discomfort with the impulse
I remember something that Sam Mason
used to say that a student said about
the unit impulse which was
his definition was unit impulse is
something that's so small everyplace I
can't see it
except that one point where it's so big
I can see it in other words I can see it
at all
well except some informality
with the unit impulse function in the
continuous-time
K's and generally we'll see
that we won't get into particular
difficulty okay now
the impose is the derivative the step we
saw
in the discrete-time case that step
could be recovered from the in polls
through a running some
in continuous time with the impulse is
the derivative overstep we would
moralist reasonably expect that this
step
would be like an integral the in polls
and indeed that's true
in fact mathematically the relationship
is
that the unit step
function in continuous-time
is the running integral although
the unit impulse function and
so is the integral from minus infinity
up to time TV
weighty is the argument at which
were examining you ft and so
just as with the discrete-time case if
we are looking at T less than zero
is no area accumulated in the integral
if we're looking at T greater than 0
then we accumulate the area
under the impulse
okay now will shortly
be returning to a
further discussion in use love
impulses and step functions
and in particular what we'll see is that
they provide a very convenient and
powerful mechanism
for describing a particular class two
systems referred to
as linear time-invariant systems to lead
up to that discussion which will
be the principal focus of the next
lecture
let's for the remainder this lecture
talk about systems in general
and then some properties have systems
and
as the lecture proceeds the
specific properties that I want to get
to our properties
when the arity and time very so let's
first talk about
systems in general and a system
in general in its most general
definition
it simply a transformation
from an input signal to an output say so
in a continuous-time case
we would have a continuous-time system
the input exit the
and the output why if the and the box
in essence is used to denote a
transformation from
except the to white T and sometimes will
also use a shorthand notation
along the lines of indicating that the
input except the
is transformed to the output y'at
now we have exactly the same
kinda definition in the discrete-time
case in the discrete-time case
of course the inputs are sequences
and the outputs are sequences and our
shorthand notation
is simple often we talk about systems
will want to talk about interconnections
systems
and will see you again in later lectures
that interconnections become very
important and powerful
and in in the way of introducing
terminology let me introduce the
terminology for a few basic important
interconnections systems the first
is what's referred to as a cascade
systems or sometimes as the series
interconnection systems and
putting two systems in cascade as i've
indicated here
means taking the output have one system
let's say system one and using Matt as
the input
to the second system which are denoted
as system to
so in this cascade with
system one first and system to second
we have the output system one going into
the input
system to now
we could've course take those two
systems
and cascade them in the reverse order
namely take the output system to and put
it into
the input of system one and
i've indicated that here and we have
system to first in the Cascade
followed by system one it's important to
keep in mind
dead in general for general systems
in the order in which you can SCADA
systems is very important
and in fact the
overall system transformation will be
different depending on which system came
first and which system came second for
example
its system one was let's say in a system
for which the output doubles the input
is double the input and system to
the output is the square root of the
input clearly
doubling first and then taking the
square root is different
then taking the square root first and
then double
now kinda amazingly
what we'll see again when we get
to this issue linearity and
time-invariant switcher class of systems
that will focus in on
somewhat amazingly it turns out that for
that
specific classes systems the SIS
overall system transformation is
independent of the order in which
the system's are cascade and we'll see
that of course in more detail later on
alright well that's a cascade or series
interconnection
let's look at another interconnection
which is a parallel
interconnection systems and
here what's meant by the interconnection
is that the input
is fitted simultaneously into system one
and into system to
and then the outputs these two systems
are added to give the overall system
output
now in this particular case
in contrast to a cascade no matter
what the systems are it turns out
that a parallel combination the order in
which
their put in parallel
is the out the overall transformation is
independent up the order
and of course that follows from the fact
that we simply adding up outputs
and the outputs can be added in any
order because the fact that addition
doesn't care
in which order you're heading things up
okay so that's the parallel
interconnection and let's look at
one more interconnection which is what's
referred to
as a feedback interconnection and
this again is a interconnection that
will
become a very important topic much later
in the course
but let me just indicate at this point
what I mean by it
but a feedback interconnection means is
that
we have one system
system one
with an input in an output
the output a system one is the output of
the overall system
and that output is fayed
into system to
the output of system to is then handed
to the input to the overall system
so in essence what happens in a feedback
interconnection
we have one system the output in that
system
is fed back through system to
added to the overall input and then that
some
is what forms the input the system one
and will see that there are
lots of uses for feedback and of course
also lots of ways the feedback getting
the gets in the way
in fact probably some love you are
already familiar with all the issues &
feedback
for example in audio systems or whatever
but this will be
a topic that will devote considerable
amount of time to
later in the course and then
of course there are lots of other
interconnections
love systems and as the course
progresses we'll see
lots of ways in which systems get
interconnected both in series and
parallel and feedback interconnections
et cetera
to achieve a wide variety of things
now what I said so far relates to
systems in general and you can't say
much
about systems when you try to treat them
in the most general form
so it's useful and important to focus in
on properties that system may or may not
have
so what I'd like to do now is turn our
attention
to system properties and will define
a number of them some of them will want
to impose on a system
some love the movie we may not want to
impose on a system
but as things progress will
tend to find it useful to an ass
weather is system does or doesn't have a
certain property
well let's begin with the property which
I A
refer to here and
is memoryless and what I mean by
system being memoryless is dead
the output at any
given time t0 depends
only on the input at the same time and
so
know what I'm suggesting is that a
memoryless system
is one for which the output at a
specific time
depends only on the input at that time
and that statement is true or that
definition
applies both for continuous-time
as i've indicated it here and also
for discrete-time as i've indicated here
and so
we have similar definition in
discrete-time
that the system is memoryless
if the output at any given time
depends only on the input at that time
well
in I have a number of examples here
let's look at
the first example which in which the
output is the square if the input
and that is a possible system either in
continuous-time
for discrete-time and that system as
you would expect is commonly referred to
as
square insists the square
up a signal and anytime depends only on
the value the signal at that time
clearly
square is a memoryless system so
in fact weekend indicate here and this
system
is members
another important system is
what is referred to as an integrator its
the the output is equal to
the integral love the input
here as i've indicated it
its a not just integrating except TV but
its integrating the square affect safety
and whether we square
before we had a great or not the
essential point
is there since we're integrating the
input
the value of the output anytime
is an accumulation a past history the
input well
accumulation a past history in essence
implies memory
to get the output at a given time
requires the input
over an interval specifically for longer
than that time so
this system in fact is not memory loss
and now I have a
third system the fine here the third
system
is a system the discrete-time system
in which the output is equal to
the input but not quite the output at
some time let's say for example that an
equal 0
is equal to the input at one
time sample or instant or value with the
index
before that and so this in fact
is a system for which the output is
simply the input the lady or shifted
by one sample so this system is referred
to as
unit delay
and now the question
the question is is that system
memoryless
well the output depends only on the
input the output at any instant depends
only
on the input at one instant but
since it depends on an instant
prior to the time in which were looking
we're different than the time at which
were looking
it violates the definition a memoryless
that we introduce and so in fact the
unit the LEI
is a system that has memory and so
let's indicate that year so this is not
a memoryless
system because of the fact that there is
one unit at the lay
and in essence the lady requires memory
okay so bats the issue memory and
and a memoryless systems let's now turn
to another
property which a system
may or may not have the property
referred to as
invertia billet now
essentially would inverted bility means
is dead
given the output above the system
you can figure out uniquely with the
input was
thats one definition for infertility
said another way convertibility means
that
given the output there's only one input
that could have caused it
that's another common so definition for
portability
another way of looking at it is in fact
to look at it in the context love a
cascade
love systems so
let's consider a system and here
is a system which are referred to as
system a
and this could be continuous-time and
discrete-time
it has an input x1
TV or an depending on whether it's
continuous-time and discrete-time that
we're talking about
and an associated output
and here we had
go system be with
its associated input an output and
now let's put these two systems in
cascade
so will take the output system one and
feed it
into the input love system
to or system be so
the output system a goes into the input
a system be
and if system is invertible
and system be is its in burgers
then the consequence
is that the output subsystem be
is equal to the input of system a
now I know there there a lotta
inputs and outputs and inverse is in the
air
by essentially what we mean by what I
just said
is that if we have system a
and is invertible and if
we cascaded with its infers
system be then
the overall cascade these two systems
is simply what's referred to as
the identity system
and the identity system is simply a
system
which if you put a signal into it you
get the same signal
out a bit in other words the overall
system is
no transformation at all clearly course
for a system to be able to be cascaded
with another system
to generate the identity system requires
that the first system system a be
invertible
so let's a
look at some examples if we had
system a as i've indicated here
where now the output is
the running integral love
the input and remember that we saw the
running into role when we talked about
the relationship between
steps and impulses if this happened to
be in in polls
then the output would be a step this
system
is referred to of course as an
integrator
since the output is
the running integral love the input
and in the
integrator in fact is an invertible
system
and its infers
is system for which the output is the
derivative
%um so the inverse
or system a if system a is an integrator
is system for which the output
is equal to the derivative the input
which not surprisingly
is referred to and
is a differentiator
so an integrator is invertible
its inverse is a differentiator which
you might want to think about
is the question of whether a
differentiator
is invertible now to answer that what
you would ask yourself is
if you always knew with the derivative
with the signal is would you necessarily
know with the signal was in other words
if you have a differentiator
you have the output of the
differentiator
could you always figure out with the
input words if you could
the system would be invertible if you
couldn't the system would not be
invertible
so you might just want to think about
that I guess
I won't tell you right now but I'm sure
that
dead you'll think about that more
particularly with the
guidance that the video manual
okay well let's look at one
last system in i've indicated here
a system for which the output
is related to the input through this
heard and what I mean by this curve
which
wasn't done a quite as well
as I might have is that
the output is equal to the square
the input so this system
is our square as we talked about before
we saw previously
are discussed the fact previously bad
the squarer is a memoryless
system
and now the question is is the square
an invertible system well question then
is if you given the square the signal
can you figure out with the signal is
and
as I'm sure you've already suspected the
answer to that is no
because obviously if the signal was
negative or positive you wouldn't be
able to figure that out
and you square so in fact
the square is not invertible part so
we've introduced several properties and
by the way
as we've gone through it also in
introduce some systems that will turn
out to be
useful important systems and
now it's continue with some other
properties a property
dead will find useful to make reference
to from time to time and will in fact
play fairly important role in a variety
of discussions
during the course is the property
which is referred to as causality now
in essence what causality beans
is the following the system is said to
be causal
if as one way of saying it only responds
when you kick it is another way of
saying it
its response that any time only depends
on values at the input
prior to that time so
a causal system both continuous-time and
discrete-time
is to find sometimes
as a system which has the property that
the output and anytime depends only on
the input prior or equal to that time
essentially what we're saying
is that the system can't anticipate
future imports and so that in fact
is another possible definition for
causality
that the system is causal
if it can't anticipate future inputs
finally at
not an alternative way of saying it
mathematically
is as follows: if I have
to signals X 1ft
nx2 T with their associated outputs why
150 and white 2
T then a system
is said to be causal if it only if it
has the property
that if those two inputs are identical
up until sometime
then the outputs are identical up until
the same time
so if we have two signals that
are exactly the same up until sometime
and perhaps do something different later
on
causality requires that
the outputs not anticipate the fact that
those inputs
are at some future time going to do
something different
and that in fact is the most useful
mathematical
definition of causality and of course
I've
written that here for continuous-time
and a the
same definition of causality also
applies for discrete-time
okay well it's look at an example
let's take an example
which is a system which is
the following discrete-time system the
output at any given time
is some love
exit Van X event the way
and active and anticipated and
this is in fact a system is very useful
and referred to as moving average
and so if we think 0 moving average
if we have here
a sequence X the van annex the van
with other values kinda going off
in both directions and any value
for any value n0 at which were computing
the output
and this is why I have in the output we
take
X 70 X 70 -1
and X 70 plus one and so
to format moving average we would take
these three bad news and combine them
together
and a moment and dividing by 3 to get
back
well is the system causal
one way to answer that is
to determine whether the output at any
given time depends on future values if
the input
and clearly if you look at this what you
see is that the output at time n0
depends both on past values and on
future bad
as opposed to another moving average
which i've indicated here where I'd
simply shifted the values
that I combine together and in this case
because love the way in which I picked
the values
the output depends on
value in n0 value
at and 0 -1 and the bad you
at n0 -2 so why I've n0 would depend
here
on X 70 X 70 -1
and X 70 -2 and
so in this case the system
is not causal and
in this case the system is cause
all right now let's turn to another
system property the property
referred to as stability now there lotsa
definitions of stability a and
there some of them get very mathematical
and formal would we've chosen
and what will use as our definition
stability is what's called
bounded input founded output stability
essentially the definition is
that a system is stable
if in only a for every bounded input
the output is found so the notion is
if you have a system any input never
gets above
some finite value and stability requires
that the output also stay within some
bounded back
and I'm sure the stability and
instability your things that you're
kinda
arm informally familiar with let me
just kinda are emphasize the point with
the something that I borrowed the
actually from my son
with some reluctance on his part a if we
for example take a system like this
which is in essence a pendulum
this system is a holding it here is
stable
because if I put in a bounded input
which is the displacement
the output which is the movement of it
remains found now on the other hand
if I put the system like this which is
in fact what's referred to as an
inverted pendulum although we could
conceivably get this to balance
just a slight displacement because the
fact that the pendulum is inverted
a slight displacement and the output
becomes unbounded now
an interesting thing with the inverted
pendulum by the way which
I'm sure all of you if you're anything
like me
was intrigued with as a kid was the
notion that you could take an inverted
pendulum
and in effect turn it back into a stable
system
by using what I'm doing right now
which is feedback but I've done in that
case
is I stabilize the system by
using feedback visual feedback from my
eye
to my hand and in fact one of the very
important things that we'll see about
feedback when we talk about feedback
systems much later in the course
is that one of their very important
applications is
in stabilizing unstable systems by the
way one of their problems
is dead if not used correctly it can
destabilize
stable system okay well let's
continue on with our a property of
stability
I have here again the example
of an integrator and as
I indicate here if we have an integrator
and we put a step
function into it or step signal into it
the output is what's referred to as a
ramp
signal it linearly increases now
question is
is a ramp on bounded the input is
is bounded step input is bounded the
ramp is unbounded
because if you try to establish
any bound on it you can always go out
far enough in time
so that the output will exceed that ban
so
in fact the integrator is
not stable
okay now finally I'd like to turn
to two properties that will make
considerable
you so there's the course goes on the
properties
love time invariance and when the arid
time invariance
in essence says
bat the system doesn't really care
what you call the origin in other words
it says if you take the input and your
shift in time
all that you've done is taken the output
and shifted in time by the same amount
someone more formally as i've indicated
here
if in continuous time we have an input X
which generates an output y'at then
time invariance requires that
if the input is shifted by any amount of
time the output is shifted by the same
amount of time and exactly
the same applies in discrete-time for
example
if we have a system which is the system
I've shown here
which by the way is the system that we
talked about previously to go
from step sequence upstart from an
imposed sequence to step sequence
we call that a running some and actually
white it's also often called is an
accumulator
what it does is accumulate past values
the input well is the
accumulator time-invariant the best way
to establish that
is to work through the equations and
verified that it either
does or doesn't satisfy the formal
definition
time invariance informally if you think
about it
it makes intuitive sense that the
accumulator
is time-invariant because if you're
accumulating values
and a few the LEI the values that you're
putting into the accumulator
then the associated values that come out
will be delayed by the same amount
the accumulated it doesn't care really
where if you shift the input is just
simply shift the Associated output but
more generally with your trying to test
time-invariant it's important to return
to the definition
and that's what you're required to do in
the samples
in the videomail okay well
I indicate another example
we had the example become an accumulator
here's another example which
in fact as we'll see later is
a system which is a modulator
the output is the input modulated and
although you might think it first that
this system
is time-invariant in fact
it is not because the input shifted
generates an output which is
the input shifted times
the same modulation function whereas
if we were to take the output above the
system
we're X 50 is the input than
what that would correspond to
is sign T-minus t0
times X love t-minus 20
and since these two are not equal
this system is not time and very
and this is an example that often
causes a slight amount of difficulty
because
it seems like when you look at it it
ought to be
and so I strongly encourage you in the
context that using
working problems in the manual
that you think very carefully about this
and on
and at least believe that when I told
you was the right answer
okay now the final
property that I want introduced today is
the property
love linearity and
linearity is defined in manner
similar for continuous-time in
discrete-time
and what it says is that
if we have some inputs with associated
outputs
let's say X 150 X 2ft
then a system is linear
if it has the proper the that the output
to a linear combination of those inputs
is the same
linear combination love The Associated
outputs
and so that's what I've indicated here
dead
if we now put into the system a linear
combination of those inputs
then for linearity we require that the
output
is the same linear combination and
exactly the same
apply is in discrete-time
and you can show from this definition
dead if a system is linear
with two inputs and its linear in terms
of an arbitrary number
imports I have
a number of examples and
these are examples there'd again I ask
you
to think about as you look at the video
manual
just to suggest the answer as well at
the suggest but to tell you the answer
the integrator as we have here is linear
this system in which the output is
double the input plus a constant
you would kinda think is linear because
it's a straight line
but one has to be careful and in fact as
it turns out
this is not linear are there is a
qualifier attached to it
because it has a property referred to is
incrementally linear
which is discussed somewhat more in
attacks
and finally we have a system which is
the square
that I've indicated again here
and squaring is definitely not
a linear operation
okay so what we've done then is to
introduce a number properties systems
a and we've also by the way is a stress
previously
as we've gone along introduced also a
number of important and useful systems
like the accumulator the integrator the
differentiator
et cetera well we'll see
is that the properties of when you're
ready in time invariance
in particular become central
important properties and in the next
lecture
what will show is there with
systems that are linear and
time-invariant
the use love the impulse function
both in continuous-time and
discrete-time provides an
extraordinarily
important and useful mechanism
for characterizing systems thank you