the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU ha for the
the
the in
the new the we concluded the last
lecture
with the statement above the sampling
theorem and just as a quick reminder
the sampling theorem said that
if we have a continuous-time signal
and we have equally spaced samples
all that signal sampled at a sampling
period which a indicators capital T
and if except he is banned limited
in other words the forty a transformer 0
outside some band where Omega Sapan
is the highest frequency then
under the condition that the sampling
frequency which is two-part divided by
the period
is greater than twice the highest
frequency
the original signal is uniquely
recoverable from the set of samples and
the sampling theorem essentially was
derived by
observing or using the notion that
sampling could be done by multiplication
or modulation with an impulse train and
the sampling theorem develop
by examining the consequence
love the modulation property in the
context of the Fourier transform
in particular if we have our signal
accept T
and it's multiplied by an impulse train
to give us a sampled signal
another impose train whose values or
areas are samples of the original time
function
as i indicate here then
in fact if we examine this equation or
equivalently
bringing accept T inside this some
if we examine either if these equations
in the frequency domain
the four EA transform love
exe PFT is the convolution
above the 40 a transformer the original
signal and the Fourier transform
up the impulse train now
be imposed strain is a periodic signal
its Fourier transform
therefore as we talked about with
Fourier transforms itself an impulse
train
and when we do this convolution n
using the fact that the 48 race for the
imposed strain
is an impulse train the result
or this convolution then tells us
that the 48 transform love
the sampled signal or the impulse train
which represents the samples is a some
love frequency shifted replications
up the 48 transform of the original
signal
so mathematically
that's the relationship it essentially
says that after sampling or modulation
with an impulse train
the resulting spectrum is the original
spectrum
added to itself shifted by multiples
integer multiples of the sampling
frequency well
let's see that as we did last time in
terms of pictures
and again to remind you of the basic
picture involved if we have an original
signal
with the spectrum is a indicated here
where
its ban limited with the highest
frequency Omega Savannah M
and if the time function is sample
so that in the frequency domain week
involved this spectrum
with the spectrum shown below which is
the
spectrum love the impulse train
the convolution if these true up these
two
is then the Fourier transform or
spectrum
love the sampled time function
and so thats what we end up with here
and then as you recall to recover the
original time function
from this as long as these individual
triangles don't overlap
to recover it just simply involves
passing the impulse train through a
low-pass filter in effect
extracting just one of these
replications
love the original spectrum
so the overall system
then for for doing the sampling and then
the reconstruction of the original
signal from the samples
consists of multiplying the original
time function
by an impulse train and that gives us
then the sampled signal
the Fourier transform I show here love
the
original signal and after modulation
with the impulse train
the resulting spectrum that we have is
that replicated around integer multiples
of the sampling frequency
and then finally to recover
the original signal or to generate a
reconstructed signal
we then multiply this in the frequency
domain
by the frequency response of an idea
low-pass filter
and what that accomplishes forest and
is recovering the original signal
now in this picture an important point
that I raise last time
relates to the fact dead in doing the
reconstruction
well we've assumed is dead in
replicating
these individual versions
0 the original signal
those replications don't overlap and
sold by passing this through a low-pass
filter in fact
we can recover the original signal well
what that requires is that
this frequency Omega Savannah M be less
than
this frequency and this frequency
is Omega so fast minus Omega serve them
and so what we require is dead the
frequency Omega Sapan
be less than Omega cyb s minus Omega sed
am
or equivalent Lee what we require is
that the sampling frequency
be greater and twice the highest
frequency
in the original signal now
if in fact that condition is violated
then we end up with a very important
effect
and that effect is referred to as a
leasing
in particular if we look back at are
original example we're here
we were able to recover our original
spectrum by
low-pass filtering if in fact
the sampling frequency is
not high enough to avoid aliasing
then what happens in that case is that
the individual replications
love the Fourier transform above the
stove the original signal
overlap and what we end up with
is some distortion as you can see if we
tried to pass this through a low-pass
filter
to recover the original signal in fact
we won't recover the original signal
since these individual replications have
overlapped
and this is the case where Omega service
minus Omega Savannah is less than
Omega so vast in other words the
sampling frequency is not greater
in this case than twice the highest
frequency
so what happens here then is that in
effect
higher frequencies get folded down into
lower frequencies what would come out of
the low-pass filter
is the reflection of some higher
frequencies into lower frequencies
as I suggested a minute ago that affect
is referred to as alias saying and in
order to
both understand that term better and two
understand in fact the effect better
it's useful to examine this a little
more closely
for the specific example a sinusoidal
signal
so let's concentrate on that and what we
want to look at
is the effect or alias saying
when our input signal is a sinusoidal
signal
now to do that what I wanna show shortly
is a computer-generated movie
that we've made and let's first
walk-through
a few frames a bit to give you our first
of all
to to set up our notation and to suggest
what it is that we're trying to
demonstrate
well what we have is an input signal
is a sinusoidal signal and
the spectrum or for a transformer that
is an impulse in the frequency domain at
the frequency the sinusoid we then
have samples love that and when we
sample that in for this particular
example its sample the 10 killer hurts
this spectrum is then replicated
at multiples all the sampling frequency
and I haven't shown negative frequencies
here but the contribution do
to the negative frequency
is at 10 killer hurts minus the input
sinusoid
we then carry out a reconstruction
with an idea low-pass filter and the
ideal ok pass filter is set at
half the sampling frequency or five
kelleher its
so what we have then is
the input signal accept T
and the impulse train exe PFT
and then the reconstructed signal is
the output from the low-pass filter
which I denote as X a party
now as the input frequency X 50
increases this impulse moves up in
frequency
but this impulse moves down in frequency
and so let's just look at a few frames
as the input frequency increases
so we have here a case
where the input frequency has move up
close to five killer hurts
as we continue further these two
impossible's
will cross and what we'll end up with as
i indicated
is aliasing so here now is a case
where we have alias saying the
replication of the negative frequency
has crossed into the passband if the
filter
and the reconstructed sinusoid will now
be the frequency associated with this
impulse
rather than the frequency Associated
with the original sinusoid and to
dramatize that
even further here is
the example where now the input
frequency
has moved up close to 10 killer hurts
but what comes out of the low-pass
filter
is a much lower frequency and in fact
you can see that here is the
reconstructed sinusoid
whereas here we have the input size
okay well now what I'm gonna wanna do is
demonstrate this as i indicated with a
computer-generated movie
and well we'll see is the effect
on the effect of reconstructing
from the samples using a low-pass filter
for an input which changes in frequency
and with the sampling rate of 10 killer
hurts
and what we'll see in the first part of
this movie is
the input except the and the
reconstructed signal
X a party without explicitly showing the
samples
and then at a later point will also show
this and indicate
that in fact the samples are those two
are equal even though
they themselves are not
so at the top will have the input
sinusoid without
showing the samples and its
for EA transform is an impulse in the
frequency domain as we've indicated
and if we sample it that imposed and
gets replicated
and so samples in particular
will have a Fourier transform not only
with an impulse
at the input sinusoid sinusoidal
frequency but also attend killer hurts
minus that frequency
now for the reconstruction we pass the
samples through an idea low-pass filter
I picked
the cutoff frequency of the low-pass
filter at half the sampling frequency
namely 5 killer hurts
and here we see is that the output
reconstructed signal in fact matches in
frequency the input signal
now as we change the input frequency
the reconstructed sinus so it is
identical
until we get to an input frequency
which exceeds half the sampling
frequency
at that point we have aliasing and while
the input frequency is increasing
the output frequency in fact is
decreasing
because that's what's inside the
passband the filter
now let's sweep it back and as the input
frequency decreases the output frequency
increases
till there's no aliasing and now the
output reconstructed
signal is equal to the input
so we sample the signal and then
reconstructed
the signal from the samples and keep in
mind
that given a set of samples there are
lots of continuous curves that we can
thread through the set of samples
the one that we picked up cores is the
one consistent
with the assumption about the signal
band with
in particular we've reconstructed the
signal
that who spectrum falls within the pass
band at the filter
now what I'd like to show is the same
reconstruction and input as I showed
before
but now let's look at the samples and
what we'll see is that
when there's alias saying even though
the output the reconstructed signal
is not identical to the input in fact
it's consistent with the input samples
that is sampling the reconstructed
signal
gives a set of samples identical to the
samples at the input
and it's just that the interpolation in
between those samples
is an interpolation consistent with you
soon
fan with love the input based on the
sampling there
so let's now look at that with
the samples also shown along with the
sinusoid
so at the top we have the input sinusoid
together with its samples
the bottom traces the Fourier transform
of the sampled waveform
the middle trace is the reconstructed
sinusoid together with its samples and
notice of course that the samples are
the input a reconstructed signal
are identical and also
the input sinusoidal frequency
and the output sinus or frequency are
identical
we now increase the frequency at the
input
the reconstructed sinusoid tracks the
input frequency
and of course the samples are the two
are identical
the interpolation in between the samples
is identical
because the fact dead the input
frequency is still
less than half the sampling frequency
and so as long as the input is frequency
is less than half the sampling frequency
not only will the samples be identical
but also
the reconstructed continuous waveform
will match
the input way for
now when we get to hear the sampling
frequency were just
on the verge Bailey is saying this isn't
alias saying
quite yet but any increase in the input
frequency
will now generate aliasing we now have a
leasing
the output frequency is lower than the
input frequency but notice
that the samples are identical now
the low-pass filter is interpolating in
between those samples
with a sinusoid that falls within the
past Pandev the low-pass filter
which no longer matches the frequency of
the input sinusoid but
the important point is that even when we
have alias saying
the samples are the reconstructed
waveform
are identical to the samples
of the original way for and notice that
as the input frequency increases
in fact the interpolated output the
reconstructed output
has decreased in frequency now as the
input frequency begins to get closer to
10 killer hurts in fact you're all I
tends to also interpolate between the
samples
with a frequency that is lower
day and the input frequency NS
particularly evident
here notice that the input samples in
fact
look like they would be associated
with a much lower frequency sinusoid
then in fact
was the sinusoid the generated a lower
frequency sinusoid
in fact corresponds to the reconstructed
one now as we sit back down
the aliasing eventually disappears and
the output sinus or tracks the input
sinusoid in frequency
so we've seen the
effective aliasing for sinusoidal
signals and turns away forms
now let's hear how it sounds now
what we have for this demonstration is
an oscillator and
a sampler and the output of the sampler
goes into a low-pass filter so the
input for from the oscillator goes into
the sampler
and the output the sampler
goes into the low-pass filter the
sampler frequency is 10 killer hurts
and so the low-pass filter
has a cutoff frequency as i indicate
here
all five killer hurts and
what will listened to is the
reconstructed output as the
oscillator input frequency berries
and recall there what should happen is
that
when the oscillator input frequency gets
past half the sampling frequency
we should hear aliasing so we'll start
the oscillator it to kill her ex
and keep in mind that what you see on
the dial
is the input frequency which you here is
the output frequency
as long as the input frequency is less
than half the sampling frequency in
other words 5 killer hurts
the reconstructed signal sounds
identical to the input
now at five still hurts were right
on the verge of aliasing and when we
increase the input frequency past five
killer hurts
the reconstructed frequency in fact will
decrease
so as we move for example from 5 killer
hurts
up to let's say 6 killer hurts
sick still hurts in fact yes alias
down to what gets alias down to
4 killer us so
6 go over to the input is for killer
hurts
at the output now if we move up even
further
7 kilohertz at the end pushed its alias
down
to three killer hurts at the outpost
so bad dan is a audio demonstration and
aliasing
so to summarize
if we sample signal and then reconstruct
from the samples using a low-pass filter
as long as the sampling frequency is
greater than twice the highest frequency
in the signal
we reconstruct exactly if on the other
hand
the sampling frequency is too low less
than twice the highest frequency
then we get alias saying in other words
higher frequencies get folded or
reflected
down into lower frequencies as they come
through the low-pass filter
now wanted the
common applications love the whole
concept of sampling
is the use sampling to convert a
continuous-time signal into a
discrete-time signal to carry out
what's often referred to as discreet I
processing
of continuous-time signals and this in
fact is something that will be talking
about
in a fair amount of detail beginning
with the next lecture
but and let me indicate that for
that kinda processing essentially what
happens
is dead we begin with a continuous-time
signal
and convert it to a discrete-time signal
carry out the discrete-time processing
and then
convert back to continuous-time and
the conversion from a continuous-time
signal to a discrete-time
signal in fact is done
by exploiting sampling specifically
by sampling the continuous-time signal
with an impulse train and then
converting the impulse train into
a sequence in a manner that all talk
about in more detail
next time now in doing that
of course as you can imagine it's
important since we want
an accurate representation of the
original continuous-time signal
to choose the sampling frequency to very
carefully avoid aliasing
and so in fact in that context
and in many other contexts alias saying
is something
that we're very eager to avoid however
it's also important to understand that
alias saying
isn't all bad and there are some very
specific contexts in which
alias saying is very useful and very
heavily exploited
one example love
a very useful context valia saying is
when
you want to look at things that happen
at frequencies
that you can't look at for one reason or
another and sampling in a leasing is
used to map those into lower frequencies
one very common example of that is the
use of the stroboscopic
which was invented by doctor how their
chechen
at MIT and sometime earlier in fact we
had
the opportunity to visit doctor Richard
ins laboratory at MIT
and see some examples of this so I'd
like to
at as a conclusion to this lecture take
you
on visit to the stroke where and MIT
in the lecture in discussing aliasing
we've stressed
the fact that in most situations it's
something that would like to avoid
however right now we're at MIT and
stroll Valley
as it's called on the way to visit the
laboratory
Mike MIT colleague Professor are alleged
where in fact a leasing is an everyday
occurrence
basically the idea is to follow dead
it in fact you wanna make measurements
at frequencies that for one reason or
another
you can't measure their sampling and
consequently aliasing
can be used to bring those frequencies
down into a frequency range that you can
measure
well professor edgerton alias
da kitchen invented the strokes call
for exactly that reason and kinda the
idea is the fall
the I essentially is a low pass filter
and so there are things that happen
at frequencies boat which
your I contract and by
sampling with light poles sampling in
time
what in effect you're able to do is
sample in such a way
that higher frequencies get alias
down to lower frequencies then factor I
contract
so let's take the look inside the where
and in fact see no aspiration or
the scroll and some its effects
will be here introduce you to my mighty
colleague I kitchen
in also by the way he this is a great
place for kids of all ages
and so my daughter just insisted on
coming along to
also helped out stock need you we could
begin with you
just saying a little bit about what the
strobe is in with some history is
steroids ring resemble an increase in a
min ly
misses them losing on Lampson
prices litter control rate planning on
school is not a good strategy is going
to turn and we're going to look at.
motor striving on balance weight
to set up some rhinos lesions in the
spring
want to know more bring on the throne
by
you writer and
throbs but just in the frequency the way
but corresponds to North influencer
little more elusive
for the facts thought maybe we could the
turn the stroller
for a minute noon the but let me
point out the by the way there the fact
that
when looking at this without the strong
mind always say essentially
our frequencies that are I can attract
so you can see the motor
turning and
we can really see other than then with
the were we can see the movie the spring
and so I get your point is that when we
put the strobe on
who were essentially sampling this and
no
you brought this stand with a frequency
that there the
Riza with the track in fact
the I guess if we turn the
incandescent light of loon
the able to really bring out
are the alias frequency so now we're
what we're looking at in fact are the
the earliest frequencies the street
courses moving a lot faster than we see
it in their ranks
you know that's going on arena
30 times second Bruins are
thirties and second occurs through the
survivors include
next move Rohingya figure 8a. saying you
don't see that
yeah friend
well we'll be seeing now is essentially
second harmonic that
someone okay
and just do you think you can make this
spring dance around a little bit
find taking this slow frequency soon as
all around
okay it's really neat let's turn the
lights back on
weekend this is Charles president with
anything 3 I'm
yeah has the third what's interesting
now if we look at this and
seeking a fifth just rolled off again
earth okay noticed just think we look at
the spring man although we can see is a
blur
and really can't see because you're
right here tracking
can see things happening station but he
said
by the way this was written demonstrated
at the World's Fair
the thickness
world because glasses
for their Wow a loses all dressed up
element using
break bring bruises
fine but failed I stick with the miners
stresses
runners or have break
bum they work on automobiles
their own thoughts on the vibrate but
let's
earth buy levitra run this for a lot
more than half an hour or a liberal
name is continues
terms
thing me maybe we can look at the
a couple other things have a about the
fam
brand the classic buzzed
that's a good idea makes too much noise
ok is to remove that over here that's
just an ordinary like the fam
has a mark on one plate surgeon
identify you can get up to speed
know that this looks like a phantom was
also demonstrated in the
world's fair few years ago yeah kinda
been
been does a movie
quicken awake practicing in to and it
was very fan
well one like it happened if the reform
do
MGM and the Peters B Smith
wanted he said he won miss royale up
custard pie into it not don't know I'm a
serious scientists for
sizes compromise on a I
so we dropped an egg into it in the news
UCI's B-movie
dropping 0 not known struggle there
there was with the
high-speed great remove yeah it's okay
so
so again I guess without this true when
we look at its
what we're looking at our frequencies it
are
much higher than the I think following
now with the stroke blindness
you can see both the alias frequency and
you can also see the original frequency
because we have the
investment line sweats I'm let's
turned down the the background lighting
and
stand then really all that were able to
see or the aliasing
frequencies stand I guess
I guess when we see more than one market
means that the
stay were actually running its and
or guns is more and more things the the
using
lower radiation steroids because the
plans aren't exactly the same
actually this gives me a chance
illustrating other important correlated
to the lecture
I'll that they could bring them to
frequency
so that re only get one more scorched
missus begins to move this is just one
way there now
okay so so the way we have now we've
essentially alias the fan speed and so
the
is just a little higher than the seeds
and now
on right at the sea and now if I could
and just a little further in fact that
looks like the fans turning back hurts
and if you think that this into context
the leasing
its it's like this to impulses in the
frequency domain
crossover in with you get an effective
you and was mathematically
you get a phase reversed in
no wasn't so I E I first understood have
a leasing
with Doc understood why stand with the
western movies
a everyone's Ryan see the wagon wheels
through November go backwards train and
there's there the
wagon wheels in western movie going
backwards yes stressed
and just see what you see is %um too
much weaker on straight up so you get to
just see greater frequency of so that's
you get to marched
u-turn and Justin's governor and you
think tourist
you impressed
schoolroom its regular spirits
all rights pictures in your honor older
adults
and I rising price revolution I guess
another thing is that this demonstrates
something that is
and I heard a long time ago which is its
should never use a power so with the
fluorescent lights the is arrest like is
a little bit of a stroke affecting
you could actually can misuse of that
standing still make mistakes a
strength that you think everything we
are doing is a good friend of
no I don't think I want to try it out
how are you this do you think that's
any sores and wounds she knows it's
going
sproule undergoing closest friends okay
let's
I'm actually we turn the lights back on
again what's
their latest see once again is that we
can see both the alias frequencies going
to you that's
and we we can also see the higher
frequencies because the
incandescent lighting its okay maybe we
can be no
is parents take a look at some other
on things and when I guess I'm curious
about is the distance you have over
their kids
doc maybe you can tell us what we have
here
churros the this to show
how you can get motion pictures on a
Susan still pictures
the circle is repeated 12 times
why does outer part over mmm on this
site
in part on the other quiet place one
time for a revolution on this
you see the exactly as it is if I skip
one picture each time
when you get there relative motions
mall the object is to show the ball
rotating
is this where that one depending on mood
straw was going faster or slower
and the other Uzan this way motion
pictures went well
100 years school long for photography
drew pictures of people
different animated features like the run
yes great
is actually the title kinda busy
aliasing can be fun conservatism
sterling if the speeds
or away if you get a lot of different
things sorted veterans
go through ruin currently reaches speeds
reserve a room in the rules it sounds
ok and the background blur basically the
high frequencies the I can't follow
and and then we're going to propose and
then again we can see
frequencies it really is down the nets
rookie I ends right now I am one place
for revolution sleep
see the corner the move is consuming
records
exactly the reasons there are an
increasing frequency
of risk if 100 one server or early get
the illusion that diamonds
room in fact let's a let's really
enhanced solution
Western the incandescent lights off
and now now are we seeing really you're
the alias frequencies
or or do you think this just adds
looks like reading recognized through
was doing rejoining licensing
of is the same rules now lower watching
is something also
might point out of a for the
I'm the lecture for the course is that
actually there
there really are two sampling
frequencies receiving one is this road
and
which is the stroke that you're running
the other is the inherent
Creamery for the TV that's running at 30
frames a second
and that's won the reasons by the way in
dead people watching this
on the video worst are in fact seeing
Flickr or a feeding or modulation
between
the two on synchronize frame rates
runner grievances
grow up so we get to of to a room
credits
of to
roaming two runs on each other of
of
you know it senator Reid's learning this
soon living room when all your friends
I think would be a good terrific homered
problem getting video Kors
they have them all sit down and analyze
all the frequencies that they're seeing
and what they're being alias through the
evening event
it's a good view run the teacher I love
you
who is great yeah remember these dudes
list
I think that a chase a few people away
from the courses good
cracks and you get you get involved in
these offerings
rule ruler and what you can do for a KMS
roots
let's bring you the incandescent lights
back again
just to remind everybody that in back
row this or
some some frequencies that are a lot
higher than the ones that
we begin to get the impression that
we're watching just the
motor running Frances Bean pattern on
long Dhaka have to
I have to say that there are many people
I know they have as much fun in the work
as you do
home like a man arm quote would but I'd
like to
do now baby is take a look at one last
experiment sure did
and what I'd like to do is a.m. is go
take a look at the
I guess what sometimes is called the
home
well not the water graphics for men with
thin air the minute dole pillar
hydraulic everything that's the 1i was
thinking and let's take a look over
there
okay one just in this Go internal war so
your doc this is the what did you got DP
HHM bird double peddler hydraulic
happening machine Gary okay then it's
a.m. so please
it looks like continues dream up it is
not its
pump over there something sixty post
second so those owners
coming out in spurts %uh so actually
again it's
it's the the sixty boss is the second
year I can follow
your eyes so is exactly basically looks
like a blur
ruseler it is a blur writers you learn
output stroll on
okay grace start so again
I guess we have this a essentially alias
then in
and again with the incandescent light
you can see both sky high frequency
and the alias frequency its and
but see I guess that's with the
frequency close to the sea and we can
adjusted so that is stop stop bothering
me going to go out and then we can
actually make it go up
scored anybody who is this South
yeah effect movie have just just again
due to stress this point to the
class the the kind of the idea here the
face reversal of course
you can see it in the time domain
Chynoweth you just think about when the
flashes of light
come but if you think I love kind of
these
impulses that we have in the frequency
domain
and we're aliasing as we change the
sampling frequency what happens is that
these impulses crossover
and what that means is that we get a
phase reversal the pending
on which faces are associated with
which side up the sea so that's kind of
the idea the phase reversal
okay let's the let's turn the
against because it is important thing in
between those who got
yeah let's let's turn the incandescent
light of first and
think one thing your so 103 know through
this thing you think you can do to get
on the other side you're on hand so we
can see with
when for the UN intervening sleuths
water there all the time well on a
nosedive it seems to me if we can't we
just the justices
the that's just go through to next year
staff the dots can do it just seeing how
come you think your finger in the air
fun to try once more its
I get snyder et that's one thing we can
do this
well as bring the lights back up and its
again just to go stress the point scary
RTC
there we are at a frequency that it's
just a little above the sea
and we can go back there and in the sea
and we can actually get a phase reversal
and I guess if we do this long enough we
get at the at the whole ocean and put it
back in
we're ever comes from is there in cars
in newsrooms gonna run is not running
too long by the Rev trailer get here yet
to be careful as well as the Moody Blues
V
surface well I don't know about them but
I guess I believe you back its
up a little more pressure on three gods
monarchy
Adams girlfriends or service teams
going things together Ste
we have these machines are all over the
place lot of fun
but that this this is really terrific I
i think that
the this whole idea of the
and abusing aliens saying in stroz and
the kinds of things that did you do with
the murder just fantastic in that we
really appreciate the chance to
come in here and see the demonstration
Rose Bowl game ruth's
hope you will use it for years the bar
over many years to come
so is I emphasized that the beginning
in what situations aliasing can in fact
be very useful
also with this demonstrates is that
particularly when you have a colleague
like da kitchen
a leasing and for that matter science in
general can be an awful lot of fun
by gonna thanks a lot that again and
thank you just the name
well I have to say that that visit was
an awful lot of fun for me and
for Justin in fact to for the whole
camera crew that was
there and hopefully you all have used at
some point will also have a chance to
visited stroll Valley well
hopefully what we've gone through today
gives you
a good feeling for the concepts love
sampling an alias saying
and both why it might be useful and why
we might want to avoid
in the next lecture will continue on
the discussion of sampling any
particular
what all be talking about is the
interpretation
love the reconstruction process not in
the frequency domain
but in a time-domain interpretation
specifically associated
with the concept %uh interpolating
between the samples
well then proceed from there too a
discussion as i've alluded to
in several lectures love what i've
referred to as
discrete-time processing of
continuous-time signals
very heavily exploiting the concept and
issues associated with sample
thank you