ha the
the norm
are
last time
we began the discussion I'll
discrete-time processing
love continuous-time signals and
as a reminder let me review
the basic notion the idea was
dead we convert
from a continuous-time signal to a
sequence
through an operation which I
represent as a continuous to
discrete-time converter
and then that sequence
is used as the input to
inappropriate discrete-time system
and after appropriate discrete-time
processing
that sequence is converted
back to a continuous-time signal
through an operation which i-label as
a discrete to continuous-time converter
now in the lecture
last time we carried out some analysis
which related 4s the spectra
in the first step this operation namely
in the transformation from a
continuous-time
signal to sequence and
let me by the way draw your attention to
the fact
that in the real world this operation
is essentially implemented
by what you would typically label as an
analog to digital converter
if in fact the discrete-time processing
is being done digitally now it's
important to emphasize that it's not
exactly what an analog to digital
converter
does but in some sense at least you
should think
love this mapping from continuous time
to discrete-time
in very much the same way there one
would think an analog to digital
converter
and the mapping back and is corresponds
in some sense to a what would happen
with a digital to analog converter well
let me review what is involved in the
mapping from
the continuous-time signal to the
sequence and
let me stress again that this operation
is basically in the continues to
discrete-time conversion
a two-step process in
the first part of the process the
continuous-time signal
is modulated with an impulse train
where the period of the imposed strain
is capital T
and so we have a continuous-time
impose Train Signal which captures
the samples love the original
continuous-time signals
that in Paul strain
is then put through an operation
which essentially re labels
the samples so that the
sample values the impulse areas
are relabeled as sequence values
and the result of that conversion is
then
the sequence X event so the overall
process then
is a sampling process followed by
what is simply in this box relabeling
process and although as I
indicated just a minute ago that is
essentially what an analog to digital
converter does
now like to digital converter doesn't
necessarily carry it out
in those two steps but particularly
in terms love carrying through an
analysis
thinking of it as a two-step process is
particularly convenient
now we talked last time
about what this mapping from continuous
time to discrete-time
means both in the time domain in terms
of the spectra
and in particular in the time domain we
begin with the continuous-time signal
which is then samples with an impulse
train
and converted to a sequence by
simply generating a sequence whose
values
are the area is love the impulses
and I stress the fact that what this
corresponds to
essentially is and normalization of the
time axis
essentially by dividing the time axis by
capital T
in the frequency-domain then
we had the spectrum of the original
signal
which because that the sampling process
is
replicated at multiples integer
multiples
all the sampling frequency Omega so
badass
or to pile over capital T
and then in converting the impulses
to a sequence we are essentially
normalizing the frequency axis so that
the frequency to pile over capital T
gets relabeled is to pie
and the resulting discrete-time spectrum
looks like
I indicate here which really is
nothing more and a frequency scaling
corresponding to the Associated time
scaling so the mapping
from the imposed strain spectrum to the
discrete-time spectrum
corresponds to mapping specified
by capital Omega equal to small make a
times capital T
an equivalent Lee it's the frequency
to pile over capital T which is
of course the sampling frequency which
gets normalized
to the frequency to pie
and so in the frequency domain
their is a frequency normalization
Associated
with the fact dead corresponding to this
spectrum
is a time sequence or discrete time
sequence
as I show previously and a discrete-time
is related to the
original continuous-time signal
through a time normalization in other
words
these sequence values are simply samples
at the continuous-time signal
with the time axis we normalized
now what we want to consider this is the
conversion from continuous time to
discrete-time
what we want to consider now is the
overall system
which implements not just the conversion
but filtering
and then coming back onto the conversion
back to continuous-time
so let's look at the overall system
and the overall system courses I've
stressed several times in the past
consists
love first the sampling process
conversion to an impulse train
and the imposed strain converted to a
sequence
that sequence is then processed
through are discrete-time filter
and after the discrete-time processing
the result of that is converted back
to an impulse train so this resulting
process sequence
is then converted back to an impulse
train
and then finally we carry out the the
sampling
process by simply using a low-pass
filter
Associated with the with the cutoff
associated with the sampling frequency
that we use
now typically in a system like that
which implements
discrete-time processing continuous-time
signals
we either we need to ensure in one way
or another
that the band with love the input is
sufficiently limited so that we avoid
aliasing
one way to do that is to force it in one
way or another or
simply know that our signal satisfies
the band with constrain
although a fairly typical thing to do in
addition
to this sampling process is
to include what is referred to as
and anti aliasing filter in other words
this is a filter
that would ban limit the input
and at least half the sampling frequency
so that we r guaranteed and
that their is no aliasing it's carried
out
in this process and it's important
to stress dead in this kinda processing
discrete-time processing
continuous-time signals except in
certain
special situations its very important
to avoid aliasing because we're going to
want
to do a reconstruction after we do the
sampling and processing
okay now this is the sequence of steps
in the time domain
let's examine what happens as a
consequence is this
in the frequency domain well
let's choose some typeof simple
representative spectrum
and of course what's important about it
is that
the specter that we choose is banned
limited or that there's an anti-aliasing
filter
and it's not the shape of course that is
critical
and as we work our way through the
system
this is the continuous-time spectrum
after sampling that spectrum is
replicated at
multiples of the sampling frequency
integer multiples the sampling frequency
and so
there would be another one over here and
another one over here at cetera
and then in converting to a
discrete-time sequence
their is The Associated
frequency normalization so that the
sampling frequency
yes normalized to a frequency
to pie okay now at that point
where we are in the system
is at this point
so that we've converted to a sequence we
now
want to carry out some filtering and
then after that filtering
convert back to a continuous-time
signals
alright so here we are at the
spectrum Associated with the
sequence and now
the processing they were carrying out is
linear time-invariant filtering in the
discrete time domain
and what that corresponds to then is
multiplying
this spectrum by the filter frequency
response and I've chosen
a particular shape and again it's not
the shape that's important to the
discussion
but the fact for example that it has a
particular cutoff frequency which will
kinda track
as we work through this and so now
the spectrum of why I have an the output
the digital filter is the product this
spectrum
and the 4e a transformer frequency
response
I'll the digital filter
now in working our way through we're
going to take the output at the filter
and undo the two-step process so we now
want to take that sequence
converted to an impulse train and then
take then imposed strain
Andy sample through a low-pass filter
so here we are now at the output to the
digital filter
we then convert that to an impulse train
well that's really on doing the original
time normalization
and so what that means is that we
are on doing the frequency normalization
in particular
we're dividing the frequency axis by
capital T whereas this point
in y Omega was to pie
now it's to pile over capital T
what that means is that acquittal and
Lee were multiplying this spectrum
by the frequency response the digital
filter
but now linearly scaled in frequency
so that will what was a cutoff frequency
Omega subsea
is now a cutoff frequency up Omega
subsea
divided by capital T so
now the next step in the process is the
reconstructing
low-pass filter and what that extracts
is simply the portion
I'll this periodic spectrum around the
origin
and so finally and spectrum of the
output
up the overall system will be the
spectrum
of the input multiplied
by a frequency response
which is the digital filter frequency
response
frequency scaled by dividing
that digital filter frequency axis by
capital T
okay now what we can ask is
we've got this processing we've
converted to discrete-time we've gone
back to continuous-time
and one can ask now what acquittal and
overall continuous-time systems is that
correspond to
in other words if we that of course is a
continuous-time system it's a continuous
time you put a continuous-time output
and the overall system dan
would be one that would give us exactly
the same output spectrum
as we're getting well what is that well
we have
is an output spectrum which is the
product
all the input spectrum and digital
filter frequency characteristic
frequency scale and so in fact
the resulting digital filter I'm sorry
continuous-time
filter is simply the digital filter
with inappropriate frequency scaling
in other words with the frequency axis
divided by capital T
so sent another way if
we show here
the frequency response or the
original digital filter
then the corresponding continuous-time
filter would be this
frequency scaled and then because love
The Associated low-pass filtering in the
reconstruction
we would select out just one of these
periods in particular the portion around
the origin
and the essential consequences that is
that the corresponding
continuous-time filter then is
given by this and these two are related
simply by a linear scaling the frequency
axis
and note dead where the digital filter
has a cutoff frequency
Omega subsea the continuous-time filter
has a cutoff frequency Omega subsea
divided by capital T
so that's the linear frequency scaling
and
by the way plant away for now and will
return to this point later
plant the way for now the the
observation
dad even if the digital filter frequency
response
is fixed which we would assume it is
by changing the sampling frequency in
fact
what we're able to do is a fact a linear
scaling
or the acquittal in continuous-time
okay well this is pretty much the
process in the analysis
but to highlight a number the issues and
emphasize these points
why I like to do is illustrate
somewhat this with a videotape
demonstration
that in fact was made originally as part
of another course a course
devoted entirely to
digital signal processing which
essentially is discrete-time processing
whether or not it's related to
continuous-time signals
and what I'd like to now focus on
are summer the details of that
demonstration
in the demonstration the
specific impulse response there
is used for the digital filter
or discrete-time filter is the one that
I show here
and the Associated
frequency response is the frequency
response
love a discrete-time low-pass filter as
i indicate below
and the cutoff frequency that filter as
i indicate the filter was designed as a
discreet I felt with the cutoff
frequency hi over five
and let me just draw your attention to
the fact that
pie over five is also
10 love to pie
and so in fact the digital
for discrete-time filter cutoff
frequency is a tenth
to pie and as all stress again shortly
remember that in the frequency
normalization
or a normalization to pie represents
in effect the sampling frequency and so
the consequence of that is that cutoff
frequency really is going to be
associated
with the 10th all the sampling frequency
but for now keep in mind that is just
simply attentive to
on now the
equivalent continuous-time
system interns are the impulse response
is of course a ban limited interpolation
love the up the
impose response associated with the
discrete-time
filter and in the frequency domain the
frequency response
is correspondingly a timescale
and a timescale I'm sorry a frequency
scale
version at the frequency response so in
fact
in the frequency domain and in the time
domain
related to the continuous-time signal
the Associated impulse response is
what I indicate here a ban limited
interpolation
or the discrete-time impulse response
and time scale than
and the frequency response following the
discussion that we've previously gone
through
is a frequency scale version all the one
associated with the digital filter
well the first thing that all want to
look at is
the impulse response and when we do
let me just indicate that
in the actual implementation things are
slightly different
then they are associated with the ideal
analysis
in particular in converting
from a discrete-time sequence
to the continuous-time signal whereas
this way of looking at it is convenient
in the context that the analysis in fact
the way it's done
is is using more or less
standard digital to analog converter
one what a digital to analog converter
does as i indicated in the previous
lecture
is to convert the sequence
not to an impulse train but in fact to
go directly through
zero-order hold and so usually what
comes onto
a digital to analog converter is a
staircase
tightness signal associated with the
zero-order hold
and then the result of that is low-pass
filter to do the reconstruction
so what we want to look at and is
that reconstruction first with just an
impulse input
and so what we'll see after the low-pass
filter
for the impulse response is
a smooth curve like this but also as
part of the demonstration
what all do just to show the zero-order
hold
is to take the low-pass filter out
temporarily
and then put it back in so first let's
just look at
the filter impulse response
what we see here is the impost response
all the overall system and
we observe for one thing that it's a
symmetrical impulse response in other
words corresponds to a linear phase
filter
we can also look at the impulse response
before that the same playing
low-pass filter let's take out that the
sampling low-pass filter
slowly and wide
we observe is basically the output I'll
the digital to analog converter which of
course is a staircase a boxcar function
not an impulse train in the real world
the
output over the day converted generally
is a boxcar type function
we can put the the sampling filter back
in now
and notice that the effectivity sampling
filter is basically
to smooth out the rough edges in
the boxcar output from the DA converter
okay so that's the impulse response the
system
now what I like to show is the frequency
response the system and to measure the
frequency response of course what we can
do
is put a sine wave
into the system and looked at
the sinusoidal output so in particular
now what will happen is that
with the system we will put in
a continuous-time sinusoid which is
sampled
converted to a sequence
the sample continues sigh sinus so it is
a discrete-time sinusoid
that goes through the digital filter and
gets attenuated or
amplified appropriately and then
the output if that is converted back and
that's
again a sinusoidal output that gets
converted back
to a continuous-time sinusoid
theoretically as i indicate here but
again as we just saw
really represented by zero-order hold
followed by
a low-pass filter so thats
the overall operation with one
modification from the diagram that we
have here
in this particular diagram I've included
a and anti-aliasing filter
in fact in the demonstration there is no
anti-aliasing filter and so
in fact the input is a sinusoidal input
which is not band limited
by virtue of an anti-aliasing filter
it's only
course been limited appropriately
if we choose the sinusoidal frequency
that way
so there is no anti-aliasing filter and
this is the system
and one consequence if that
is dead in fact if we sweep
the input sinusoid only up to half the
sampling frequency
will see no aliasing but if we let its
we passed that we're going to get
aliasing
now in the demonstration the sampling
rate
its picked for this party the
demonstration is a 20 kilohertz sampling
rate
that means based on the sampling theorem
that as long as the input frequency
is below 10 killer hurts we get no
aliasing
when the input frequency goes beyond 10
killer hurts
that higher frequency is going to get
alias down
into a lower frequency a consequence is
that then
is that as we go through the process
saying
and we demonstrate the frequency
response to the system
what we'll see in the output is
no alias saying when the input is below
10 killer hurts
as the input sweeps past 10 killer hurts
when when we let it which we will
eventually in the demonstration
dan in fact that frequency as it finally
shows up here
will begin to be aliased down into a
lower frequency
another way thinking about that is dead
when we watch the frequency response
love the system as
we look at the digital filter frequency
response
what we're sweeping and as we go from
zero
up to 10 killer hurts
in the input frequency is this portion
of the frequency response
as we sweep from 10 killer hurts out to
20 kilohertz
what we'll see is this portion the
frequency response
in other words will see it periodically
replicate
or if we look at the
corresponding continuous-time frequency
response
what it means really is that sweeping
from 0 to 10 killer hurts
is moving up this way and then sweeping
from 10 killer hurts
to 20 kilohertz on the input
really because if the alias saying
reflects itself in a digital filter by
looking back down it toward lower
frequencies and so the continuous-time
filter
sweeps back down from 10 killer hurts
back 20 okay
so that so we'll see and we'll see it in
several different ways as explained in
the demonstration
so now let's look and the frequency
response
sold now we like to illustrate
is the frequency response love the
acquittal in continuous-time
filter and we can do that by sweeping
the filter with a sinusoidal input
so what we'll see in this demonstration
is
on the upper trace the input sinusoid on
the lower trace the output sinusoid
using a 20 kilohertz sampling rate in a
sweep
from 0 to 10 killer hurts in other words
a sweep from 0 to
effectively hi interns at the digital
filter
so work will observe as the input
frequency increases
is that the output sinusoid will have
essentially constant amplitude
up to the cutoff frequency the filter
and then approximately zero amplitude
past so let's now sweet the filter
frequency response
and the area is the filter
cutoff frequency
now we can also observe the filter
frequency response in
several other ways one way in which we
can observe it is by
looking also at the amplitude if the
output sinusoid as
a function of frequency rather than as a
function of time
and so will observe that on the
left-hand SCO
while on the right-hand scope will have
the same trace their we just saw
namely to traces the upper traces the
input sinusoid
the lower traces the output sinusoid and
in addition to observing
the frequency response let's also listen
to the output sinusoid
and observe the attenuation
in the output as we go from the field to
pass band to the filter stopping again a
20 kilohertz sampling rate
and a sweep range from 0 to 10 killer
now
course when the filter stop
now if we increase the sweep range
from 10 killer hurts the 20 kilohertz
so that the sweep range is equal to the
sampling frequency
in essence that corresponds the sweeping
at the digital filter
from 0 to 2pi and in that case we'll
begin to see
some %uh the periodicity in the digital
filter frequency response
so let's do that now with 20 kilohertz
sampling rate
and a sweep range is 0 to 20 kilohertz
now as we come near to Pine
we get back into the past
an finally back to
a0 to 10 killer hurts we so they were
again sweeping
only from 0 to 2pi with regard to the
digital filter
now an important observation is that
with the digital or discrete-time
filter cutoff frequency fixed as i've
indicated here
and I remind you that what the cutoff
frequency is
is a 10 to hi with that cutoff frequency
fixed
because I love the normalization that we
get
as we come back to a continuous-time
filter in fact what we have
is a cutoff frequency dead is
dependent on the sampling frequency or
on the sampling period
and more specifically since the
discrete-time or digital
filter has a cutoff frequency which is
attentive to pie
the normalization as you recall
is dead to pie in discrete-time
frequency
corresponds to Omega sed s/ the sampling
in terms of continuous-time frequency
the consequence
is dead this cutoff frequency in fact
is 110 all
not to pine now because at the
normalization its 110
I'll the sampling frequency so
consequently as we change the sampling
frequency
what will happen is that even with the
discrete-time filter cutoff fixed
the cutoff frequency I'll the equivalent
continuous-time
filter will change now
that's what I want to demonstrate but
let me
again stress and ask you to keep in mind
dead
this demonstration is done without an
anti-aliasing filter in
and we are going to be changing the
sampling frequency
and so keep in mind dead as
we look at this as the input frequency
sweeps past half the sampling frequency
whatever sampling frequency we happen to
be looking at
then because the fact that there's no
anti-aliasing filter
will get daily as saying in other words
the frequency in the digital filter
discrete-time filter as we sweep the
input frequency up
will move up in frequency until we get
past half the sampling frequency and
then essentially will move back down
frequency consequently what will get
then are or we'll see our periodic
replications
the frequency response when we swept
past have see half the sampling alright
so now
let's look at the same digital filter
but the frequency response as
we change the sampling frequency now
what we would like to demonstrate is the
effective changing the same thing
frequency and we know that
the sampling that the effective filter
cutoff frequency
is tied to the sampling frequency
and for this particular filter
corresponds to attend
of the sampling frequency consequently
if we double the sampling frequency we
should double
the affective filter past and where war
double the filter cutoff frequency and
so let's do that now it again is 0-10
killer hurt sweep range
but a forty kilohertz sampling frequency
me and
we should observe that the filter cutoff
frequency has now doubled
out 24 killer now
let's begin to decrease the filter
sampling frequency
so from forty let's change the sampling
frequency to 20 kilohertz
we should see the cutoff frequency cut
in half me
now we can go even further we can cut
the sampling frequency down
10 killer hurts and remember that the
sweep range is 0 to 10 killer hurt so
now will be sweeping from 0 to 2pi
so as we get close to two pi will see
the passband again
and now
let's cut down the sampling frequency
even further
to by kilohertz my
here we are at 2pi
and then
at for pop alright so
that illustrates the effective changing
the sampling frequency
now let's conclude this demonstration at
the effect
on the sampling frequency on the filter
cutoff frequency by carrying out some
filtering
on some live audio white will
watching this case is the output
audio waveform as a function of time
on the single trace go and also
will listen to the output will begin it
with a forty killer hurts
sampling rate then reduce that to 20
kilohertz 10 killer hurts and then five
alerts
and in each of those cases the effective
filter cutoff frequency
then is cut in half from for keywords to
kill hurts
21 kilohertz and then to 500 cycles so
let's begin with the forty killer hurt
sampling frequency
or ineffective filter cutoff frequency
of work killer
now let's reduce net 20 kilohertz am
frequency or to kill hurts filter
and 10 kelleher sampling frequency
the
then finally in my Google Earth family
cigars running to me why minor in Psych
grueling
analog all the
I now let's finally include why
returning to
a little higher quality ragtime like me
the same
theme
right well hopefully
what you've seen in the demonstration
and in this lecture
is gives you a sense of feeling
for the analysis and the use
I'll discrete-time filters
for processing continuous-time signals
and
as you may be aware and as I've tried to
indicate
previously in the past this in fact is
one very important but not the only but
one very important
context in which discrete-time filtering
issues and this in fact is
an area that is developing rapidly
because at the fact dead
microprocessors digital technology
computers et cetera
afford considerable flexibility
in carrying out digital processing of
signals
and it is and went digital processing is
used at
naturally corresponds
to to implementing the processing
and analyzing it in discrete-time now
in the next lecture will be continuing
on another aspect developing another
aspect
love sampling any particular
what we'll be talking about is sampling
of discrete-time signals
as all indicate there one of the
contexts in which
discrete-time sampling in fact plays an
important role
is in the context in which
we are processing continuous-time
signals
using discrete time processing where in
fact
one step that we might want to take in
addition to the steps that we've talked
about here
is an additional sampling process
following
whatever kinds of filtering that we that
we do well that's a discussion and a
topic that will be going into in the
next lecture
thank you