the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home in
the
the in
the moon
the over the last series of lectures
in discussing filtering modulation
sampling we've seen how powerful
and useful the four EA transform is
beginning
with this lecture and over the next
several lectures I'd
like to develop and exploit a
generalization
other 48 transform which will not only
lead to some important new insights
about signals and systems
but also will remove some of the
restrictions
that we've had with the Fourier
transform the generalization
dead we'll be talking about in the
continuous-time cases referred to
as the apostrophe its form and in the
discrete-time cases referred to as the z
transform
but I'd like to do in today's lecture is
begin on the continuous-time
case namely a discussion at the La Paz
transform
continued at it to the next lecture and
following that
develop the z transform for
discrete-time
and also as we go along exploit
the two notions together now
to introduce the notion of the law
applies transform
let me remind you again all what led us
into the Fourier transform we
develop the 48 transform by
considering the idea love representing
signals as linear combinations a basic
signals
and in the Fourier transform in the
continuous-time case the basic signals
that we picked in the representation
were complex exponentials
and in what we refer to as
the synthesis equation the synthesis
equation corresponded
to in effect a dick opposition as a
linear combination
decomposition affects ft as a linear
combination of complex exponentials
and of course associated with this was
the corresponding analysis equation dead
in effect gave us the amplitudes
associated with the complex exponentials
now why did we pick complex exponentials
well recall that the reason was
that complex exponentials are I can
functions of linear time-invariant
systems
and that was very convenient
specifically
if we have a linear time-invariant
system
with an impulse response 850 well we had
shown
is that that class a systems has the
property
that if we put in a complex exponential
we get out
a complex exponential at the same
frequency
and with the change in amplitude and
this change in amplitude
in fact corresponded as we showed as the
discussion went along
to 248 transform all
the system impulse response so
the notion love decomposing signals
into complex exponentials was very
intimately connected in the Fourier
transforms very intimately connected
with the eigenfunction property a
complex exponentials for linear
time-invariant systems
well complex exponentials have that type
are not
the only I can functions for linear
time-invariant systems
in fact what you've seen previously
is that if we took a more general
exponential
you to the st. where s
is a more general complex number not
just J Omega
but in fact Sigma plus J Omega for any
bad you have s
a comp the complex exponential is an
eigenfunction
and we can justify that simply by
substitution into the convolution
integral
in other words the response to this
complex exponential
is the convolution up the impulse
response
with the exhortation an notice
there we can break this term into a
product
eat to the st. you need to the minus s
now and BU the st. term
become outside the integration
and consequently just carrying through
that algebra
would reduce this integral
to an integral with
in the st. fact there outside so just
simply carrying through the algebra
what we would conclude is that a complex
exponential
with any complex number ass which
generate as an output
a complex exponential have the same form
multiplied by whatever this integral is
and this integral of course will depend
on what the value a veces
but that's all that it will depend on or
said another way
what this all can be denoted as
is some function Hibs that
depends on the value of s so finally
then you the st. as an exhortation
to linear time-invariant system
generates a response
which is a complex constant depending on
S
multiplying the same
function that excited the system
so what we have been is
the I can function property more
generally in terms of
a more general complex exponential
where the complex factor is given by
this integral
well in fact with that integral
corresponds to
is what we will the fine
as the apostrophe its form of the
impulse response
and in fact we can apply this
transformation
to a more general time function that may
or may not be
the impulse response this ove a linear
time-invariant system
and so in general it is this
transformation
on a time function which is
the a-plus transform that time function
and it's a functional bests so
the definition up the applause transform
is that the applause transform overtime
function X 50
is the result love this transformation
on exit to the it's the noted as
excessive ass
and as a shorthand notation as we had
with the four EA transform
then we have in the time domain the time
function except the
and in the apostrophe its form domain
the
function XFS and these then
represent a transformed pair
now let me remind you that
that the the development of that mapping
is exactly the process that we went
through initially in developing
a mapping that ended up giving the
giving us the Fourier transform
essentially what we've done is just
broaden your horizon
some white or our notation some white
and rather than pushing just the complex
exponential through the system
we've pushed a more general time
function either the st.
where ass is a complex number with both
a real part in an imaginary part
well the discussion we going through so
far course is
very closely related to when what we
went through
for the Fourier transform the mapping
and we've ended up with
is called the applause transform and as
you can well imagine and perhaps
may have recognized already there's a
very close connection
between the applause transform and the
Fourier transform
well to see wanted the connections well
we can observe
is that if we look at the Fourier
transform expression
and if we look at the applause transform
expression
where ass is now a general complex
number Sigma plus jail maker
these two expressions in fact are
identical
if in fact Sigma is equal to 0
if signatures equal to 0 so that ass is
just jail maker
then all that this transformation is
is the same as that substitute in s
equals jail maker
and this is what we get so
what this then tells us is dead if we
have the apostrophe it's for
and if we look at the applause transform
at
ass equals J Omega
then that in fact corresponds to
the Fourier transform affect safety
now there's a slight notational issue
that this raises and it's very
straightforward to clean it up
but it's something that its you have to
just kinda
focus on for second to understand what
the issue is
notice that on the left hand side of
this equation
X a vast representing the applause
transform
when we look at that would signal to 0
RS equal to jail maker
are natural inclination is to write that
as exit J Omega of course
on the other hand the right hand side of
the equation namely the Fourier
transform exit T
we've typically written as
X all Omega focusing on the fact that
it's a function love this variable Omega
well there's a slight awkwardness here
because here we're talking about
an argument J Omega here we're talking
about an argument Omega
and a very straightforward way of
dealing with that is
to simply change our notation
for the Fourier transform recognizing
that the Fourier transform
course is a function of Omega but it's
also
in fact the function J Omega and if we
write it that way
then the two notations come together in
other words the applause transform
at st. cause jail maker just simply were
reduces both mathematically and
rotationally
to the Fourier transform so the notation
that will now be adopting
for the four th transform is the
notation
whereby we express the 48 transform no
longer simply as active Omega
but choosing as the argument jail make
simple notational change
now here we see one relationship between
the Fourier transform and
the the plots transform namely that
the poss transform pressequals chair
maker reduces to the Fourier transform
we also have number another important
relationship
in particular the fact that the
applause transform can be interpreted
as the Fourier transform all a modified
version affect safety let let me show
you what I mean
here of course we have the relationship
that we just developed
namely s equals jail maker plus
transform reduces the Fourier transform
but now let's look at the more general
applause transform expression
and if we substitute in s equals Sigma
plus J Omega
which is the general form for this
complex variable ass
and we carry through so the algebra
breaking this into the product up to
exponential
the product the two exponential see the
minus Sigma T
time see the minus jail make it to the
we now have
this expression where of course in both
these
their is a DT
and now when we look at this
what we observe is that this in fact
is the 48 transform of something
what's the something it's not accept T
anymore it's the Fourier transform up
x50
multiplied by e2 the minus Sigma T
so if we think I've these two terms
together
this in a brawl is just the four EA
transform
it's the for a transformer Beck city
multiplied
by an exponential Sigma is greater than
its a an exponential that
the case with time Sigma is less than 0
it's an exponential the crows
time so we have
then this additional relationship which
tells us that the apostrophe s for
is the 48 transform love
and exponentially weighted time function
now this exponential weighting has
some important significance in
particular
recall that there were issues have
convergence with the 48 transform in
particular the Fourier transform
may or may not converge and for
convergence in fact
what's required is that but I'm
fortunate we're transforming be
absolutely integral now
we can have a time function that isn't
absolutely integral
because let's say it grows exponentially
as time
increases but when we multiply it by
this
exponential factor that's embodied in a
posh transform
in fact that brings the function back
down for positive time
and will impose absolute integrability
on the product %uh XFT times
e2 the minus Sigma T and so
the conclusion an important point is
that
the applause transformed the Fourier
transform this product may converge
even though the Fourier transform
effective t doesn't in other words
the apostrophe s form may converge even
when the Fourier transform
doesn't converge and will see that will
see examples of it is the discussion
goes along now let me also
draw your attention to the fact although
we won't be
working through this in detail
to the fact that this equation
in effect provides the basis
for us to figure out how to express
accept T
interns love the applause transform
effect we can apply the inverse Fourier
transform to this
thereby to this account for the
exponential factor by bring it over to
the other side
and if you go through this and in fact
you'll have an opportunity to go through
this both in the video course manual
and also it's carried through in the
text
what you end up with is
a synthesis equation X expression for
exit T
in terms of Xmas which corresponds to a
synthesis equation
and which now builds x50 I have a linear
combination if not
necessarily functions the foreign to the
Chi Omega TV
but interns love functions
or basic signals which are more general
exponentials
you to the st.
okay well let's just look at
some examples love the apostrophe s form
of some time functions
and these examples that I'll go through
are all examples that are worked out in
attacks and so I don't want to focus on
the algebra what I'd like to focus on
are some with the issues and the
interpretation
let's first the ball look at example
the example in the text which is example
9.1
if we take the Fourier transform
love this exponential then as you well
know
the result that we have is one over J
Omega plus a
and bekannt converge for any a
in particular it's only for a greater
than 0
what that really means is that for
convergence of the 48 transform this has
to be
a decaying exponential it can't be
in increasing exponentially if
instead we apply the applause
transformed to this
applying to the the deal applies
transform is the same as taking the 48
transform or
X 50 times an exponential in and
the exponential that we would multiply
by is he to the minus Sigma T
so in effect taking the applause
transform of this
is like taking the Fourier transform
augie to the minus eighty
e2 the minus Sigma T
and if we carry that through just
working through the integral we end up
with applause transform which is one
over est plus a
but just as in the Fourier transform
the Fourier transform all converge for
any a
now what happens is that the
love pasta Rance form will only converge
when the forty a transformer this
converges
said another way it's when the
combination is a plus Sigma
is greater than 0 so we would require
that by right over here a plus Sigma
is greater than 0 warmer that Sigma
is greater than minus a so in fact
in the apostrophe s former this
we have an expression one over est plus
a but
we also require in interpreting that
dead the real party bass be greater
then minus a so that
essentially the 48 transform up X 50
times you to the minus Sigma T converges
so it's important to recognize that the
algebraic expression that we get is
only valid for certain values love the
real party vez
and so for this example we can summarize
it as
this exponential as the apostrophe s
form which is one over est plus a
where ass is restricted to the range the
real party best greater than
minus a now
we haven't had this issue before love
restrictions on what the value a veces
with the with 48 transform either
recover Jordan converge
with a plot strands form there are
certain values the best we now have more
flexibility and so they're certain
values are the real party best for which
it converges in certain values for which
it doesn't
the values Ave S for which the
apostrophe s form
converges is the values
are referred to as the region of
convergence
up the applause transform
and it's important to recognize that
in specifying the applause transform
what's required is not only the
algebraic expression
but also the domain or set of values
evas
for which that algebraic expression is
ballot just two
underscore that point let me draw your
attention to another
example in the text which is example 9.2
example 9.2 we have an exponential
for negative time 0 for positive time
and if you carry through the algebra
there you end up with
a low price transform expression which
is again one over S plus a
exactly the same algebraic expression as
we head for the previous example
the important distinction is that now
the real party bass is restricted to be
less than minus a
it so in fact if you compare this
example
with the one above it and let's just
look back at
the answer that we had the air
if you compare that those two examples
here
the algebraic expression is 100 breast
but say with a certain
regional convergence here
the algebraic expression is one over est
plus a
and the only difference between those
two is the domain a region of
convergence
so there's another complication or twist
now
not only do we need to generate the
algebraic expression
but we also have to be careful to
specify
the region of convergence
over which that algebraic expression is
valid
now later on in this lecture and
actually also
arm as the discussion a little past
transform goes on
will begin to see and understand more
about
how the region of convergence relates to
various properties of the time function
okay well let's finally look at one
additional example from the tax
and this is example 9.3 and what it
consists of
is the a type function which is the sum
love two exponentials and
although we haven't formally talked
about properties a little fuss transform
yet
what are the properties that will see it
is relatively easy to develop
is the fact that the apostrophe s form
of Assam
is the summer the applause transform so
in fact we can get
the applause transform love the solo
these two terms
as some love the apostrophe its forms
and so for this one we know from the
example that we at looked at previously
example 9.1
that this is a form one over est plus
one
with a region of convergence which is
the real party best greater than -1
for this one we have a poss transform
which is one over est plus two
with a region of convergence which is
the real party bass
greater than -2 so
for the two of them together we have to
take the overlap with those two regions
in other words we have to take the
region that encompasses both the real
party best greater than -1
in the real party best greater than -2
and if we put those together then
we have a combined regional convergence
which is the real party best
greater than -1 so this is the
expression
and for this particular example what we
have
is a ratio of polynomials
the ratio polynomials is a numerator
polynomial and at the nominator
polynomial
and it's convenient to
summarize these by
plotting the roots love the numerator
polynomial
and the roots to the denominator
polynomial in the complex plane
and the complex plane which they are
plotted is referred to
as vs playing
so we can for example take the
denominator polynomial
and summarize it in by specifying the
fact
or by representing the fact
that it has roots at st. cause -1 and at
a Sikh was minus-2
and I've done that in this picture by
putting an X
where the roots have the denominator
polynomial order
the numerator polynomial has a rude ass
equals
-3 hands and i've represented that by a
circle
so these are the roots to the
denominator polynomial
and this is the route up the numerator
polynomial for this example
and also for this example we can
represent
the region of convergence which
is the real party best greater than -1
and so that's in fact
the region over here
there is also if I draw these just the
router the numerator and denominator
plan of polynomials
I would need an additional piece of
information
to specify the algebraic expression
completely namely
multiply constant out in front of the
whole thing
well this particular example has
the applause transform as a
rational function namely its one
polynomial in the numerator and another
polynomial in the denominator
and in fact as we'll see applies
transformers which are ratios are
polynomials
form a very important class they were in
fact represent systems
better describe a ball by linear
constant coefficient differential
equations
you shouldn't necessarily in fact for
sure you shouldn't see why
that's true now will see that later but
that means that a-plus transforms
that are rational functions namely
the ratio love the numerator polynomial
divided by the nominator polynomial
become very important in the discussion
that follows
and in fact in we have some terminology
for this the route so the numerator
polynomial
are referred to as zeros
up the applause transform because of
course those are the values a bass
at which XFS become 0
and the roots to the denominator
polynomial are
referred to as the polls up the applause
transform
and those are the values vs
at which the applause transform blows up
namely becomes infinite if you think
love setting s
equal to evaluate this denominator
polynomial goes to zero
of course extra bass becomes infinite
and
what we would expect in a course will
see that
that this is true well we would expect
is that wherever that happens there must
be some problem
with convergence oval poss transform and
indeed the applause transformed doesn't
converge
at the polls namely at the roots the
denominator polynomial
so in fact let's focus in on that a
little further
let's examine and talk about the region
of convergence
all the applause transform and
how its associated both with properties
of the time function
and also with the location love the
polls
all the applause transform and as we'll
see
the air are some very specific and
important
relationships and conclusions that we
can draw
about how the region of convergence
is constrained an Associated with the
locations the polls in the ass point
well to begin with we can
of course make the statement as I just
made
that the region of convergence contains
no polls
in particular if I think
love this general rational function
the polls love XFS by the values evas
at which the denominator 0 or equivalent
Lee
XFS blows up and of course
then that implies that the expression is
no longer converged
okay well that's one statement that we
can make now there
are some others and one for example
is the statement that if I have a point
in the S plane that corresponds the
convergence
then in fact any line in the S plane
with that same real part will also
be said %uh values for which the
apostrophes form converges
and what's the reason for that the
reason for that
is dead s is Sigma plus J Omega
and convergence all the applause
transform is associated with
convergence love the four EA transform
all
it to the minus Sigma see times X 50
and so the convergence only depends on
Sigma
if it only depends on Sigma than
for one if it converges for one value
Sigma
I'm sorry for what for a value Sigma
for some valuable maker Danny will
converge
for that same Sigma for any valuable
make
the conclusion n is dead the region of
convergence
if I have a law if I have a point that I
also have a line
and so what that suggests is that as we
look at the regional convergence
in fact corresponds to strips in the
complex plane
now finally we can tie together
the region of convergence to the
convergence of the Fourier transform in
particular since we know that
the applause transform reduces
to the 48 transform when
the complex variable yes is Sigma is
equal to jail maker
the implication is that if we have the
law applies transform
and if the a-plus transform reduces to
the 48 transform
when sick make 10 in other words when s
is equal to jail make a
then the 4e a transformative exit see
converging is equivalent to the
statement
that the a-plus transform converges
for Sigma equal to 0 in other words that
the region of convergence
includes what DJ Omega axis
in the ass point
alright so we have then some statements
that kinda tied together the location of
the polls
and the region convergence let me make
one other statement which is
much harder statement to justify and I
won't try to I just simply stated
and that is that the regional
convergence oval plus transform
is a connected region in other words
if the entire region
consists of a single strap in the S
plane
it can consist of a strip over here for
example in a strip over there
well let me let me I'm emphasize summer
those points a little further
let's suppose that I A have
ale a-plus transform
and Google+ transform their
I am talking about is a rational
function which is
one over S plus one times as plus two
then the poll 0 pattern as its referred
to
in the S play in the location love the
roots love the
numerator and denominator polynomial
course there is no numerator polynomial
the denominator polynomial roots which
have represented by these X's
are shown here and so this is
the poll 0 pattern
and from what I said the region of
convergence
can't include any polls
and it must correspond to strips
in the ass plane and furthermore it must
be
just want some one connected region
rather than multiple regions
and so with this algebraic expression
then the possible choices for the region
of convergence
consistent with those properties are the
following:
one of them would be region of
convergence
to the right love this poll
a second would be a region of
convergence
which lies between the two poles
as a show here and
a third is region of convergence
which is to the left love this poll
and because it the fact dead I said
without proof that
the region of convergence must be a
single strip it can't be multiple strips
in fact we could not consider as a
possible region convergence
what I show here in so in fact
this is not a valid region of
convergence
there are only three possibilities
Associated
with this poll 0 pattern namely to the
writer this poll
between the two poles and to the left
that this poll
now to carry the discussion further
we can in fact associate
the region of convergence above the law
applies transform
with some very specific characteristics
of the time function and what this will
do is to help us understand
how various for various choices
love the region of convergence the
interpretation
that we can impose on the related time
function
let me show you what I mean
suppose that we start with
a time function as i indicated here
which is a finite
duration time function in other words
it's zero
except in some time interval now
recall that the Fourier transform
converges
if the time for action has the property
that is absolutely integral and as long
as everything stays finite and
interns have ample to in a finite
duration signal
there's no difficulty that we're gonna
run into here
now here the Fourier transform will
converge and now
the question is what can we say about
the reach of convergence
of the apostrophe it's for well
the applies transform is the Fourier
transform
all the time function multiplied by an
exponential
and so we can ask a pan out whether we
can destroy the absolute integrability
of this
by multiplying by an exponential that
the case
that grows too fast in the case too fast
to whatever let's take a look at that
suppose that this time function
is absolutely integral and
let's multiply it by
a decaying exponential so this is now
except eat I'm see the minus Sigma T
if I think multiplying these two
together
and what you can see is that for
negative for positive time
sort of thinking informally I'm helping
the integrability of the product because
I'm pushing this part down
for negative time unfortunately I'm
making things bro
but I don't let them grow indefinitely
because there's some time before which
this is equal to 0 likewise
if I head a growing exponential
then for a growing exponential
for negative time or for this part
perhaps
this part making things smaller for
positive time eventually this expansion
was growing without
found but the time function stocks at
some point
so the idea then kinda is dead
for a finite duration
time function no matter what kinda
exponential I multiply by whether it's
going this way are going this way
because of the fact that
essentially the limits on the integral
are fine I'd I'm
guaranteed that'll always maintain
absolute integrability
and so in fact then for a finite
duration time function
the region of convergence is the entire
s play
okay now in we can also
make statements about other kinds of
time functions
and let's look
at a time function
which I a defined as a right-sided
time function and
a right-sided time function is one which
is 0 up until sometime and then
it goes on after that presumably off to
infinity
now let me remind you that
the whole issue here with the region of
convergence
has to do with exponentials
that we can multiply a time function by
and have the product end up being
absolutely integral
well supposed dead when I multiply this
time function
by an exponential which lets ATK's
but an exponentially to the minus Sigma
0t
what you can see me sort of intuitively
is dead if
this product is absolutely integral
if I would increase Sigma 0 then I'm
making things even better for positive
time because I'm pushing them down
and whereas they might be worse for
negative time
that doesn't matter because before some
time
the product is equal to 0 so if this
product is absolutely an agreeable
then if are chosen exponential
it's a minus signal one teeny where
signal one
is greater than 60 then that product
will also be absolutely integral ball
and we can draw
important conclusion about that about
the region of convergence from that
in particular we can make this statement
dead if the time function is right sided
and if convergence
occurs for some value segment 0
then in fact we will have convergence of
the law applies transform
for all values all the real party bass
greater than Sigma 0 the reason
of course being dead if Sigma 0
increases
then the exponential DK's even faster
for positive time
now what that says then thinking another
way enters the region of convergence
as we might droid in the ass plane is
that
if we have a point that's in the region
of convergence corresponding to some
value Sigma 0
band all values evas to the right of
that
in the S plane will also be in the
region convergence
we can also combine that with the
statement that for rational functions
we know dead there can't be any polls
in the region of convergence if you put
those two statements together
then we end up with a statement dead if
x50 is right sided and if it's a plus
transformers rational
then the region of convergence is to the
right
up the rightmost poll so
we have here a very important insight
which tells us
dead weekend im in for some property
about the time function from the region
of convergence
or conversely if we know something about
the time function namely being right
sided
then we can infer something about the
regional convergence
well in addition to right-sided
signals we can also have left sided
signals
Analects I did signal is essentially a
right-sided signal turned around
in other words a left-sided signal is
one
that is zero after some time
well we can carry out exactly the same
kind of argument there
namely if the signal goes off to
infinity in the negative time direction
and stops
someplace for positive time if I have an
exponential
I can multiply it by and have that
product be absolutely integral ball
but if I choose an exponential that
decays even faster for negative times
that I'm pushing the stuff
way out there down even further then
II enhance the integrability even more
an you might have to think through that
a little bit but it's exactly
the flip side of the argument for
right-sided signals
and the conclusion and is dead
if we have a left-sided signal
and we have a point a value up the real
party best which is in the region of
convergence
then in fact all values
to the left at that point in the S plane
will also be in the region of
convergence
now solar to the statement that we made
for right-sided signals
if expertise left-sided and in fact
we're talking about a rational applies
transform which we most
typically well then in fact we can make
the statement
there the region of convergence is to
the left
of the leftmost poll because
we know it has if we find a point that's
in the region of convergence
everything to the left then has to be in
the region of convergence
we can have any polls in the region of
convergence you put those two statements
together and it says
is to the left the leftmost poll
now the final situation is the situation
where
we have a signal which is neither right
side or left side it goes off to
infinity for positive time
and it goes off to infinity for negative
time and their the thing to kinda
recognizes that
if you multiply by an exponential and
its decaying
very fast for positive time it's gonna
be growing very fast for negative time
conversely if it became very fast for
negative time is growing very fast for
positive time
and this kind of this notion of trying
to balance the value Sigma
and in effect with that says is that the
region of convergence can't
extent too far to the left or too far to
the right
said another way for a two-sided
signal and if we have a point which is
in the region of convergence
than that point defines
strip in the ass plane dead takes
that point and extends it to the left
until you bump into a pole
an extensive to the right until you bump
into a pole
fight so he you begin today and see that
we can tie together some properties in
the region of convergence
and the right-sided mister left-sided
mister two-sided NIS
love the time function and you have a
chance to examine that
in more detail in the video course
manual
let's conclude this lecture by talking
about
how we might get the time function
given the low class transformed
well if we have a plus transform we can
in principle get the time function back
again by
recognizing this relationship between
the applause transform
and the 48 transform and using the
formal for EA transform expression
or quietly the formal inverse Laplace
transform
expression which is in the tax but more
typically what we would do is
what we've done also with the Fourier
transform
which is to use simple
plus transform pairs together with the
notion
all the partial fraction expansion and
let's just go through that with an
example
let's suppose that I have
a a-plus transform as i indicated here
and its polls are applied and a region
of convergence which
is to the right if this poll and what we
can identify
from the region of convergence in fact
is that we're talking
about a right-sided time function
so the rear richer convergence is the
real party best greater than -1
and now looking down at the algebraic
expression
we have the algebraic expression for
this is i indicate here
acquittal on tlie expanded in a partial
fraction expansion
as a show below so if you just simply
combine these together
that's the same as this and the region
of convergence
is the real party bass greater than -1
now the region of convergence or
this is a solid to turn so the the time
function is this summer to time
functions
and the region of convergence
all love the combination must be
the intersection of the region of
convergence associated with each one
recognizing that this is to the right of
the polls
that tells us immediately that each of
these two
then would correspond to bill plus
transform
love a right-sided time function
well let's look at it term by term
the first term is the factor 1 over s
plus one
with the region of convergence to the
right if this poll
and this hat algebraically
corresponds to what i've indicated and
this in fact
is similar to or special case if the
example that we pointed to at the
beginning at the lecture namely example
9.1
and so we can just simply use that
result if you think back
to that example or refer to your notes
we know
dead time function of the form
eat to -80 gives us all a plus transform
which is one over S Plus
a with the real party bass greater than
minus a and so this is the applause
transformer the first
or sorry this is the inverse the poss
transform the first term
if we now consider the poll add
s equals -2
and here is the region of convergence
that we originally began with
in fact we can having removed the pole
at -1
extend this region of convergence
to this poll and we now have
an algebraic expression which is -1 over
s plus
to the real party best greater than -1
although in fact we can extend the
region of convergence
up to the poll and the inverse
transformer this is now again
referring to the same example minus you
to the -2 T
times a unit step and if we simply
put the two turns together then
adding the one that we have here to what
we had before
we have a total inverse Laplace
transform
which is that
so essentially what's happened is dead
each of the ex each over the polls has
contributed
an exponential factor and because if the
region of convergence
being to the right of all those polls
that
is consistent with the notion that both
of those terms correspond to right-sided
time functions
well it's just the focus for
for a second or two on the same
Posey role pattern but instead I love
a region of convergence which is to the
right at the polls
as we had before well now take a region
of convergence which is between the two
poles
and I'll let you work through this more
leisurely
in the video course manual but when we
carry out the partial fraction expansion
as I've done below
we would now associate with this poll
a regional convergence to the right with
this poll
a region of convergence to the left
and so while what we would have
is the sum love a right-sided time
function due to this poll
and in fact that serve the form you to
the minus T
pretty positive and a left-sided
type function due to this poll
and in fact that serve the form in the
minus two TV
pretty negative and so in fact
the answer that we will get when we
decompose this
use the partial fraction expansion being
very careful
about associating the region of
convergence
this poll to the right and if this poll
to the left
will have then when we're all done a
time
function which will be of the form eats
the minus
T times a unit step pretty positive
and then we'll have a term of the for me
to the I'm sorry this would-be to the
minus 2 T's since this is at -2 in this
is
-1 this would be a plus sign in this
would be minus
you to the minus the for TE negative
and you look at that a little more
carefully when
I you sit down with the video course
manual
okay well what we've gone through rather
quickly is
an introduction to the applause
transform
and a couple points to underscore again
is the fact that the applause transform
is very closely associated
with the Fourier transform and in fact
the applause transform
4s equals jail maker reduces to the 48
transform
but more generally the a-plus transform
is the 48 transform
love x50 with
an exponential weighting and there are
some exponentials for which that product
converges there are other exponentials
for which
that product has a Fourier transform
that doesn't converge
bad then imposes on the discussion above
plus transform
what we refer to as the region of
convergence
and it's very important to understand
that in specifying a a-plus transform
it's important to identify not only
the algebraic expression but also the
values the best namely
for which it it's valid namely
the region of convergence low class
transformed finally what we did was to
tied together some properties over time
function
with things that we can say about the
regional convergence office supplies
transform
now just as with the Fourier transform
the applause transformer has some very
important properties and I love these
properties both
are some mechanisms for using a fast
transforming
for such such systems as linear cut
those described by a linear cut the
coefficient
differential equations but more
importantly
the properties will help us as we
understand the further
will help us in using exploiting
the appliance transform to study and
understand
linear time-invariant systems and
thats what will go on to next time in
particular
talking about properties and then
associating
with linear time-invariant systems much
of the discussion
dead we've had today relating
to the austrians 1 thank you