the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT ided you
home
in
the norm
are
the last lecture we discuss the number
general properties for systems which
as you recall applied both to
continuous-time
and to discrete-time systems
and these properties were the properties
associated with the system having memory
the issue
love whether a system is or isn't
convertible
we talked about causality instability
and finally we talked about when the
arity
and time-invariant in today's lecture
what I'd like to do is focused
specifically on when the arity in time
invariance
and show how for systems that have those
properties
we can exploit them to generate
a general representation well let me
begin by
just reviewing the two properties again
quickly
time invariance as you recall
is a property that apply both to
continuous-time and discrete-time
systems
and in essence stated bad for any given
input and output relationship if we
simply shift the input than the output
shift by the same amount
and of course exactly the same kind of
statement
applied in discrete-time so it i mean
variance was a property
it said that the system didn't care
about what the time origin
the signal is when the arity
was a property related to the fact that
if we have
et cetera outputs associated with a
given set of inputs
as i've indicated here with the inputs
as feasted K and the output decisive K
then the property of when the arity
States that if we have an input
which is a linear combination up those
inputs
then the output is
a linear combination of the Associated
outputs
so that linear combination of inputs
generates for linear system at the end
output which is
a linear combination up the Associated
outputs now
the question is how can we exploit the
properties have many arity
and time-invariant and there's a basic
strategy
which will flow more or less through
mostly this court's
the strategy is to
attempt to decompose the signal you the
continuous-time and discrete-time
into it said a basic signals
and I've indicated that
here and the question then
is what basic signal should we pick well
the answer kinda is we should pick said
a basic signals
they provide a certain degree have
analytical convenience
so we choose instead of inputs for the
decomposition
bad provide outputs
that we can easily generate now and
we'll see
when we do this there are to
classes love inputs that are
particularly suited
to that strategy one class is
the set love the late impulses namely
decomposing a signal into a linear
combination if the
is and as we'll see that leads to a
representation
for linear time-invariant systems which
is referred to
as convolution a second
is a decomposition of inputs into
complex exponentials
a linear combination of complex
exponentials
and that leads to a representation
love signals and systems through what
will refer to as
for your analysis now
four-day analysis will be a topic for
a setup later lectures but I'd like to
begin with
is the representation in terms of
impulses and the associated description
linear time-invariant systems using
convolution
so let's begin where
a discussion are discrete-time signals
and in particular the issue of how
discrete-time signals
can be decomposed as a linear
combination
love the lady impulses
well in fact it's relatively
straightforward
what I've shown here is a general
sequence with values which i've
indicated
at the top and more or less
as we did when we talked about
representing
a unit step in terms of impulses
we can think of this general sequence as
a sequence
I'll impulses delayed
namely occurring at the appropriate
prime instant and and with the
appropriate ample to
so we can think love this general
sequence
as and im polls occurring at an equal 0
and and with the high dive exit 0
plus and im polls all quite active one
occurring at time n equals 1 and so
that's active one time
Delta than -1 and in polls at -1
with an amplitude love exit -1
et cetera so if we continue
to generate a said Oh waited the late
unit samples like that
and if we had all these together
then that will generate the total
sequence
algebraically then what that corresponds
to
is representing the sequence as
some love individual turns over as i've
indicated here
or in terms over general thumb
the song %uh exit K felt the then minus
K
so that's our strategy the strategy is
to decompose
an arbitrary sequence into a linear
combination
or waited too late impulses and here
again is the representation which we
just
finish generating
now why is this representation useful
it's useful because we now have a
decomposition at the sequence
as a linear combination all basic
sequences namely that the late impulses
and if we are talking about a linear
system
the response to that linear combination
is a linear combination of the responses
so if we denote the response
to with the late in paul's as H+ the
cave and
then the response to
this general input is what i've
indicated here
where why event of course is the output
due to the general in protective and
H+ the cave and is the output do
to the late in polls and these are
simply
the coefficients in the waiting
so for linear system we have
this representation and
if now in addition the system is
time-invariant
we can in fact relate the outputs
due to these individuals the late in
polls
specifically if the system is
time-invariant
then the response to an impulse at the
time
K is exactly the same as the response to
an impulse at time 0
shifted over two-time K said another way
h2k a van it simply
80 then minus K where 80
is the response to the system to an
impulse at an equal 0
and it's generally useful to
rather than carrying around 80 a band
just simply define 80 then
as a chip and which is
the unit sample or unit impulse response
to the system
and so the consequent then is for
a linear time-invariant system
the output can be expressed as this
some where a true then minus K
is the response to an impulse occurring
at time n equals K
and this is referred to
as the convolution saw
now we can just to emphasize
how we've going about this let me show
it from another perspective
we of course have taken the sequence X
the van
we have decomposed that as
a linear combination out these waited
the late impulses
when these are added together those
correspond
to the original sequence active and
if this in polls for example
generates a response
which is exit 0 times a chip and we're a
tremendous the response
to unit in polls at an equal 0
and the second one the late generates
the delayed
waited response and the third one
similarly
and we generate these individual
responses
these are all added together and it that
linear combination
that forms the final output
so that's really kind of the way we're
thinking about it we have a general
sequence
we're thinking love each individual
sample
individually each one of those pops the
system
and because the linearity the response
is the sum
for those individual responses
well thats what happens in discrete-time
and
pretty much the same strategy works in
continuous-time
a particular
we can begin in continuous-time
with the notion 0 decomposing
a continuous-time signal into
succession love are bitterly narrow
rectangles
and as these rectangles is the with the
rectangles goes
0 the approximation gets better and
essentially what's going to happen is
that you to those individual rectangles
as they get narrower and narrower
correspond more and more
to an impulse well let me show you what
I mean
here we have a continue with time signal
and I've approximated it
by staircase
so in Athens I can't think of this
as individual rectangles
a fight associated with the height the
continuous curve
and so i've indicated that down below
here for example
is the impulse corresponding to the
rectangle between
people's -2 dealt in people's minds
felker
here's the one from minus felt that 20
and as we continue on down we get
impulses or rather rectangles from
success the park to the way for
now let's look specifically at the
rectangle for example starting at zero
and ending at Delta
and the amplitude of it is exit Delta
and so
what we have actually this should be
exit 0
and so not be just correct that
here that sex is zero and so
we have a rectangle a fight exit 0
and recall the function that I defined
last time
as dealt this the capital Delta p
which had height1 over Delta and with
dealt
so multiply finally by this last little
Delta
then this is a representation for
the rectangle that i've shown there now
there's a little bit about you were
there too kinda track through
but what we're really doing is just
simply representing this
in terms the rectangles what I want to
do is describing each rectangle
as in terms that function dealt with the
bell 30
which in the limit then becomes an
impulse well so extract that
through a little further
when we have that linear combination
then were saying that x50 can be
represented
by Osama's I indicate here
which I can then
right more generally in this form just
indicating that this is an infinite sum
we now want to take the limit as Delta
goes to zero
and his daughter goes to zero notice
that this term becomes are bitterly
narrow
this goes to our impulse function and
this of course
goes to exit Towne and in fact
in the limit some out this form
is exactly the way an integral is the
point
so we have an expression for wire T
in terms of an impulse function their I
have to admit
is a little bit have detailed the kinda
focus on
at your leisure but this is the general
load the strategy
so what we have now is and integral
tell that tells us how except he can be
described
as a thong or linear combination
involving in polls
this bottom equation by the way is often
referred to as the sifting integral
in essence what it says is that if I
take a time function exit tea and put it
through that integral
the impulse as did dipped by
generates X-eighty all over again
now at first glance what it could look
like
is that we've taken a time function X 50
and proceeded to represented in a very
complicated way
interns have itself and one could ask
her why bother doing that
and the reason going back to what r
strategy was is that
what we want to do is exploit
the property lovely area so
by describing a time function
as a linear combination have waited too
late impulses
as in effect we've done through
this some Asian that corresponds to a
decomposition in terms of impulses
we can now exploit linearity
specifically recognizing that the output
have a linear system is this some
or the responses to these individual
inputs
so with h2k
Delta I love see corresponding to the
response
to built this adult the T-minus k Delta
and arrested this stop the exit k Delta
and there's little doubt the
are basically scale factors for a linear
system
then if the input is expressed in this
form
the output is expressed in this form
again taking the limit is Delta goes to
zero
by definition this corresponds to an
integral
and it the integral that we indicated
that I indicate here
with H+ the tower T corresponding to
the impulse response
due to an impulse occurring at
time town now again we can do
the same thing a in particular
if the system is time-invariant then the
response to each of these the late
impulses
is simply at the late version up the
impulse response
and so we can relate these individual
terms
and in particular than the response to
an impulse occurring at time t cloth
towel
it's simply the response to an impulse
occurring at time 0
shifted over to the time origin town
and again as we did before but dropped
the subscript 80
so 80 love the
will simply defined as a trip to the
and what we're left with when we do that
is the description over linear
time-invariant system
through this integral which tells us
how the output is related to
the input and two the impulse response
again let's just quickly look at this
from another perspective as we did in
discrete-time
recall that what we've done is to take
the
continuous function decomposed it in
terms
%uh rectangles and then
each of these rectangles generates
its individual response
and then these individual responses are
added together
and as we go through that process
the chorus there's a process whereby
we let the approximation go to the
to the representation over smooth talker
now again I stress that their is
certainly
paramount to kinda examined carefully
there
but it's important to also reflect on
what we've done which
is really pretty significant well we've
managed to accomplish
is to exploit the properties linear
ready in time invariance
so that the system could be represented
interns only over its response to
and in polls at time 0 so for a linear
time-invariant system quite amazingly
actually
if you know its response to an impulse
at equal 0 or 10 equal 0 depending on
discrete or continuous time then in fact
through the convolution some in
discrete-time or the convolution
integral in continuous-time
you can generate the response to an
arbitrary input
let me just introduced a small amount
have
notation again reminding you
all her the convolution some in the
discrete-time case
which looks as i've indicated here this
summer
exit Khon minus K
will have the requirement to making such
frequent reference
to convolution dead it can be any and
to notation we represented as I have
here with an asterisk
and so X a van with the asterisk
a trip and means r denotes the
convolution affects a van with a chip
and
and correspondingly in the
continuous-time case
we have the convolution integral in
which
here is the third thing in to grow as we
talked about representing exit the
interns or itself hour as a linear
combination of the late impulses
and here we have the convolution
integral and again
will use the asterisk to denote
convolution
now there's a lot about convolution
that we want to talk about it their
properties of convolution which tell us
about properties
linear time-invariant systems also
it's important to focus on the mechanics
or implementing accomplish in in other
words understanding and generating some
fluency and insight
into what these particulars
some an integral expressions me
so let's first look at discrete-time
convolution
and examine more specifically what in
essence
some tells us to do in terms of
manipulating the sequences
so and returning to the
expression for the
convolutions Tom as I show here
some love exit K a true then minus
K let's focused in on an example
where we choose active and as a unit
step and a chip and as Arial exponential
times the unit step so with the quick
fix a van
is as they indicate here
sequence a true fan is an exponential
for positive time in zero for negative
time so we have active and in a tube and
but now let's look back at the equation
and
let me stress that what we want is not
excessive and nature then we want exit K
because we're going to some over K and
not a trip K
but a chip and minus K
so we have then from
expand its straightforward to generate
exit K at that
simply changing the index it's a nation
and what's a true then minus K well what
they two-minus K
H A minus K is huka flipped over
so hip this is white
8 UK looks like than
this is what a2 n my SK looks like
and in essence why it the operation of
convolution
or the mechanics of convolution tells us
to do
is to take the sequence HO
and minus K which is a check minus k
position with its origin and cake balls
and
and multiply this sequence by this
sequence
and some the product from K equals minus
infinity plus infinity
so if we were to compute for example
the output at an equal 0
as I positioned this sequence here this
is that an equal 0
I would take this and multiply it by
this and some
from minus infinity plus infinity or
for an equal one I would position it
here frank with two outs with position
it here at center
well you can kinda see what the idea is
let's look at this a little more
dynamically and see it
in fact how one sequence fly past the
other
and how the output why I have an build
up to
the correct answer
so the input they were considering is a
step input
which I show here and the impulse
response that we welcome all this with
is a decaying exponential now
to form the convolution we want the
product %uh exit K
not with a chip K but with a chip and
minus K
corresponding to taking a chief K and
reflecting at about the origin and then
shifting it appropriately
so here we see HR then minus K for an
equal to 0
namely H minus K and now a true
one minus K which will show next is this
shifted to the right by one point
here we have a 2-1 minus K
shifting to the right by one more point
is a trip to minus K
shifting again to the right will have
ages 3 minus K
and now let's shift back to the left
until and is negative and
then will begin the convolution so
here's an equal 0
any cause -1 any cause -2
and and it was minus-3 now to form the
convolution we want the product
exit k with a true then minus K song
from
minus infinity plus infinity and
for and negative that product is zero
and therefore the result the convolution
is zero
as we shift to the right will build up
the convolution
and the result the convolution will be
shown on the bottom trace
so we begin the process
with and negative and here we have any
calls -1
at n equals 0 we get our first 90
contribution
now as we ship further to the right
corresponding to increasing N
we will accumulate more and more
turns in the psalm and the convolution
will build up in particular for this
example
the result to the convolution increases
monotonically
asymptotically approaching a constant
and that constant in fact
is just simply the accumulation love
the values under the exponential
now let's carry out the convolution this
time with an input which is a
rectangular pulses that have a step
input
again the same impulse response namely
the King exponential
and so we want to begin with HR then
minus K
again with and negative shown here and
again with any negative
there are no 90 turns in the product
and so the convolution for and negative
will be zero as it was in the previous
case
again on the bottom trace will show the
result of the convolution as the impulse
response
slides along at any cost 0 we get our
first 90 term
and as in increases passed
0 we will begin to generate an output
basically the same as the output that we
generated with a step input
until the impulse response
reaches a point where as we slide
further
we slide outside the interval where the
rectangle is non-zero
so when we slide one point further from
what shown here
the output will now DK
corresponding to the fact dead the
impulse responses sliding outside
the interval in which the input is
non-zero
and so on the bottom trace we now see
the result that the convolution
okay so what
you've seen then is an example
love discrete-time convolution let's now
look at an example love continuous-time
convolution
and as you might expect continuous-time
convolution operates in
exactly the same way continuous-time
convolution
we have be expression again
y'at is an integral with
now except now NHL t minus
now it had exactly the same kinda
perform
as we had previously for
discrete-time convolution and and in
fact the mechanics
0 the continuous-time convolution are
identical
so here Misar example with X 50 equal to
unity
step and 850 now a real exponential time
two units that I show
here x50 which is the unit step function
here we have a gypsy
which is an exponential for positive
time
and 0 for negative time now
again looking back at the expression
work on pollution it's not accept either
we want
its except now that we want and it's not
H all tea or a chip how that we want it
minus now we plan to multiply these
together
and integrate over the variable town
and that gives us the output at any
given time
if we wanted at another time we change
the value
the as an argument inside this integral
so here we have exit T
here we have a trip to you which isn't
quite what we wanted
here we have except now and that's fine
its just
X-eighty with T relabel this panel and
now
what is 850 minus can now
well here's a chip panel
and if we simply turn that over
here is 850 -10 and a trip T-minus now
is position then at now
equal to P and as we change the value to
the
to change the position this signal and
now we multiply
these two together and integrate from
minus infinity Department Kennedy
whip 850 minus now positioned at the
appropriate value with T
well
again its best really to see this
example and get the notion
love seek signal being flipped and the
to think not flying past each other
multiplying in integrating by
looking at it dynamically and observing
how the answer build-up
again the input that
we consider is a step input and again we
use an impulse response
which is a decaying exponential and
to form the convolution we want the
product
love accept an hour not with a chipped
out but with a chip T-minus
now so we want HFT time reversed
and then shifted appropriately depending
on the value with T
let's first just look at age 50 -10 now
for T positive corresponding to shifting
a chip -10 now to the right and here we
have
TV increasing here
is TV decreasing and we
we want to begin the convolution with T
negative
corresponding to shifting H A minus
towel
to the left now to form the convolution
we want the product if these two
and pretty negative there are no 90
contributions to the integral
and so the convolution will be 0 party
less than zero
and the bottom trace we show the results
of the convolution
here for T negative
and pretty less than zero we will
continue to have zero in the convolution
now as TV increases past
0 we begin to get some 90 contribution
in the product indicated by the fact
that the convolution
the result to the convolution starts to
build-up
and as see increases further
we will get more and more 90
contribution
in the in a grand and so
the resulted the convolution will be
a monotonically increasing function for
this particular example
which asymptotically approaches a
constant
and that constant will be proportional
to the area under the impulse response
because that the fact that work
involving
with the step input
now let's carry out the convolution with
an input which is
a rectangular Paul's again an impulse
response which is an exponential
and so to form the convolution we want
except now with a2
T-minus towel H A T minus now shown here
for TE
negative and again to form the
convolution we take
the integral all the product if these
two
which again will be 0 for
T less than zero so the bottom trace
shows the result of the convolution
here shown is zero and it will continue
to be 0
until T becomes positive at which point
we build up
some 90 turn
in the in a grant now as we slide
further
until the impulse response
shifts outside the interval in which the
polls
is 90 the output will build up
but here we've now begun to leave that
interval
and so the output will start to BK
exponentially
and as the impulse response
slides further and further corresponding
to
increasing see then the output
will DK exponentially representing the
fact
that their is less and less area
in the product love except now
and a chief T-minus now and
asymptotically
this output will then approach 0 okay so
you've seen convolution a you see the
derivation of convolution and kinda the
graphical
representation convolution finally
let's work again with these two examples
and let's go through those two examples
analytically
so that we finally see how analytically
the result develops for those same
examples
well we have
first the discrete-time case and let's
take our discrete-time example
and and in general the convolution some
is as I indicated here so yes
is just our expression from before which
is
the convolution some and if we take our
two examples
the example love and it put which is
unit step and an impulse response
which is a real exponential multiplied
by a unit step
we have then
replacing exit K by
what we know the input to be an HR then
minus K
by what we know the impulse response to
be the output is
the expression that we have here now
in this expression and you'll see this
of very generally and with the more
complicated examples
when you look at the tax as
you go to evaluate these expressions
generally what happens is that the
signals have different analytical
forms in different regions and that's a
fact
what we have here your particular let's
look at the thumb and well we observed
first the ball
is that the
limits on this song are going to be
modified
depending on where this unit step
is zero and non-zero in particular
if we first consider what will turn out
to be the simple case
namely and less than zero for and less
than zero
this unit step is
0 for K
greater than an and with an less than
zero
that means that this unit step never
is 90 for K
positive on the other hand
this unit step is never 90
or is always 0 for k negative
let me just stressed that by looking at
the particular grabs
here is the unit step you FK
here is the units that you then minus K
and for and less than zero so that this
point comes before this point
the product these two is equal to 0
that means there is no overlap between
these two terms
and so it says that why I have an
the output is 0 for and less than 0
well that was an easy one a her
bring greater than 0 it's not quite a
straightforward
as coming out with the answers 0 so now
let's look at what happens when the two
units steps overlap
and this would correspond to
what i've labeled here as interval to
namely for and greater than 0
if we just look back at the
summation that we had the summation now
corresponds to this unit step
and this unit step having some overlap
so for interval to
corresponding to an greater than 0 we
have
you have K the unit step
we have you love and minus K
which is a unit step going backward in
time
by which extends
for positive values have an
if we think about multiplying these two
together
we will get in the product unity
for what values at K well
for K starting at zero corresponding to
one of the units steps
ending at hand corresponding to the
other units that
so we have an overlap between these
for k equal to 0 et cetera
up through the value and
right now that means that in terms of
the original some
we can get rid of the units steps
involved by simply changing the limits
on the some
and the limits now are from zero
to an the term
out for to the end minus K
we had before you with Cain you then
minus K and that disappeared because
because we don't with that simply by
modifying the limits
we now pull out the term output to the N
because the summation is on canine and
so we can
simply poll that term
out at the some
and we now have out but the minus K
which we can write rewrite as alpha to
the minus 12 PK
and the upshot of all of this is that
why I have an
now we can really express as output to
the end
its own from 0 to end up outfit to the
-1
to the K well question is how do we
evaluate that and
it's essentially corresponds to a finite
number
turns in a geometric series and that bio
by the way is estimation that will recur
over and over and over and over again
and it's one that you should right down
right on your back pocket right in the
palm of your hand
or whatever it takes to remember it what
you'll see is that that will recur
can more or less the throughout the
course
and so it's one worth remembering and in
particular
what the storm love a geometric
series is is what i've indicated here
we have this song from 0 to our they did
to the K
and it's one minus beta to the are plus
one
this is one more than the
upper limit on the summation and in the
denominator is one minus beta
so this equation is important
is no point in attempting to derive it
however you get to it it's important
to retain okay well
we can now use that some Asian
in the expression that we just the
ballot
and so let's proceed to a value a tax on
clothes
form so we now know go back
to the expression that we just worked
out
why event is output to the end its own
from 0 to N
output to the -1 to the K
this plays the role a beta in a turn
that I just
in the expression and I just presented
and so using
bat using that result we can rewrite
this summation as i indicate here
and the final result that we end up with
after a certain amount of algebra is
why I have an equal to one minus output
to the end plus one
divided by one minus out for
and let me just kinda vindicate with a
few dots here
dead there is a certain amount of
algebra required in going from
this step to this step and
and I I'd like to leave you with the
phone an opportunity you doing at your
leisure
okay well so so the expression we have
now
for wired and is why I have an
equal to one myself up to be enforced
one divided by one minus now for
that bring greater than 0 we found out
previously that it was 0 for and less
than 0
and finally if we were to plot this what
we would
get is the graph that I indicate here
the first non-zero value occurs at an
equal 0
and it has a height 1 and then
the next 90 value at one and this has a
height
a one plus alpha and this is one place
now for
on South squared and and
the sequence continues on like that
an asymptotically approaches as n goes
to infinity
asymptotically approaches one over one
minute South for
which is consistent with the algebraic
expression
that we have that we develop and
obviously of course
is also consistent with the movie
alright so that's our
discrete-time example which we kinda
went through graphically
with the transparencies and we went
through graphically with the movie you
know we've gone through analytically
now let's look analytically at
the continuous-time example which pretty
much
close in the same way as we've just gone
through
so again we have
the convolution integral which is
the integral indicated at the top
and our example you recall was with
accepting as a unit step
and a trip to the as
an exponential times the units that so
when we substitute those then this then
corresponds to
exit to the and this corresponds to 850
-10 now
and again we have the same
issue more last which is that inside
that integral
there are two steps one of them going
forward in time and one of them going
backward in time and we need to examine
when they overlap in when they don't
when they don't overlap the product of
course is zero
and there's no point doing any
integration because the anagram 20
so if we track it through we have again
interval one which is to us$10,000
pretty less than zero this unit step
which only begins at: equals 0
a tally cool 0 and this unit step
which is zero by the time
how gets up to TN beyond party less than
zero
is no overlap between
the unit step going forward in time
and the units that going backward in
time and consequently
the in a grand is equal to 0 and
consequently
the output is equal to 0 okay
now we can
likewise looked at the interval where
the to unit steps to overlap and in that
case what happens again is that the
overlap
in essence the units that tells us gives
us a range
on the integration and in particular
the two-step overlap 20 is greater than
from how equal 0
two towers both T so
critical to party greater than 0
again of course we have in this
expression
this product love this unit step
and this unit step is equal to 1
in this rain
and so that allows us then
to change the limits on the integral
mister from minus infinity two plus
infinity
we know that the in a grand is non-zero
only over this range
looking at this in to grow we can now
pull out the term which corresponds to
you need to the -80 just as we pulled
out
a term in the discrete-time case
and we noticed in the integral we have
eat to the
-8 -10 now so that gives us the integral
from 0 to TV to the eight-hour
and if we perform at integration
we end up with this expression
and finally multiplying this by either
the -80
we have for y'at pretty greater than 0
the algebraic expression that I
indicated on the bottom
so so we had worked out
to less than zero and we come out 10
we work out take greater than 0 and we
come out
with this algebraic expression
and if we plot this out to rate
expression as a function of time
we find that what it corresponds to is
an exponential behavior starting at zero
and exponentially heading asymptotically
forward the bad you one over it
okay now we've gone through these
examples several ways than one is
analytically
in order to develop a feel and fluency
for convolution
it's absolutely essential to work
through a variety of examples
both understanding them graphically and
understanding them as we did hear
analytically and you'll have an
opportunity to do that
through the problems that I suggested in
the video course manual
in the next lecture what will turn to
are some general properties of
convolution
and show how this rather amazing
representation
when your time invariant systems in fact
leads to a variety
%uh properties linear time-invariant
systems
and will find that convolution its
fairly rich in its properties and what
this leads to
are some very nice and
desirable and exploitable properties
linear time-invariant systems thank you