the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home the
the
in
the new the in this lecture we
begin a discussion of the topic
modulation
which is among other things a very
important
topic in practical terms for example it
forms the cornerstone for many
communication systems
and also as we'll see as these lectures
go along
a particular for modulation referred to
as poss amplitude modulation and
eventually
impulse modulation or impose train
modulation
forms a very important bridge between
continuous-time signals in discrete-time
signals
now in general terms
what we mean when we refer to modulation
is the notion
%uh using one signal to very
a parameter up another signal for
example
a sinusoidal signal has three parameters
amplitude frequency and phase and we
could think for example
love using one signal
to very let's say the airport to up a
sinusoidal signal
and what that leads to is an ocean which
will develop in some detail
referred to as sinusoidal amplitude
modulation
and would correspond to a
sinusoidal signal refer to as the
carrier
and its amplitude being buried on the
basis
love another signal now
alternatively we could think all burying
either the
frequency or the phase a sinusoidal
signal
again with another signal and with that
leads to is another very important
notion
which is referred to as sinusoidal
frequency modulation where essentially
it's the frequency up a sinusoid that's
changing
depending on the signal that we're using
to modulate this sinusoid now
sign a soil amplitude frequency and
phase modulation
are extremely important topics and ideas
in the context ok communication systems
what are the reasons is dead if you want
to transmit a signal let's say for
example a voice signal
the voice signal that you're listening
to now if you try to transmit that over
long distances because the frequencies
involved
the medium that you use to transmitted
won't carry it long distances the idea
then
is to essentially take that signal like
a voice signal
use it to modulate a much higher
frequency signal
and then transmit that higher frequency
signal
over a medium dead essentially can
support
long-distance transmission at those
frequencies then at the other end of
course
the voice information or whatever else
the information is
is taken off now also
a notion that that leads to an will be
developing in
some detail is kind of the idea that in
fact
you can simultaneously transmit more
than one signal
by in essence taking several voice
signals or other signals
using them to modulate either the
frequency or amplitude
love sinusoidal signals at different
frequencies
ending all those together that's a
process called multiplexing
and then at the other end the
transmission system
taking those sinusoidal signals apart
and then
extracting the envelope or frequency
modulation information
to get back to the voice signal or other
information carrying signal
so that's one of the very important ways
in which
modulation is used sinusoidal modulation
is used in communication systems
and and white will see as
in particular as we go through today's
lecture
is there'd amplitude modulation
sinusoidal amplitude modulation
in fact follows in a fairly
straightforward way
from the properties of the four EA
transform
that we've developed in summer the
earlier lectures
so our focus on in today's lecture
will be on sinusoidal amplitude
modulation
in continuous-time in the next lecture
will
consider the same set of notions related
to discrete-time
and also a concept referred to as poss
amplitude modulation
and all of these follow very in a very
straightforward way from the modulation
property for the 48 transform
issues of frequency and phase modulation
are
a little more difficult to analyze but
in fact many have
the techniques that we've developed in
the previous lectures
also provide important insights into
frequency phase modulation
summer this is develop in more detail
in the book so what I'd like to do
is focus for now on the concept
love amplitude modulation
and in as i indicated
there are several kinds love carrier
signals
on which the modulation can be
superimposed
the basic structure for an amplitude
modulation system
is one in which there is the modulating
signal let's say for example Voice
and a carrier signal what's referred to
as the carrier
and then of course the resulting output
is the modulated output
now to analyze this since we have
multiplication in the time domain
we know from the property the 48
transform
that we've developed previously the
modulation property
dead multiplication in the time domain
corresponds to
convolution in the frequency domain and
it's this basic property or equation
dead lets us analyzed in some detail in
fact
the notions of amplitude modulation
as we go through this lecture and the
next lecture
we'll be talking as i indicated about
several different types
carrier signals one is
what's referred to as poss carriers and
that leads to
among other things the concept the pulse
amplitude modulation
that will be deferred until the next
lecture
in today's lecture what I'll focus on is
first the case of a complex exponential
carrier
second the case of a sinusoidal carrier
and in fact in the complex exponential
carrier a sinusoidal carrier
are obviously very closely related since
the complex exponential carrier is in
effect
to sinusoidal carriers one
for the real part and one for the
imaginary part
so let's first begin a discussion love
amplitude modulation by considering a
complex exponential carrier
and then moving on to a discussion of a
sinusoidal carrier
so the issue then is dead
we have a signal
x50 it's multiplied by a carrier
and the carrier they were considering is
a carrier signal
see if the of the form
e2 the J Omega CT
plus status see thats the form
love our carrier signal and
what we can first analyze is what
the result things signal or spectrum is
at the output the modulator well we can
do that by
concentrating on the modulation property
and let's consider just are as a
serb general for respect from what i've
indicated here
for the 48 transform love
the input signal
or modulating signal exe phone maker and
so
this is intended to represent
the spectrum affect safety
and then the carrier signal since it's a
single complex exponential
has a $4 EA transform which is
an impulse in the frequency domain
and the airport to up the impulse is
to partay to the J status subsea
where we noticed that the complex
amplitude incorporates
the phase information so
now if we multiply in the time domain
week involving the frequency domain and
as you know
involving a signal with an impulse just
shifts that signal to the location of
the impulse
and so as a consequence and taken care
various
factors what we end up with is spectrum
then that is centered at the carrier
frequency
Omega subsea so
what this says is dead if we have a
signal
x50 and we
use it to modulate a complex exponential
carrier
in the frequency domain what we've
simply done is to take
the original spectrum and shifted in
frequency
to so that was originally at zero
frequency is now centered around the
carrier frequency
now we've now modulated in effect to a
higher frequency
things are happening at a higher
frequency band and
the next question is how do we do much
away or in other words
how do we get the original signal back
well of course one way that we can think
of doing it
particularly in the context love this
specific carrier if we look back at the
top equation
we have as the result in the modulation
X 50 time see if he were see if t is
this
and we could consider for example
just simply dividing the modulator
output by this
or equivalently taking the modulated
output
and multiplying by the to the
minus J Omega CT plus they to see
well let's track that through in terms
of the spectra
we have again the spectrum or
the output the modulator which is the
original spectrum shifted
up to the carrier frequency we have
below that the spectrum love
e2 the minus J Omega CT plus they to see
and if we now convolved this with this
that results in simply shifting this
spectrum except for
an issue the scale factor shifting this
spectrum
back down to the origin so can bombing
these two together
the spectrum that we end up with is that
so weekend track this through in the
frequency domain
in the frequency domain that says ship
the spectrum up
when you want the modulate ship the
spectrum back down
and alternatively we can look at
algebraically
in the time domain what it says is if
you multiply it by either the plush
chair make a CT
then when you want to get back multiply
by in the minus chair make a CT
now one question that I you could
conceivably be asking is
if we're talking about practical systems
and not
simply mathematics in fact
doesn't make sense in the real world to
consider
using a complex exponential carrier
and the answer to that in fact is
yes dead very often in practical systems
one considers
using a carrier which in fact is a
complex exponential
well a complex exponentials complex
there's a
square root of -1 in the air and you can
kinda basse-bolle how do we get a square
root of -1
and the answer is fairly simple let's
look again at the modulator which we
have here
and in effect with that says is we want
to multiply
a real-valued signal by you the chair
make a CT plus they to see
now we can equivalent Lee use oil as
relationship
to break this down into a cosine and
sine term
and so what that means interns have an
implementation equivalent Lee
is modulating x50
onto a cosine carrier
and that then gives us the real part
ald the complex output and modulating it
onto
a sinusoidal carrier these two being
ninety degrees out of phase
and that gives us the imaginary part
and so in effect this is the complex
signal
if we just simply think both hanging
attack on here that says square root of
-1 RJ
and we appropriately combined complex
signals
following the rules of complex
arithmetic and indeed that's exactly the
way things are done in the real world
a complex signal is simply a set love
to real signals and of course if we look
at the spectra
involved if we we have here the real
part and the imaginary part pov
the complex output if we
again refer back to the original
spectrum accessible maker
and the modulated spectrum
which I show down here the original
spectrum
shifted up to the carrier frequency
in effect we're building nests I dove
two lines
one-line representing the real part
love that and the real part in the time
domain corresponds to the even part in
the frequency domain
and so with the output of one of the
Cosi if the cosine modulator we have a
spectrum
that looks like this and
the output love the along the imaginary
branch
has a spectrum that looks like this
recalling the top branch that this
for positive frequencies is positive and
was positive here and so in effect when
you add them
this portion of the spectrum will cancel
out
so in effect what we're doing is
building
then the complex signal
in effect outta to real signals or we're
building this complex
the spectrum the complex signal I dove
separate lines the represent the
even and the art parts
okay now their
are lots of applications love amplitude
modulation
and we'll be seeing a number of these as
we go through the discussion
what I'd like to do in is just indicate
briefly
one now which is an application that
are in fact surface is fairly often in
the context
love a complex exponential carrier
and bad is the notion love using
modulation
to permit
the application %uh love
a very well designed and implemented
low-pass filter
to be used as a bandpass filter and in
fact as a set a bandpass filters
account here's the idea the idea is
if we have a fixed filter
work we have let's say we have a signal
and we want to thank
all a filter which we want to kinda move
along the signal
one way to do it is to somehow have
filters the move along the signal
the other possibility is to keep the
filter fix and let
the signal move in frequency in front of
the filter
let me that may be a little more
specific
suppose that we have a signal accept T
and in we modulated with a complex
exponential carrier
with the carrier frequency Omega see
and the output if that is then processed
with a low pass filter
and then we d modulate the result
then in fact what we've done is to take
the spectrum
or the input signal
shifted pullout what is now around low
frequencies
and then shift that part of the spectrum
back to where it belongs
so if we look at that interns
over actually tracking through the
spectra we would have
initially a spectrum for the original
signal
which I show at the top as excessive
Omega
after modulating or shifting that
spectrum
up to a center frequency Omega see
we then have what I indicate here and
the dotted line corresponds to
the passband the low-caste filter
well the results have low pass filtering
rejects
all the spectrum except the part around
low frequencies
and the next step is then 2d modulate
this and so in effect the modulating
will shift this spectrum back to where
it originally came from
and so that result will be what I
show in the final result
which is here and what we can say is
that
this in fact is equivalent
if we can look back at the top spectrum
this is equivalent to having extracted
with a bandpass filter a section out of
this part of the spectrum
so interns love tracking through the
spectrum and looking at
the equivalent filtering operation
then what we accomplished was
to pull out this part of the spectrum
using a low-pass filter and modulation
but acquittal atlee what we implemented
was
a bandpass filter as i indicate here
now of course a signal with this
spectrum since
this spectrum is not kind you get
symmetric we know that this signal does
not correspond to a real-valued signal
a quite lovely this filter doesn't
correspond to a filter whose impulse
response Israel
if in fact we add another step to this
which is to take the real part of the
output
then by taking the real part of the
output we would be taking the
even part of the spectrum associated
with that complex signal
and the acquittal with author that we
would end up with then
is the filter that I indicated the
bottom
which is a bandpass filter
now just two reiterate a point that I
made earlier
a question of course is why would you go
to this trouble why not just build a
bandpass filter
and one other reasons is that
its often much easier to build
affixed filter a filter with a fixed
center frequency for example a low-pass
filter
than it is to build the filter that has
variable compliments in it so that
when you bury them the filters center
frequency shifts around
now if you want to look at at the energy
and a signaling different frequency
bands
then you'd like to look at it through
different filters
and so kind of the idea here which is
really the basis for many spectrum
analyzers
is to build a really good quality
low-pass filter
and then use modulation which is often
easier to implement use modulation
to shift the signal essentially in front
of the wind
in front of the filter
okay well so we've can work their way
through
modulation with a complex exponential
carrier
and what we saw
among other things with a complex
exponential carrier
is that in fact what a car sponse to
is to
branches one being modulation
with a cosine and the other modulation
with the sign
and so in fact in the real world weren't
there in a practical system
modulation the complex exponential
carrier really would be accomplished
with modulation with the sinusoidal
carrier
and in particular with sinusoidal
carriers
that are in quadrature as its referred
to or
covertly ninety degrees out of phase
okay well you in fact
sinusoidal modulation in other words
modulation using only a sinusoidal
carrier
very often is used in its own right
not only for for generating a complex
exponential carrier
but in fact as a carrier by itself
well let's looking at what the
consequences
love modulation with a sinus or to carry
or R and a particular
work through again what the specter are
and how we get the original signal back
again
soul in we are talking then about a
carrier signal
which is simply a sinusoidal signal
with some phase and of course we can
right that as the some love too complex
exponential
signals and so in effect now
when we apply the modulation property we
have the original spectrum
which a show here accessible maker
and that's convolved with the spectrum
love the carrier
and the spectrum of the carrier in this
case
is two impulses one at
plus Omega see and one at minus Omega
see
and the amplitudes if these incorporate
the phase
and later on in the lectured and
and to and subsequent lectures all
have a tendency to drop that they
deserve see just
to keep the notation an algebra little
cleaner but
for now I've incorporated and so now
when we apply the modulation property
what
we will do is convolved this spectrum
with this spectrum and the result of
course
is that the spectrum of the original
signal
gets replicated at both Omega since the
and at minus Omega subsea and
the resulting spectrum at the output to
the modulator then
is the spectrum that I show here
okay well now the question of course is
see now what's happened is there with a
sinus or carrier we've moved
the spectrum to both plus i'll make a CD
and minus Omega see
and now if we want to get the original
signal back again
well we would like to do somehow is move
that spectrum back down
to the origin now in the case for
complex exponential
that was easy to do which shifted one of
which is shifted back down
let's see what happens if in fact we
attempt 2d modulate
by again multiplying by the same
sinusoidal carrier
so let's examine what happens if
we now take
are modulated signal
and again modulated
onto the same sinusoidal carrier
to generate the output WT if we look at
the spectra
we have then the
modulated spectrum which we had
initially
and we now want to convey all that again
with the spectrum
or the carrier signal the specter the
carrier signal
I indicate here and if you tracked
through the convolution which is fairly
straightforward
then in fact what happens as you can
follow this with this
is you end up with
a composite spectrum which
is what i've indicated on the bottom
curve and has
in effect the spectrum of the original
single exit see
replicated in three places one
is at -2 Omega subsea
one is around the origin and wanna
shifted up to
twice the carrier frequency well
it's this piece that we want if we could
eliminate everything else
and keep this then that would in fact
correspond to the spectrum
love the signal dead the original signal
exit T
how do we do that well we know how
to eliminate part of the spectrum and
keep another part of the spectrum that's
called filtering so in fact what we
would do
is put the result if this
through a low-pass filter low-pass
filter route would retain the part of
the spectrum
around DC and eliminate the
remaining part of the spectrum so we
would keep this part
and eliminate the part of the spectrum
that we have over here
and let me just draw your attention to
the fact that because of the way the
algebra works out
the amplitude love this replication the
spectrum is half with the original
spectrum was and that means dead
ideally to keep scale factors correct we
would choose the amplitude this
to be to to scale this
backup 21 okay so
what we have is the modulator and
demodulator
and just to summarize
for the case Ave sinusoidal
carrier as opposed to a complex
exponential carrier
the modulator is just as it is in the
complex exponential case
its multiplication with the sinusoidal
carrier
with frequency Omega see if a status
see in the d modulator
in the D modulator we would take the
modulated signal
modulated again with the same carrier
signal and as we'll see later
it's important to keep the same face
relationship
this result is now not yet quite
that the modulated signal we need to
process that
with a low-pass filter that extracts the
part of the spectrum
around DC and throws away the upper part
of the spectrum the case generated in
the second modulation process and the
resulting output
is the original signal
accept T right now
what we've done is we've taken X 50
we've
modulated it onto a carrier and then
we've taken a modulated signal and we
figured out how to get back except Ian
of course
one Caswell if you start with exiting
you want to get X thirty back again
white by the going through all that why
not just use exit see the beginning at
the end and obviously
their are lots of reasons as i indicated
before
and just two reiterate what they are
the notion of an is that what you'd like
to do
is shift the signal into a different
frequency band
for transmission over some medium day
is more match to that frequency band
then the frequency range the original
signal also
as I alluded to there's the notion that
you can take lotsa signals
and transmit them simultaneously over
one
channel whether the channels a wire a
mic wave like a satellite link or
whatever
again using the idea of modulation
and what that process is referred to
as is multiplexing and let me just
quickly indicate what
that multiplexing process corresponds to
we could think for example love taking
the taking one signal
and modulating it on to one carrier
with one carrier frequency taking
a second signal modulating it onto a
different carrier frequency
taking a third signal and modulating it
onto a third carrier frequency et cetera
and if we choose these carrier
frequencies
appropriately then in fact weekend and
all those together
and do it in such a way that the specter
don't overlap
an end up with one broader band signal
that incorporates the information
simultaneously in all of those
signals so just to illustrate that in
the frequency domain
what we have let's say RR three spectra
xaxa
the Annex E and we would for example
take
this spectrum and modulated
to a carrier frequency Omega sed est
we can take this spectrum and modulate
it to a carrier frequency Omega sabi
where Omega sabi is chosen so that
when we and these two together they
don't overlap
so that they can eventually be separated
out and then of course we can do the
same thing
with the third signal and put that in a
frequency range over here
be careful that none of those overlap
and lonely and all those together the
composite spectrum
is what I show here and
as you can see essentially
by doing appropriate bandpass filtering
we can pull at whatever part of the
spectrum we choose to
and then d modulate that in the
appropriate way
of course we can do this not just with
three signals but perhaps with
tens or hundreds of signals so that's a
process
dead is typically referred to as
multiplexing and as i've described here
it's referred to as frequency division
multiplexing
that is dividing the frequency band into
cells and plucking
different signals into each one of those
and in so if we want now to recover one
of those channels
in a frequency division multiplexing
system
as i indicated we would first d
multiplex
the multiplexing corresponding to
pulling out
the appropriate channel with a bandpass
filter
and after D multiplexing we would then
d modulate and we would be modulated
with the carrier appropriate to the
channel that we've pulled out
and the the modulation of course
involves multiplying by the carrier and
doing appropriate
low-pass filtering to finally get the
signal back
and frequency division multiplexing
is one of those things that is
are its it's a fact which uses the
typeof multiplexing issues for example
in typical broadcast a.m.
radio systems where all the channels are
superimposed
together and it's your home radio
receiver that does the appropriate the
multiplexing in the modulating
and of course you can see that not only
is modulation an important part
of that but as I alluded to in the last
lecture filtering
also becomes an important part love
these practical systems
okay now the kinda amplitude modulation
that i've talked about so far
is what's referred to as
synchronous modulation and
the reason for the term synchronous is
dead in fact
what's implied in the system's
is a synchronization between
the transmitter and receiver in
particular
in the system as we've talked about it
the modulator
and the D modulator
have a synchronization in
both frequency and phase the face here
is indicated status if C
and if we take a look at the D modulator
the the modulator has a
phase love status subsea
and in general
there's the issue love whether we cannot
maintain that synchronization between
the modulator and demodulator
and so what we want to examine now
more generally is what the consequences
might be
and the solution to the resulting
problems
if in fact we don't have synchronization
between the modulator and demodulator
synchronization in terms of phase and
they're also by the way is another
problem which is the issue
synchronization
in frequency thats examine more in
the text and one of focus on here is
just the issue synchronization it face
to give you some sense of
what the issue is okay well
so now what we want to look at is what
happens if we have a modulator
with face status at sea
and it D modulator where the phase
instead if a is
said being status if C is some other
phase
the subsea and if you tracked through
the details and the algebra
then what you'll find is dead in fact
the output love the low-pass filter
rather than being XFT the signal that we
want
is X if T multiplied by a scale factor
and the scale factor is the cosigner the
phase difference
now one can ask okay well what's the big
deal about
a scale factor if it's too small will
make it bigger purse to be will make it
small
but there's several points 1 is notice
for example that if the phase difference
between
much later and the modulator is 90
degrees
then in fact the output at the modulator
or if it isn't quite ninety degrees the
amplitude might be small
and the implication would be a that if
there's other noise that gets injected
in the system
the signal to noise ratio is very low
now even worse
is the issue that if
in fact there's a phase difference but
the exact phase differences and
maintained
so that the modulator and demodulator
kinda fade in and out of phase
then in fact the output at the modulator
is x50 multiplied
by a time-varying fading term which is
the cosigner the phase difference
well what that means essentially is dead
if you use this kind of system to do
that the modulation
then in fact what you need to be careful
about is
maintaining synchronization in phase and
also is it turns out a frequency between
the modulator and demodulator
now there are alternatives to this
and the alternative is what's referred
to as
a synchronous the modulation and
let me indicate what the idea behind a
synchronous
the modulation is
now recall the what we've done in
amplitude modulation
is to take the carrier signal and very
its ample to
with the signal that eventually we want
to get back
so if we look at the amplitude modulated
waveform it might
typically look as i indicated here
and what we're trying to get back is
we're trying to get back
the envelope well one could imagine
building a circuit or designing a device
which in some sense will
tracked the envelope and in fact a
common circuit to do that is a fairly
simple
circuit consisting love a diode
and a resistor and capacitor in parallel
kinda the idea being that the capacitor
charges up
as this way for moves up to its p
and then as the way for drops down the
capacitor discharges through the
resistor and
it kinda tracks the envelope in fact the
kinda output
that we would get is the type of
behavior that
i've indicated here and in fact than
that is
a type all the modulation it
it's the modulation that doesn't require
synchronization between
the modulator and demodulator and
it's fairly inexpensive to build
but it has obviously some
trade-offs associated with it well
to can indicate where the trade-off
comes from or where the issue surfaces
notice the what we're doing is tracking
the envelope with the sinusoidal signal
and we're calling mad or we're suing the
back is our regional
signal exit T
well suppose that XFT
the original signal is sometimes
positive and sometimes negative
what might we see as we look
at the output out the modulator well the
output at the modulator would've course
follow the envelope down and
then it would follow the envelope back
up again
in other words what would tend to
generate is
a full-wave rectified version all the
signal that you were really trying to
get back
now there's a simple solution to this
the simple solution
is to make sure that the signal
that is the modulating signal XFT
never goes negative so if it happens to
voice signal happens tends to go
negative that happens to
we can simply at a constant to it and
and a
watchin of constant so that it always
stays positive
well let's look at that in the
what we want to do then if we're
considering a synchronous the modulation
is to take our original signal x50
and and to it a constant
where the constant is made large enough
so they were sure
that this is a positive signal
and it's a really let me just draw your
attention to the fact that I'm now
suppressing
the phase on the carrier signal since
the phase is not important to the
argument and it's just some additional
notation to carry around
now so the the idea then is an a
constant exit see
notice that if we just take this term
and expanded out into two terms
accept a cosigner Omega CT plus eight
times cosine Omega CT
then in block diagram terms we can we
can represent that as i've shown here
and so it would correspond to modulating
the signal
accept T onto the carrier Omega some CT
and also injecting some carrier
with an amplitude a and the output at
the modulator is then the summer those
two
and the tech depending on exactly what
this value a is
will influence what the envelope a look
like
and I indicate below to possibilities
one is where I'd made a fairly large
and one is where I've made a
significantly smaller
and their are both positive and negative
issues associated with whether a is too
large a raise too small
for example if a is small
in relation to the amplitude
love the signal then %uh rather pay is
large in relation to the airport to the
signal
then this envelope tends to be very flat
and it tends to be easy to track it with
that simple diode RC circuit
as compared with the case down here
on the other hand their is a price that
you pay
for this kind event below and the price
that you pay is perhaps best seen in the
frequency domain
if we look in the frequency domain here
is our original spectrum
here is the spectrum at the output
%uh the modulator and the impulse that
occurs here
corresponds to the carrier this injected
the larger a is the more carrier is
injected
the more carrier thats injected
the easier it is for the envelope
detector
2d modulate so
one can ask well why not just put a lot
in well
the obvious answer is dead
it's not and information carrying part
but the signal
and so in some sense it represents
inefficiency in transmission because
what you're transmitting is power energy
that doesn't have any information
associated with it is simply the
injection of a carrier
to make d modulation for a
an AC Christie modulator the modulator
to make
the the modulation easier
and so there's this trade off and in
fact one
kinda represents the trade-off and the
Pratt Associated primers very often
returns a percent modulation
where the percent modulation is
a the essentially the ratio the maximum
signal level
to the amplitude love the injected
carrier
and depending on whether
the modulations very high or very low
the trade-off
is dead the transmission is more
efficient and it takes more energy but
the modulator is simpler
or the modulators more complicated but
the transmission is simply now there are
situations where you might very well
want to use one or the other for example
in home radio your
of unwilling to transmit a lot of power
so that you can have inexpensive
consumer-oriented receivers
on the other hand in satellite
communication you willing
to pay a very high price for the
modulators and D modulators
but its the amount of power that's
transmitted
that's at a premium and so in one case
satellite communication you use
synchronous modulation and demodulation
where isn't typical consumer-oriented
broadcasting
you would use a sink in a synchronous
system and
Jenna and transmit more power even
transfer more power even if it's
inefficient so that the D modulator
can be simply now
in a synchronous system then as we've
indicated there's one source of
inefficiency which
is this injection at the Carrier there
also
is a somewhat different issue
related to inefficiency in sinusoidal
amplitude modulation
and its inefficiency that is
separate from the issue synchronous
first is a synchronous systems in other
words it's not associated with
the injection of the carrier its a very
different issue
let me indicate what that is let's look
again
in at the spectrum love
X 50 which i've indicated here
and in a sinusoidal amplitude modulation
system
we would shift this to
are centered around plus and minus the
carrier frequency
now notice there in the original system
we
occupier frequency spectrum thats two
times Omega Savannah M
by the time we've shifted it we've used
up
thinking a positive and negative
frequencies we've used up
twice as much all the frequency spectrum
well you could say okay let's let's just
shift this up this way and
get rid of this part that's of course
what the complex exponential carrier did
and the issue there really is that now
you've got to transmit both the real
part an imaginary part
so what you can think about and ask is
if you still want to transmit a
real-valued signal
happen you somehow remove the
inefficiency or redundancy in the
spectrum
well notice that what we have is
this spectrum moved here and moved here
and we could imagine building a
real-valued signal by
eliminating what I refer to here as the
lower sideband
I have the positive frequencies and the
otto's the negative frequencies
and in effect what we've done is taken
just the positive frequencies here
shifted them there
the negative frequencies here and
shifted them here and the resulting
spectrum
is what I indicate below
well this in fact is what is often done
and what is referred to as is single
sideband
what we've done is we've kept the upper
in this particular case we could
alternatively by the way
think love putting this system together
where we retain the lower
sideband instead of the upper sideband
and in either case well we removed is
and inefficiency in transmission at the
signal
namely we have a real value signal but
it only requires as much
total band with the terms thereof the
frequencies that I
that in which there's energy president
as
the original sick well how do we do this
there are a variety of ways
in and there's one procedure that is
discussed in more detail in the text
which uses was referred to as a
90-degree face splitter
the simplest way at least conceptually
is to think about doing it with
filtering and the idea simply
is dead if we have are modulated signal
here's the spektr on the modulated
signal and if that modulated signal is
simply put through
a high pass filter than the result
will be to eliminate
the lower sideband if we choose the
high-pass filter
to have a characteristic as I indicate
here
so this course conceptually is a very
sharp cutoff filter
and what it eliminates are the lower
side bands and the resulting spectrum
is what we have below
and this in fact is really kind of the
basic idea
behind single sideband transmission
again there's a trade-off it's clearly
more efficient
then double sideband transmission
but also has the complication
or additional issue dead the modulator
becomes a little more complicated
because you need
this filtering operation or some
equivalent operation to get rid of the
unwanted side
okay well this is a fairly quick
tour through a variety of issues related
to modulation
and it really is just the tip of the
iceberg obviously
modulation in the context so sinusoidal
modulation as we talked about has
in fact the lotto detailed issues
associated with it
it's important to recognize day at
and to be somewhat pleased by the fact
dead
not only with the mathematical
foundations that we've developed
can we understand the basics of
sinusoidal amplitude modulation but in
fact
what you'll find issue if you
dig into this somewhat deeper that the
basic background that we've built up so
far
the mathematical tools are really
pretty much what you need for a much
deeper understanding
love all the issues involved
so from a what might have seemed like a
fairly abstract mathematical property
associated with the Fourier transform
we've begun
to develop what should give you the
sense that some
important practical considerations
and as we'll see in the next lecture
very much the same kinds of notions
apply a
for discrete-time sinus oil on complex
exponential
amplitude modulation and also as i
indicated at the beginning at the
lecture
in the next lecture will also talk about
what's referred to as possible to
modulation it's a different kind of
carrier
and what that will lead to among other
things
is a very important bridge
between the notions of continuous-time
and the notions of discrete-time thank
you