the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from 100 to them IT courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT ided you
home
the
in
the new
are
for
over the last several lectures we've
dealt with the representation
of linear time-invariant systems through
convolution
and just to remind you over basic
strategy
essentially the idea was to
exploit the notion of when the arity by
decomposing the input into summer basic
inputs
and then using when the arity to tell us
that the output can be represented as
the corresponding linear combination of
the Associated outputs
so if we have a linear system
either continuous-time and discrete-time
for example with continuous time
if the input is decomposed as a linear
combination
a basic inputs with each of these basic
inputs
generating an Associated output and if
the system is linear
then the output love the system
is the same linear combination love The
Associated outputs
and the same statement is identical
both for continuous-time in
discrete-time so
the strategy is to decompose the input
into these basic inputs
and the imports
were chosen also with some particular
strategy in mind in particular for both
continuous-time
for discrete-time in this representation
the
basic inputs used in the decomposition
are chosen first the ball so that
a broad class signals can be represented
interns are these basic inputs and
second of all
so that the response to these basic
inputs
is in some sense easy to compute now
in the representation which latest
to convolution the particular choice
that we made
in the discrete-time case for our basic
inputs
was a decomposition up the input interns
or delayed impulses and
The Associated outputs that that
generated
were delayed versions of the impulse
response
decomposing the input into a linear
combination of these
the output into the corresponding linear
then led to the convolution some in
the discrete-time case and
in the continuous-time case a similar
kinda decomposition in terms of impulses
and Associated representation
love the output in terms of the impulse
response
led to the convolution in ago now
in this lecture and for number the
succeeding lectures
will want to turn our attention to a
very different
said the basic building blocks and
in particular the signals there
will be using as the building blocks for
or more general signals
rather than impulses as we've dealt with
before
will be in general complex exponentials
so in a general sense
in the continuous-time case and will be
thinking in terms of a decomposition
afar signals as a linear combination
I'll
complex exponentials continuous-time
or in the discrete-time case
complex exponentials where sees the case
complex here
in discrete-time and s2 K's complex here
in continuous-time now
the basic strategy of course requires
dead we choose a settlement puts basic
building blocks
which have two properties one is that
the system response be straightforward
to compute were in some sense easy to
compute
and the second is that it be a fairly
general said a building blocks
so that we can build lots of signals I
love them
what will find with complex exponentials
either continuous-time and discrete-time
is that they very nicely have those two
properties
in particular the notion that the
output over linear time-invariant system
is easy to compute
is tied to what's referred to as the eye
can function property
a complex exponentials which will focus
on
shortly in a little more detail
and second of all the fact that
weekend in fact represent very broad
classes have signals as linear
combinations
these will be a topic an issue
that will develop in detail over in fact
are the next
set of lectures this lecture and the
next set of lectures
now in in doing this although
we could in fact begin with our
attention focused
on in general complex exponentials
what will choose to do his first focus
on the case in which
the exponent in the continuous-time
cases
purely imaginary as i indicate here
and in the discrete-time case where
the magnitude of the complex number Z CK
is equal to 1 so what that corresponds
to in the continuous-time case
is said building blocks
the form you DJ Omega sed Katie
and in the discrete-time case said a
building blocks
the for eat a DJ Omega KN
well we'll see is a representation in
these Terms
leads to what's for two as for EA
analysis and that's what we'll be
dealing with over the next several
lectures
will then be exploiting this
representation actually
through most the course and then toward
the end of the course will returned to
generalizing
the for a representation to the
discussion over plus transforms the
transforms
so for now we want to restrict ourselves
to
complex exponentials a particular form
in
and in fact also initially to
continuous-time
signals and systems so let's begin
with the continuous-time case the
complex exponentials that we want to
deal with
in and focus first the ball on what I
refer to as
the eigenfunction property love this
particular set a building blocks
we're talking about
basic signals the form either the J
Omega some Katy
and this statement is there
for a linear time-invariant system the
response to one of these
is 0 exactly the same form
just simply multiplied by a complex
factor that complex factor depending on
what the frequency Omega k is
now more or less the justification for
this is the proof follows by
simply looking at the response to a
complex exponential
using the convolution integral so
if we put a complex exponential
into a linear time-invariant system
with impulse response a gypsy then
we can express the response as i've
indicated here
we can then recognize that this complex
exponential
can be factored into two terms and so
we can rewrite this complex exponential
as this product second recognize
that this term can be taken
outside the integral over here because
of the fact that
it depends only on tea and not on tap
now
and so what we're left with when we
tracked this through
is that with a complex exponential input
we get
an output which is the same complex
exponential
namely this factor times
this integral and this integral is
what I referred to above as
H all omega-6 K
and so in fact we put in a complex
exponential
we get out a complex exponential love
the same frequency
multiplied by a complex constant and
that is what's referred to as the
eigenfunction property I can function
meaning
that and I can function of a system or
mathematical expression
is a function which when you put it
through the system
comes out looking exactly the same
except for a change in amplitude
that change in amplitude being the eigen
value so
in fact this function is
the eigenfunction
and this bad you
is the I can bag
okay now it's because if the
eigenfunction
property that complex exponentials a
particularly convenient as building
blocks
namely you put it through the system
they come out with the same form
and simply scale the other part to the
question related
to the strategy that we've been pursuing
is
to hope that the signals
can be used as building blocks to
represent a
very broad classes signals through
linear combination
and in fact that turns out to be the
case with complex exponentials
as we worked our way through that
will first consider the case love
periodic signals
and what that leads to is a
representation a periodic signals
through what's called the forty a series
following that
we will turn our attention to non
periodic or as I refer to it a periodic
signals
and the representation that's developed
interns love linear combinations a
complex exponentials
is what's referred to as the 48
transport so
the first thing that we want to deal
with our periodic signals
and before you series okay so
what we're talking about then is the
continuous-time
for a series and
the for a series is a representation for
periodic continuous-time signals we have
a signal then which is periodic and
were choosing t0 to denote the period
so its t0
then corresponds to the period
our periodic signal Omega 0
is to party over t0 as
you recall from our discussion love
periodic signals and sinusoids before
and that's two pirates 0
so this is the fundamental frequency now
let's examine first the ball complex
exponentials
and recognize first the ball that
there is a complex exponential that has
exactly the same period and
fundamental frequency as are more
general periodic signal
namely the complex exponential you to
the jail maker 0t
where Omega 0 is to Paul II over t0
or equivalent Lee t0 is to pie over
Omega 0 now
that's the complex exponential which has
t0 as the fundamental period but
think there are harmonically related
complex exponentials
that also have t0 as a period
although in fact their fundamental
period shorter
so we can also look at complex
exponentials
before either the JK Omega 0t
these likewise are periodic
with the period love t0
although in fact their fundamental
period
is t0 divided by K or equivalently
to par i divided by their fundamental
frequency
k Omega 0 so as K
a richer varies these correspond to
harmonically related complex
exponentials
now with the forty a series
says and will justify this kinda bit by
bit is the discussion goes I'm
what the four-day series says that in
fact what for EA
said which was essentially the
is brilliant insight is that if I have
a very general periodic signal I can
represented as a linear combination of
these harmonically related
complex exponentials so
that representation is what i've
indicated here
and this summation is
what will be referred to as
the for EA
series
and as we proceed with the discussion
there are two issues
couldn't that will develop one is
assuming
that our periodic signal can be
represented this way
how do we determine the for a series
coefficients
as they refer to a suitcase that's one
question
and the second question will be
how broad a class of signals in fact can
be represented that
this way and bats another question their
will deal with separately
now just focusing on this representation
for a minute this representation
love the four EA series which
I repeated again
here
is what's referred to as the complex
exponential form love for EA series
and it's important to note incidently
day this summation involves frequencies
k Omega 0
their are both positive and negative
in other words this index K runs over
limits that include both negative values
and positive ads
now that complex exponential form is one
representation for before you a series
and in fact it's the one that we will be
principally
relying on in this course there is
another representation that
perhaps you come across previously
and that in a variety of other contacts
is
is typically used which is called the
trigonometric form
the forty a series without really
tracking through the algebra
essentially we can get to the
trigonometric for
from the complex exponential form by
recognizing that if we express the
complex coefficients
in polar for or in rectangular for
and expand the complex exponential
term out in terms of cosine plus J sign
using just simply Oilers relation then
in we will end up with the
representation
for the periodic signal
were a re expression love the for a
series
expression that we had previously either
in the form that I indicate here
we're now the periodic signal is
expressed
in terms of a summation love cosines
with appropriate ample to in phase
or another acquittal or triggered a
metric for
involves rearranging this
in terms or a combination
of cosines and signs now
in this representation the frequencies
of the sinusoids
very only over positive frequencies
and typically one thinks
of periodic signals is having positive
frequencies associated with them
however let's look back
at the complex exponential form
for the forty a series at the top of the
board
and in that representation when we use
this representation
will find it convenient to refer to both
positive frequencies and negative
frequencies so
the representation that we will most
typically be using is the complex
exponential form
and in that form what will find as we
think it decomposing a periodic signal
in to its compliments
at different frequencies it will involve
both positive frequencies
negative frequencies
okay now we have the
for EA series representation as i've
indicated here
again so far I sidestepped the issue as
to whether this in fact represents all
the signals that we'd like to represent
let's first address the issue
love how we determine these coefficients
Acer K assuming that in fact this
representation is Val
and again all kinda move through the
algebra
fairly quickly its a the outbreak steps
the ones that
you can pursue more leisurely just the
kinda
verify them in step through them but
essentially the algebra develops I did
the recognition
that if we integrate a complex
exponential
over one period t0
and I mean by this notation that this is
an integral
over a period where I don't particularly
care
where the period starts and where the
period stops in other words
exactly what period I picked that this
integral
is equal to t0 when M is equal to 0
and it's equal to 0 if am is not equal
to 0
that follow simply from the fact that if
we substitute in
for using Oilers relations so that we
have the integral to cosign
was J times assign if M
is not equal to 0 than
of these integrals over a period are
0 the integral over sign it a periodic
have a sinus or a cosigner sign
over an integral number periods is zero
whereas
if M is equal to 0 this in a crawl
will be equal to 20 the integral the
cosine
and the integral on the sign is equal to
okay well the next step
in developing the expression for the
coefficients a Sat K
is to refer back to
before a series expression which was
that except he
is equal to the sum with basic K either
the JK Omega 0t
if we multiply both sides that by either
minus
jaan Omega 0t and
integrate that over a period
both sides of the equation integrated
over a period
so these two equations are equal and
then
in essence interchange the summation and
the integration
so that this pardon the expression cons
outside the psalm
and then we combine these two complex
exponentials together
where we come out is
the expression that i've indicated here
in
and then essentially what happens at
this point algebraically
is that we use the result that we just
developed
to evaluate this cynical so
multiplying both sides the forty a
series in and doing the integration
leads us after the appropriate
manipulation
to the expression that
I have up here and
this is equal to
this integral is equal to t0
if K is equal to an
corresponding 20 up here and 80
otherwise which is what we have
demonstrated or are you previously
and the upshot of all that then is that
the right hand side if this expression
disappears
except for the term when K is equal to n
and so finally we have what I indicate
here
taking t0 and moving it over to the
other side of the equation
we then that then tells us
how we determine the forty a series
coefficients
a7 Auris K so
that in effect and is the
what we refer to as the analysis
equation the equation that begins with
excessive to me
and tells us how to get the for a series
coefficients
what are referred to as
the 48 series synthesis equation
is the equation that tells us
how to build exit see outta love
these complex exponentials so we have
the synthesis equation
which is the one that we started from we
have
the analysis equation which is the
equation
that we just developed
okay so we in effect have
going through the issue love assuming
there for a series representation
is in fact valid how we get
the coefficients we want to address
somewhat the question love how broad a
classic signals that we're talking
are we talking about and what's in fact
amazing
and was for EA's amazing insight
was that it's a very broad class say but
let's first look at just some examples
in which we take a signal assume that it
has the Fourier series representation
and see what the for a series
coefficients look like so
will begin with what I refer to as
an antisymmetric periodic square wave
periodic of course because we're talking
about periodic signals
square wave referring to its shape and
antisymmetric referring to the fact that
it is an odd
time function in other words it is
antisymmetric
about the origin now
the expression for the for a series
coefficients
tells us that we determine a sieve K
by taking one over 20 times the integral
over a period
affects 50 either minus JK Omega 0t
DT the most convenient thing in this
case
is to choose a period which
let's say goes from minus 20 over to the
plus 20 over to
so here except he is -1 here
expertise plus one and so
I've expressed the for a series called
efficiency as
this integral that's from minus 20 over
and then and it said that is the
positive part of the cycle and so we
have
these two integrals now I don't want to
tracked through the details both the
algebra again I
I guess I've decided that that's much
more fun for you do on your own
but the way it comes out when you go
through it
is the expression that I finally
indicate after
suggesting that there are a few more
steps to follow
and what develops is that
those two integrals together for K
not equal to 0 come out to this
expression
and that expression is not valid for k
equal to 0
per kg equal to 0 we can go back to
the basic expression for the forty a
series
which is one over t0 the integral over a
period
exit see in the minus JK Omega 0 /td TD
for cake 10 of course this term
just simply becomes one and
so the zeroth coefficient is one over 20
times the integral
X 50 over a period now
going back to the original function
that we have what we're saying then is
that
0th coefficient is one over 20 times the
integral over
one period which is in effect the
average value
and it straight forward to verify the
for this case that average value
is equal to 0 okay
now let's look at
these for a series coefficients on a bar
graph
and i've indicated that here the
expression for the for a series
coefficients we just developed and
a involves its
0 for cake 0 it's a factor this form
for canine equal to 0 plotted on a bar
graph
then we see values like this 0
at cake 0 and and associated values
and their number things to focus on
when you look at this
one is the fact that the forty a series
coefficients for this example
are surely imaginary
a second is that the Fourier series
coefficients for this example
are odd sequence in other words if you
look at this sequence which you see
are these values for negative K
flipped over so there their imaginary
and odd and
what that results in when
you look at the
the triggered a metric form the 4e a
series
is that in fact those conditions if you
put the terms altogether
lead you to a trigger a metric
representation
which involves only sign terms
in other words no co-signed turns let me
just draw your attention to the fact
that
since a suitcase the acer case or
imaginary
this jay takes care that fact so that
these coefficients
are in fact real so what this says
is that for the antisymmetric square
wave the
it in effect the forty a series is a
sign series
the antisymmetric square wave is an odd
function
sinusoids are not are odd functions and
so this is all kinda reasonable that
we're building
odd function ido odd functions
as an additional aside which a I won't
exploit or refer to any further here
but just draw your attention to is that
another aspect
love this periodic square wave the
particular one that we chose
is dead it is what's referred to as a
on harmonic function in other words
for even values if K
before a series coefficients 30 their
only 90
for iPad use K
okay now let's look at another example
another example
is the symmetric periodic square wave
and this is in fact example
4.5 worked out in more detail in the tax
then
I won't bother to work work this out in
detail here
except to draw your attention to several
points here is the symmetric periodic
square wave
and what I mean by symmetric
is that it's an even time function
now just kinda extrapolating your
intuition
what we you should expect is that if if
it's a
only even time function it should be
built up
or buildable if it's built up a little
%ah to only
even sinusoids and in fact
that's the case so if we look at
the four-day series coefficients for
this
the zeroth coefficient again as the
average value
which in this case is a half here I've
plotted
hi times the for a series coefficients
so
0 thank you as pie over to
the coefficients are now and even
sequence
and in in other words symmetric
about cake 0 and the consequences that
is that when you take these coefficients
and put together the equivalent
triggered a metric form
the triggered a metric for involves
only cosines and no
sign turns now
you'll see this in and other examples
not that will do in the lecture but
examples in the text in the video manual
if in fact
the square way was neither symmetric or
antisymmetric
then the trigonometric form would
involve both
sines and cosines and
that is of course the more general case
furthermore in the two examples are
shown here
we we in both cases
the signal is odd harmonic
in other words for even bad news K
the coefficients are equal to 0 although
I won't justify that here that's a
consequence that the fact that
this symmetry is exactly about half a
period
and if you made the on time with a
square wave
different in relation to the of time
then that property would also
disappear
now
what's kind amazing actually in
is that if we take a square wave like
I have here or as I had in the
antisymmetric case
the implication is that I can bill
that square wave by adding up
on of signs were cosines and
it really seems kinda amazing because
the square wave after all
is a very discontinuous functions
sinusoids are very continuous and it
seems puzzling that in fact
you can do that well let's look in a
little bit of detail
how the sinusoidal
turns and up to
build a square wave and to do that
let's first define what I refer to
as a partial song so
here we have the expression
which is the synthesis
equation telling us how accept T could
be represented
as complex exponentials if it can be and
let's consider just a finite number of
turns in this song
and so X 7ft of course as n goes to
infinity
approaches the infinite sum that we're
talking about and although we could do
this more generally let's not let's
focus on the symmetric square wave case
where because it the symmetry of these
coefficients namely that a suitcase
equal to minus
is equal to a serb minus K we can
rewrite
these turns as cosine turns and so this
partial some
can be express the way arm expressing it
here
well let's look at
a few the Stearns on the graph I have
first the ball exit tea which is our
original square wave
the turn that I indicate here
is the factor over half which
is this term
with any calls one that would correspond
to anyone co-signed term
to that and so the sole those two would
be yes
which looks a little close to the square
wave but
certainly not very close to it at all
and in fact
in its somewhat hard to imagine without
seeing the terms build-up how in fact by
adding more and more turns we can
generate something
that is essentially flat except at the
discontinuities
so let's look at this example and what
I'd like to show
is this example but now as we add many
more turns to it and let's see in fact
how these individual turns add up
to build up the square way so
this is the square wave that we want to
build up
through the forty a series is this some
of sinusoids
and the term for cake 0 will be a
constant which represents the DC value
with this
and so in the partial sum as we develop
it
the first thing they will show is just
the term for cable 0
now for cables one we would add to that
one sinusoidal term and
so some love the term for cake was one
cake was 0
is represented here now
when we go to K calls to because of the
fact that this is an odd harmonic
function
in fact the term for cake was it was too
will be will have zero amplitude and so
this won't change
here we show the
for a series would cake was to and
there's no change
and then we will go to cable 23
and
and we will be adding then one
additional sinusoidal term here's cake
was three
when we go to cable 24 again there won't
be any change
but their will be another term that's
added at cake was five here and cable 6
again because it's odd harmonic no
change and finally cable 7
is shown here okay and we can begin to
see that
this starts to look somewhat like the
square wave but
now to really emphasize how this builds
up let's
more rapidly and Ed many more terms and
in fact
increase the number of turns up to about
a hundred recognizing
that the shape will only change on the
inclusion
all the odd number terms not the
even-numbered turns because it's an odd
harmonic function so now we're
increasing and we're building up toward
k equal to 100 200 turns an
notice that it is the higher
order turns dead tend to build up
the discontinuity corresponding to the
notion
there'd the discontinuities or sharp
edges in a signal
in fact are represented through the
higher
frequencies in the forty a series and
here we have
a not too unreasonable approximation
to the original square wave there is the
artifact of the ripples at the
discontinuity and in fact
though that rippling behavior at the
discontinuities
is referred to as the Gibbs phenomenon
and it's an inherent part love the forty
a series representation at
discontinuities
now to emphasize this
let's decrease the number of turns back
down
and we will carry this down
to k equal to 1 again
to emphasizes how the sinusoids are
building up
the square wave here we are back at Cape
cools
1 and then finally we
will and back in the sinusoids that we
took out
and let's build this back up to 100
turns
showing the approximation dead
we generated with a hundred turns to the
square way
okay so so what you saw is that
in fact we got awfully close to a square
wave
and the other thing think that was kind
of interesting about it is that went
along
was the fact that with the low
frequencies
what we were tending to bill was the
general behavior
and as the higher frequencies came in
that tended to contribute the
discontinuities
work contribute to the discontinuity and
in fact something their will
standout more and more as we go through
our discussion
love for a series of 48 transforms is
that general statement that its the
low-frequency
terms bat represent
the broad time behavior and
its the high-frequency terms that are
used to build up
the sharp transitions in the time domain
okay now we need to get a little more
precise
about the question of how in fact
the 48 series
or when before you a series represents
the functions that we're talking about
and in what sense they represent them
in and so if we look
again at the synthesis
ok wage in were really wanna ask
is if we add up enough for these terms
in what sense does this some represent
this time function well
let's again use the notion love are
partial some
so we have the partial song down here
in and we can think love the difference
between
this partial some and the
original time function as
the ever and I've defined the error here
and what we would like to know is does
this error
decrease as we aired more and more turns
and in fact in what sense if the air
does decrease in what sense
there's a decrease now in detail
this is a fairly complicated an
elaborate topic I don't mean to make
that sound frightening
its mainly a statement that I don't want
to explore it and a lot of detail
but it relates to what is referred to
as the issue a convergence the forty a
series
and the convergence the 48 series
the the bottom line on at the kinda and
statement
can be made in several ways one
related to convergence the for a series
is the following if
I have a time function which
is what is referred to as square
integrable namely
its integral over a period is finite
then
what you can show kinda amazingly
is that the energy E in
that error in other words the energy in
the difference between the original
function
and the partial some the energy and that
goes to zero as n goes to infinity
a somewhat tighter condition is a
condition referred to as it the racially
conditions which says that
if the time function
is absolutely integral not square
honorable but absolutely integral
and I've kinda hedge the issue by just
simply referred to accept T as being
well behaved
then the statement is dead the error in
fact goes to zero
as and increases except at the
discontinuities
and what well-behaved means in that
statement
is that as discussed in the book there
are a finite number
maxima and minima in any period and a
finite number finite discontinuities
which is essentially
always the case so under square in Accra
bility
what we have is the statement not that
the partial sum goes to the right value
at every point
but that the energy in the air goes to
zero
under the jewish way conditions it says
that in fact the signal goes to the
right back to you
at every time instant except
at the discontinuities so
going back to the square wave
the square wave satisfies either one of
those conditions and so
what the consequences is that with the
square wave
if we looked at the error then in fact
what we would find is that the energy
in the error would go to zero as we at
more and more turns in the partial some
and in fact
if says the square wave also satisfies
the dish les conditions
the actual value with the air the
difference between
the partial some and the true value will
will
actually go to zero that difference will
go to zero
except at the discontinuities and
that in fact is kinda evident as
we watch the function build-up
by adding up these terms and so in fact
let's go back and see again
the development the partial sons
in relation to the original time
function let's observe
this time again basically what we saw
before which is that it builds up
to the right answer and furthermore what
will plot this time also as a function
of time
is the energy in the air and what we'll
see is that the energy in the air
will be tending toward zero as the
number
turns increases so
once again we have the square wave and
we want to again show the buildup of the
forty a series this time showing also
how the energy in the air decreases as
we had more and more turns
well once again will begin
with cake was 0 corresponding to the
constant term
and was shown on the bottom trace is
the energy in the air between those two
and
will then and the term for cables 1
to the DC term and will see that the
energy will decrease
when we do that here we have then the
summer
cake 10 cables 1 now
with cables to the energy won't decrease
any further because it's an odd harmonic
function
that's what we've just added in when we
add in the term for cables 3
again will see the energy in the air
decrease
as reflected in the bottom curve
so there we are at cables 3 when
we go to cable 24 there again is no
change in the air
at cables 5 again the air decreases
k equal to 6% know there will be no
change again
an 8k course 7 the energy decreases
and now let's show the how the air
decreases by building up the number
turns much more rapidly already the air
has gotten somewhat small on the scale
in which were showing it so let's expand
out
the ever scale the vertical axis
displaying the energy in the error so
that we could watch
how the energy decreases as
we had more and more terms so here we
have
the vertical scale expanded and
now what we'll do is increase
the number of turns in the forty a
series and watch the energy in the air
at decreasing
always decreasing of course on the
inclusion
love the odd number turns and
not on the inclusion of the
even-numbered turns because the fact
that it's an odd harmonic function now
the energy in the air
asymptotically will approach 0 although
point by point the forty a series will
never be equal to the square wave
it will at every instant of time
except at the discontinuities where
there will always be
some ripple corresponding to
what's referred to as the Gibbs
phenomenon
okay well so what we've seen in is
a and a quick look at the Fourier series
representation love periodic signals
we more broadly
wanna have a more general representation
love oath signals in terms of complex
exponentials and so our next step
will be to move toward a representation
I'll not periodic or a periodic signals
now the details if this I leave for the
next lecture
the only thought that I want introduced
at this point
is the basic strategy you which
is somewhat amazing and kinda
interesting to reflect on
in the interim the basic strategy
with in a periodic signal is
to think love representing
this a periodic signal as a linear
combination of complex exponentials
by this simple trick all
periodically replicating this signal
generating a periodic signal
using a Fourier series representation
for that periodic signal and then
simply letting the period go to infinity
as the period goes to infinity that
periodic signal becomes the original
a periodic one that we have before and a
40 a series
representation then becomes what we
refer to as the Fourier transform so
that's just a quick look at kind of the
basic idea
and approach that will take in the next
lecture will develop this
a little more carefully more fully
moving from the 40 a series which we've
used for periodic signals
to develop the for EA transform
which will then be representation for a
periodic see
thank you