the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU home in
in
the in
the new the
last time we began the discussion
love z transform and
as with the La Paz transforming
continuous time we developed it
as a generalization of the Fourier
transform the
expression that we got to dizzy
transform is
the some that I indicate here and
we also briefly talked about and in
Bercy transform
integral and some other informal methods
love computing the inverse eat transform
but
we focused in particular on the
relationship between busy transform
and the Fourier transform pointing out
first the ball dead busy transform
when we choose the magnitude is the
equal to 1 so the magnitude is the the
for
you to the jail maker just simply
reduces
to the 4e a transformer the sequence
then in addition we
explored busy transform foresee more
general complex number
and in a discrete-time z transform case
we expressed that complex number in
polar form
as our you DJ Omega and
recognized dead busy transform
expression
in fact corresponds to the four EA
transform
love the sequence exponentially weighted
and
because I love the exponential weighting
the
see transform converges for some
values of our corresponding to some
exponential weighting
and perhaps not for others and that
led to a notion which corresponded to
the regional convergence associated with
dizzy transform
and we talked some about properties in
the region of convergence
particularly in relation to the poll 0
banner now the sea transform has
a number all important and useful
properties just as the apostrophe s form
does
and as one part of this lecture what
will want to do in fact
is exploit some of these properties in
the context of systems described by with
your constant coefficient difference
equations
the spur ticular properties said
play an important role in that context
so the properties that I indicate year
and in particular their is as
with continuous time a linearity
property that tells us
dead the busy transform a linear
combination of sequences
in fact is the same linear combination
of busy transforms
a shifting property that
indicates dead dizzy transform
Aug exit then shifted is busy transform
all exit then multiplied by a factor Z
the -10 0
and then the convolution property
for which the z transform
all a convolution sequences is
the product all the associated see
transforms
and with all of these properties
of course there is again the issue love
what the Associated region of
convergence is
in comparison with the regional
convergence the original sequences
and that is an issue this address
somewhat more in the text and let's not
going to adhere
with the
convolution property the
convolution property as in
continuous-time
course provides a mechanism for dealing
with linear time-invariant systems in
particular
in the time domain a linear
time-invariant system
is described through convolution namely
the output is the convolution love the
input
and the impulse response because of the
convolution property associated with
busy transform
z transform up the output is busy
transformer the input
times the sea transform up the impulse
response
and again very much the same as
what we had in continuous-time and also
what we had
in the context that the discussion with
the Fourier transform
in fact because if the relationship
between busy transform the 48 transform
busy transform all the impulse response
evaluated on the unit circle in other
words for the magnitude is equal to 1
in fact corresponds to the frequency
response of the system
more generally when we talk about this
the transform
are the impulse response we will refer
to it as
the system function associated with the
system
now the convolution property in these
other properties as i indicated
we will find useful in talking about
systems which are described
by linear constant coefficient
difference equations and in fact
will do that shortly but first what I'd
like to do
is to continue
to focus on the system function
for linear time-invariant systems and
make a couple comments
that tie back to some things that we
said in the last lecture
relating to the relationship between
the region of convergence a system or
I'll I'm sorry the regional convergence
a busy transform
and the issue of how that
where that is in relation to the holes a
busy transport
now in particular we can draw some
conclusions
flying back to that discussion about the
polo cations 0 the system function
in relation to weathered the system is
stable and whether the system is causal
in particular recall from one of the
early lectures way back when
dead stability for a system
corresponded to the statement that the
impulse response
is absolutely some local furthermore
when we talked about the Fourier
transform
the Fourier transform all a sequence
converges if the sequence is absolutely
some mobile
so in fact the condition for stability
and others I'll a system and the
conditions for convergence in the
Fourier transform ovitz impulse response
in fact are the same condition namely
absolute some ability now
what does this mean what it means is
dead
if the Fourier transform converges
that means that the z transform
converges on the unit circle
consequently if the system is stable
then the system function z transform the
impulse response
Moss also converge on the unit circle
in other words the impulse response must
have a 48 transform
that converges soul for stable system
then the region of convergence the
system function
must include the unit circle in the
seaplane
so we see how stability relates
to the location all
the region of convergence and we can
also relate causality
to the region of convergence in
particular we know
dead if system is causal
than the impulse response is right sided
for sequences right-sided the regional
convergence
love it see transform must be outside
the outermost poll
so for causality the regional
convergence services to function must be
outside the outermost poll
for stability the regional convergence
must include the unit circle
and in fact we can also then draw from
at the conclusion
dead if we have a system its causal
unstable
than all polls must be inside the unit
circle
because of the fact that the polls must
because the fact that the region of
convergence must be
outside the outermost poll and has to
also include the unit circle
soul for example if we had
let's say system with a system function
as I indicate here
with the algebraic expression for the
system function
being the expression that I indicate
here with a pole at sequels a third
and another poll as equals to an 8-0 at
the origin
if in fact the system
was causal corresponding to an impulse
response that's right sided
this then would be the region of
convergence
the system function alternatively
if I knew that the system was stable
then I know that
the region of convergence must include
the unit circle and so
this would be then the region of
convergence
and what you might now want to ask
yourselves
is if instead the region of convergence
for the system function is this there
and
is the system causal first question
second question is is the system stable
remembering that for causality the
regional convergence must be outside the
outermost poll
and for stability must include the unit
circle
all right now what I'd like to do is
look at the properties
love the z transform
and in particular exploit these
properties in the context systems
that are described by linear constant
coefficient difference equations
and the three basic properties that play
a key role in that discussion
are the linearity property
shifting property and the convolution
property
and and so the stand are the properties
dead I want to exploit so
let's do that by first looking at a
first-order difference equation and in
the case
love a first-order difference equation
which
I've written as i indicate year no turns
on the right hand side but we could have
terms of course in general
so why am i sayi van -1 equals x seven
and we can use the linearity property
so that if we take this the transformer
both sides have this expression
that will then be busy transformer this
term plus the transformer this term
and so using those properties
and together with the shifting property
the property that tells us that the Z
transform I'll
y ven -1 is see to the -1 times the
transformer y ven
we then convert the difference equation
to an algebraic expression
and we can solve this outbreak
expression for
busy transform up the output in terms of
busy transformer the input
now what we know from the convolution
property
is that for system the the chance for
the output is the system function times
the transformer the input
so this factor that we have then
must correspond to the
system function or equivalent Lee
busy transform of the impulse response
the system
and in fact then if we have this the
transform we could figure out
what the impulse response that the
system is
by computing or determining what the
inverse the transformants
except for the fact that that expression
is an algebraic expression and
doesn't yet totally specified dizzy
transform because we don't yet know what
the region of convergence is
how do we get the regional convergence
well we have the same issue here as we
have with the apostrophe in swarm
namely the point dead difference
equation
tells us in essence what the algebraic
expression is
for the system function but doesn't
specify the region of convergence
that is specified by either explicitly
because it's one way or another we know
with the impulse responses
or implicitly because we know certain
properties in the system
such as causality and/or stability
so if on a
let's say a imposed on this system in
addition to the difference equation
the condition all causality
then what that requires is dead the
impulse
response the right-sided or
the region of convergence be outside the
outermost poll
and so for this example that would
require then
that the region of convergence
correspond to
the magnitude is Z greater than the
magnitude a
what you might think about is whether I
would get the same condition
if I required instead that the system
be stable and furthermore you could
think about the question of whether I
could
specify or impose on this system that if
the boat stable in causal
the real issue let me just kind of point
to it is dead
the answer to those questions relate to
whether the magnitude a vase less than 1
with a magnitude is greater than one
if the magnitude have a is less than one
and I specify causality
that will also mean
that the system is stable in any case
given this region of convergence then
the
impulse response is the inverse
transformer that see transform which is
a to the end times you there
right now let's look at second order
equation is a very similar strategy
for the second-order equation the one
that I picked is
love this particular form and I've
written
the coefficients parametrically as i
indicate here for a specific reason
which will see shortly again I can apply
this the transform
to this expression and I've skipped
an algebraic stepper to hear when I do
this then
again you I use the when you're ready
property and a shifting property
and I end up with this algebraic
expression
if I now solve that to express why if
the
in terms of exits the and a function of
Z
then this is what I get for the system
function
and in so this is now
a second-order system function and will
have 20 that the origin
and it will have two poles
again and there's the question 0
what we assume about the regional
convergence I haven't specified date yet
but if we let's say assume that
the reach dead the system is causal
which I will tend to do
then that means that the region of
convergence is outside the outermost
poll
now where the polls well let me just
kinda vindicate
dad if and you can verify this
algebraically
I actually Jer dead
if the cosine beta term
is less than 1
then the roots of this polynomial
will be complex and in fact the polls
are at are eat a plus or minus J theta
soul for Cosi pay to less than 1% then
the polls are complex and
the complex polls at an angle theta and
with a distance from the origin equal to
the parameter are
so in fact let's just look at that
and what I show here is the
poll 0 pattern
assuming that are is less than one
and that cosine data is less than one
and we have a complex poll pair shown
here
and now if we we assume that the system
was causal
that means that the region of
convergence is outside these polls
and that would then include the unit
circle
which means that the system is also
stable
and in fact as long as the region of
convergence includes the unit circle
we can also talk about the
frequency response of the system namely
we can evaluate the system function
on the unit circle and we in fact
evaluated
the forty a transform associated with
this
polls 0 pattern last time and recalled
that
the frequency response then is one that
has
a resident character with the resonant
peak
being roughly in the the sanity love
the angle of the Polo cation
and as the parameter are very slight
Cesar get smaller
this peak 10's to broaden as our
gets closer to one the residence tends
to get sharp
alright well this is now
can a job look at busy transform and we
see very strong parallels to the
low-cost rents form
in fact throughout the course
I tried to emphasize and it just
naturally happens
that there are very strong relationships
and parallels between continuous-time
and discrete-time
and in fact at one point we
specifically map from continuous I
discrete time when we talked about
discrete-time processing of
continuous-time signals
and what I'd like to do now is turn our
attention
to another very important reason
for mapping from continuous-time to
discrete-time
and in the process of doing this what
will need to do is exploit
fairly heavily the insight into wishin
and procedures that we've developed for
the La Paz transform and easy transport
specifically what I would like to begin
is a discussion
relating to mapping continuous-time
filters to discrete-time filters
or continuous-time system functions to
discrete-time system functions now
why would we want to do that well their
are at least several reasons for wanting
to Mac continuous-time
filters to discrete-time filters one of
course is the fact that
in some situations what we're interested
in
doing is processing continuous-time
signals
with discrete-time systems or
said another way simulate
continuous-time
systems with discrete-time systems
and so would be natural in a setting
like that to think a mapping the
the desired continuous I filter to a
discrete-time
told so that's one very important
context
is another very important context in
which
this is done and then is in the con- it
or in the in the context or
for the purpose all exploiting
establish design procedures for
continuous five filters
the point is the following: we may or
may not
be processing it a sample
continuous-time signal with our
discrete-time salter maybe just be
discrete-time signals that we're working
with
but in that situation
still we need to design the appropriate
discreet I filter
historically their is a very
rich history
associated with design a continuous-time
filters
and in many cases it's possible
and very worthwhile and efficient to
take those designs and map dome
to discrete-time designs to use them as
discrete time filters
so another very important reason for
talking about the kinds mappings there
we will be going into
is this simply take advantage I love
what has been done historically
in the continuous-time case
all right now if we want to map
continuous I filters to discrete-time
filters
then in continuous-time we're talking
about a system function
and an associated differential equation
and indiscreet I'm there is the
corresponding
system function and the corresponding
difference equation and
basically what we want to do is generate
from a continuous-time system
in some way a discrete-time system that
meets in dissociated set ok desired
specifications
now there's certain constraints that its
reasonable an important to impose on
whatever kinds mappings we use
obviously wanna mapping that will take
are continuous-time system function
and map it to a discrete-time system
function correspondingly in the time
domain
their is a continuous-time impulse
response
that maps to the Associated
discrete-time impulse response
these are more less natural the two that
are important and
sometimes easy to lose sight of are the
two that I indicate here
in particular if we r mapping
a continuous-time filter with let's say
a desire desirable
frequency response to a discrete-time
filter and we would like to preserve the
good qualities that frequency response
as we look at the discrete-time
frequency response
then it's important that
what happens in the ass plane for the
continues type filter along the jail
make axis
relate in a nice way to what happens
in the seaplane around the unit circle
because it's this over here
that represents the frequency response
in continuous-time
and this contour over here that
represents the frequency response
in discrete-time so that's an important
property we want
have the J Omega axis to map
to the unit circle another
more less natural condition to impose
is a condition that if we
are assured in some way that our
continuous type filter is stable
then we would like to concentrate on
design procedures that
more or less preserved at and will give
us stable digital filters
so these are are reasonable conditions
to impose on the procedure
and what I'd like to do in the remainder
this lecture is look at
to common procedures for mapping
continuous-time filters to discrete-time
filters the first one that I
want to talk about is one that in fact
is very frequently use
and also one
that as we'll see for a variety of
reasons is
highly undesirable the second
is one that is also frequently used and
as we'll see
is arm in certain situations very
desirable
the first one i wanna talk about is
the more less intuitive simple
procedure 0 mapping a difference
equation at
differential equation to a difference
equation by
simply replacing derivatives by
differences and kinda the idea is that
it
a derivative is more or less a
difference and there's some dummy
parameter capital T that I've thrown in
here which
I won't focus too much on but in any
case
this seems to have some plausibility if
we take the differential equation and do
this with all the derivatives
on both in terms of wife tnx ft
what we'll end up with is a difference
equation
now what we can use are the properties
love the boss transforming dizzy
transform
to see what this means in terms of a
mapping a particular
using a different ciation property from
a plus transforms
in the a-plus transform domain we would
have this
using the properties for
busy transform busy transformer this
expression would be this
and so in effect what it says
is dead every place in the system
function
or the differential equation that we
would be multiplying by S
when we'll pass transformed in the
difference equation we would be
multiplying by this factor
so in fact what this means is that
the mapping from continuous time to
discrete-time
corresponds to taking the system
function
and replacing s wherever we see it
by one minus the to the -1 over capital
T
and so if we have a system function in
continuous-time
and we map it to a discrete-time system
function
this way by replacing derivatives by
differences
then that corresponds to replacing asked
by
$1 -2 -1 over capital T
now we'll see shortly what this mapping
actually means more specifically in
relating yes plane to the seaplane
let me just quickly because I want to
refer to this
also point to another procedure very
much like backward differences
which corresponds to replacing
derivatives not by the backward
difference is that I just showed
but by former differences and in that
case
then the mapping corresponds replacing
asked by
Zeta minus one over capital T
looks very similar to the previous case
and
so there the relationship between the
system functions
is what I indicate here
alright well let's just take a look at
what that those mappings correspond to
when we look at this specifically
in the S plane and in the seaplane brown
what I show here is the s plane
and chorus its things in the left after
the S plane posing left after the s plan
that would guarantee stability
its the chair make axis that tells us
about the frequency response
and in the seaplane its
the unit circle that tells us about the
frequency response
and things inside the unit circle or
poles inside the unit circle to
guarantee stability
now the mapping from yes point to the
sea plane corresponding
to replacing derivatives by backward
differences
in fact can be shown to correspond
to mapping DJ Omega axis
not to the unit circle but
to the little circle that I show here
which is inside the unit circle
the left half oath the S plane maps to
the insider that circle
what does that mean that means they had
if we have
a really good frequency response
characteristic along this contour
in the S plane will see that same
frequency response
along this little circle that's not the
one we want though
we would like to see that same frequency
response around the unit circle
to emphasize this point even more
suppose for example
that we had appear polls
in our continuous-time system function
that look like this
then where they're likely to end up
in busy plane is
inside the unit circle of course by if
the polls here are close to the jail
make axis
that means that these polls will be
close to this circle
but in fact might be very far away from
the unit circle
so what would happen then is dead
if we saw in the continuous-time filter
very sharp residence
the discrete-time filter in fact might
very well have that residents broadened
considerably
because the polls is so far away from
the unit circle
now 1 plus
with this method and it's about the only
one
is the fact that the left after the S
plane
maps inside the unit circle in fact
inside the circle inside the unit circle
and so stability is always guarantee
let me just quickly mention and you'll
have a chance to look at this a little
more carefully in the
video course manual dead for
forward difference is that a backward
differences
this contour and yes plane
maps to a line in the seaplane
which is online tangent to the unit
circle
and in fact is the line that I show
their
so not only are for differences
equally bad and turns at the issue
whether they mapped from the chair may
get access to the unit circle
but they have further difficulty
associated with them
which is the difficulty dead
they may not and generally don't
guarantee stability
right now that's one method and
I'll one as i indicated that so often
use partly
I am a because it seems so intuitively
plausible
and what you can see is that by
understand it carefully the issues and
the techniques of apostasy transforms
you can begin to see what some of the
difficulties with that method
for those methods are the next method
dad I'd like to talk about is a method
that in fact is very
commonly used and it's a very important
useful method
which Chynoweth can be motivated by
thinking along the lines of both
mapping the continuous-time filter to
a discrete-time sold their in such a way
dead the shape up the impulse response
is preserved
and in fact more specifically so that
the discrete-time impulse response
corresponds to
samples love the continuous-time impulse
response
and this is a method that's referred to
as
in polls invariance
so what imposing variance corresponds to
is designing the filter in such a way
that the discrete-time filter
impulse response is simply
sample version love the continuous type
filter impulse response
with a sampling period which I do know
here's capital T
and that will turn into a slightly
confusing parameter
shortly and perhaps carried over into
the next lecture
and hopefully we'll get that
straightened out though
within those two lectures now
remembering
the issues of sampling the discrete-time
frequency response then since the
frequency response is the forty a
transformer the impulse response
is related to the continuous-time
impulse responses I indicate here
and what this says is that it is
the superposition
all replications love the continuous
high frequency response
linearly scaled in frequency and
shifted and added to each other it's the
same old
are so shifting ending a really is
saying issued the same sampling issues
that we've addressed before
well this equation will help us
understand what the frequency response
looks like
but in terms of an analytical procedure
for mapping the continuous-time system
function
to a discrete-time system function we
can see
dat and develop it in the following way:
let's consider the continuous-time
system function
expanded in a partial fraction expansion
and just for convenience on picking
first-order polls this can be
general generalized or rather single
polls this can be generalized
to on multiple order polls
and we won't do that here the same basic
strategy applies
if we expand this in a partial fraction
expansion
and we look at the impulse response
associated with this
we know how to take the inverse Laplace
transform with this
where I'm just naturally assume because
our the throughout the discussion
the continuous-time impulse response
then is
someone exponentials with these
amplitudes
and at these complex exponential
frequencies
now impulse in various corresponds to
sampling this
and so the discrete-time impulse
response
is simply a sample version of this and
in the AC cave course carries down
and we have the exponential were
sampling at Eagles and capital T and so
we've replaced that here and then the
unit step
to truncate things for negative time
right well let's manipulate this further
and
eventually what we want to get is
relationship mapping
from the continuous-time to the
discrete-time filter
so we had this staff that we can rewrite
that
now as I show here just
simply taking this and outside we have
EDS
k capital T so now this is %uh the for
the summer terms like a suitcase me
times fated to the N we can compute is a
transformer this
and busy transform the week at I show
here it's simply a sieve K over one
minus
in the s2k capital T see the -1
simply carrying this term or this
this parameter down
so we started with a continuous-time
system function which was the sole turns
like a sieve K over s minus SFK the
polls were tested K
we now have the day that discrete I
filter in this form
and consequently then this procedure in
Polson variance
corresponds to
mapping the continuous I filter to
discrete-time filter
by mapping the polls in the continuous I
filter
according to this mapping
the continuous part filter poll and SFK
gets map topo edited the s2k capital T
and the coefficients a suitcase
a are preserve
and that an algebraically is what the
procedure of impulse and variance
corresponds to
okay well let's look at
how we interpret summer this in the
frequency domain
and in particular
we have the expression that tells us how
the
discrete-time frequency response
is related to the continuous-time
frequency response
this is the expression that we had
previously
when we have talked about issues of
sampling
so that means that we would form the
discrete I frequency response
by taking the continuous-time one
scaling it
in frequency according to this parameter
capital T
and then Anne replications that together
so if this is the continuous-time
frequency response just simply an idea
low-pass filter with the cutoff
frequency of omega-6
see van the its
frequency scaling operation would keep
the same basic shape
but but linearly scale the frequency
axis so that we now have Omega sexy
times capital T
and then the discrete-time frequency
response
would be a superposition at these and it
together
at multiples of 2 pie indiscreet
time-frequency
and so that's what we have here
so this is the discreet I frequency
response
so this looks very nice it looks like in
Polson variance will
take the continuous I frequency response
just simply
linearly scale the frequency axis and
incidently periodically repeated
we know that for an idea low-pass filter
that looks just fine and in fact
for a ban limited frequency response
that looks just fine
but we know also that anytime that were
sampling
here with sampling the impulse response
we have
in effect in the frequency domain where
the potential for a second effect
dead we refer to as alias so in fact
if instead of the ideal low-pass filter
we had taken a filter that was an
approximation to a low pass filter
then the corresponding frequency scale
version
would look as I've shown here and now as
we add these together
then what we will have is some potential
for distortion corresponding to the fact
that
these replications overlap and
what that will lead to is aliasing
so some things that we can say about
imposing variance
is there yet we have an algebraic
procedure at all
illustrate with another example shortly
for taking a continuous I've system
function mapping it to a discrete-time
system function it has a very nice
property in terms of both
a %uh mapping the mapping from
the frequency axis in continuous-time
the to the
unit circle namely
to a first approximation as long as
there's no aliasing
the mapping is just simply a linear
scaling the frequency axis although
there may be some alias saying that
means of course that this method can
only be used
if the frequency response that's being
mapped work the system is being mad
has a frequency response that's
approximately low-pass had asked to be
approximately ban limit
and then what we have is some
pop potential distortion which comes
about because bailey's
also because if the mapping the fact
that polls at soka
get map to polls at you to the s2k
capital T
if the analog a continuous-time filter
is
stable meaning that the real party Vesta
case is negative
then the discrete types author is
guaranteed to be stable
in other words the magnitude as the
suitcase a
will be guaranteed to be less than 1 I'm
assuming of course that discussion
we're are always imposing causality and
systems
Bardwell to just look at the algebraic
mapping
a little more carefully let's take a
simple example
here is an example all
a system a continuous-time system where
I simply have a resident poll pair
with a real with an imaginary part along
the
Majuri accessible make it so far a real
part of mine a South
for and so The Associated system
function and
is just the expression which
incorporates
the two poles and I put in a scale
factor to Omega so far
and now to design the discrete-time
filter using in Polson variance you
carry out a partial fraction expansion
of this
and that partial fraction expansion is
shown below
we have a pole at minus South a-minus J
Omega are and at minus alpha plus Chi
Omega are
and to determine the
discrete-time filter based on imposing
variance
we would map the polls and preserves the
coefficients a Sat K
referred to as the residues and so the
discrete-time filter that we would end
up with
as system function which I indicate
here and we have is a
said preserve the residue and
the poll is now at either minus out the
TE
you the vice chair makes a party that's
one term
and the other term in Assam has a pole
at the complex conjugate
location if we were to add these to
factors together then what we would get
is both polls and
0 at the origin and
in fact then the poll is defined by
its angle and this angle
is is
eat see the J Omega so far
capital see and by its radius
and this radius is eat to the minors
alpha capital T
all right now we can look at the
frequency response
associated with that and and let's just
do that
for the original
continuous-time frequency response
what we have is simply a resident
character is a show
as shown here and if we
map this using your post in various
which we just did
the resulting frequency response
that we get is the frequency response
which I indicate
we see that that's basically identical
to the continuous-time frequency
response
except for by a linear scaling the
frequency axis if you just compare
the the dimensions along which the
frequency axis is shown
and for one except for one minor
issue which we switch is particularly
highlighted
when we look at the frequency response
at higher frequencies
what's the reason why those two curves
don't quite follow each other at higher
frequencies
well the reason is aliasing other words
what's happened
is dead the in the process I'll
applying in polls and variance the
frequency response the original
continuous-time filter
is approximately preserved except for
some distortion
thats ocean correspondent aliasing
well just for comparison let's look at
what
would happen if we took the same example
and when I can work it through here
carefully
waco work through it all not even
accurately
if we took the same example and mapped
it
to a discrete-time filter by replacing
the rivet is by backward differences
what happens in that case is dead we get
frequency response that I indicate
here and notice dat the resonance
in the original continuous-time filter
is
totally lost in fact
basically the character love the
continuous-time
frequency responses los what's the
reason
well the reason goes back to the picture
that I drew before
the continuous-time filter had a
pair love resident polls close to the
jail may axis
when those get mapped using back with
differences they end up close to this
little circle that's inside the unit
circle
but in fact for this example are far
away from the unit circle
alright so so far we have
one useful technique for mapping
continuous I filters to discrete-time
filters and apart to highlights are the
issues I focused attention also
on some not so useful methods
namely mapping derivatives to forward or
backward differences
next time what I would like to do
is look at impulse invariance
for another example namely the design
0 a Butterworth filter and all
talk more specifically about what
butterworth filters or
at the beginning that lecture and then
in addition
what will introduce is another very
useful technique
which has some difficulties which
imposed and variance doesn't have
but avoids the principal
difficulty that impulse in various does
have namely aliasing
admitted is referred to as the violin
you transformation
which we will to find and
utilize next time thank you