the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license
your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high-quality educational resources for
free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of them IT
courses
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at 0 CW
that MIT that EDU ha in
in
the
the in
the moon
the
over the last several lectures we
developed the for a representation for
and continuous-time signals what i'd
now like to do is develop a similar
representation for discrete-time
and let me begin a discussion by
reminding you up what are basic
motivation was the idea
is that what we wanted to do was exploit
the properties
love linearity in time and variance for
linear time-invariant systems
so and in the case love
linear time-invariant systems the
basic idea was to consider
decomposing the input as a linear
combination
love basic inputs and then
because I've Lenny arity the output
could be expressed as
a linear combination of corresponding
outputs where
saw I serve I is the output
due to fee survive so
basically what we attempted to do was
decompose the input
and then reconstruct the output through
a linear combination all the outputs to
those basic inputs
we then focused on the notion
love choosing the basic inputs
with two criterion mine one was
to choose them so that a broad class
signals
could be constructed out over those
basic inputs
and the second was to choose the basic
inputs
so that the response to those was easy
to compute
and as you recall one representation
that we ended up with
with those basic criteria in mind:
was the representation through
convolution
and then in beginning the discussion
love the for a representation of
continuous-time signals
we chose as another said a basic inputs
complex exponentials so
for continuous-time we chose
a set love basic inputs which were
complex exponential
the motivation there was the fact that
the complex exponentials have we
referred to as
the I can function property namely
if we put complex exponentials into our
continuous-time systems
than the output is a complex exponential
love the same form with
only a change in complex amplitude
and that change in complex amplitude is
what we referred to as the
frequency response %uh the system
and also by the way as it developed
later
that frequency response as you should
now recognize from this expression
is in fact the 48 transform the
continuous-time for EA transform
all the system impulse response and
the notion all decomposing a signal as a
linear combination of both these complex
exponentials
is what the first the forty a series
representation and then later the
Fourier transform representation
corresponded to
and finally to remind you
love one additional point the fact is
that because the eigenfunction property
the response
once we decompose the input as a linear
combination
complex exponentials the response to
that when your combination
is straightforward to compute once we
know the frequency response
because if the eigenfunction property
now
basically the same strategy
and many of the same ideas work in
discrete-time
paralleling almost exactly what happened
in continuous-time
so the similarities between
discrete-time and continuous-time
are very strong although as we'll see
there are a number
a differences and it's important
as we go through the discussion to
illuminate
not only the similarities but obviously
also the differences
well let's begin with the I can function
property
and let me just say that just as in
continuous-time
if we consider said a basic signals
which are complex exponentials
then discrete-time linear time-invariant
systems
have the I can function property namely
if we put a complex exponential into the
system
the response is a complex exponential
at the same complex frequency and
simply multiplied by inappropriate
complex factor or constant
and just as we did in
continuous-time we will be
referring to this complex constant which
is a function
of course the frequency other complex
exponential input
will be referring to this as the
frequency response
and although it's not particularly
evident at this point
as the discussion develops through this
lecture what in fact will happen
is very much paralleling
continuous-time this particular
expression
in fact will correspond
to what will refer to as the
for EA transform the discrete-time
Fourier transform
up the system impulse response so there
of course there's a very strong parallel
between continuous-time and
discrete-time
now just as we did in continuous-time
let's begin a discussion by
first concentrating on periodic the
representation through complex
exponentials
love periodic sequences and then
will generalize that discussion to the
representation
Ave periodic signals so
let's consider furs a periodic signal
or in general signals which are periodic
period to notify capital and and then
course the fundamental frequency is
to pie divided by capital
now we can consider exponentials
which have this as a fundamental
frequency
war which are harmonics that
and that would correspond to the class
of complex exponentials
the form you to the JK Omega 0n
so these complex exponentials then
as k varies are complex exponentials
that are harmonically related with
all of which our periodic with the same
period
capital and although the fundamental
is different for each of these each of
them being related by
an integer amount
now again just as we did in continuous
time we can consider
attempting to build our periodic signal
I have a linear combination
love these and so we consider
a periodic signal which is
a weighted sum all these
me complex exponentials and
of course this periodic signal this is a
periodic signal as can be
verified in more or less in a
straightforward way by substitution
and of course one of the things that
will want to address shortly
is how broad a classic signals again can
be represented
by this psalm and another question
obviously will be
how do we determine the coefficients a
suitcase
however in before we do that let me
focus on an important distinction
between continuous-time and
discrete-time
in the context of these complex
exponentials and this representation
when we talked about complex
exponentials and sinusoids
early in the cores one up the difference
is that we saw between continuous-time
and discrete-time
is dead in continuous-time as we very
in the frequency variable we see
different complex exponentials
as Omega berries whereas in
discrete-time
we saw in fact dead there was a period
this city
or said another way it's straightforward
to verify
that if we think I love this
class a complex exponentials day
in fact if we consider burying
K by an ink to it
capital and where capital and is the
period
all the fundamental
complex exponential then in fact
if we replace K by K plus capital and
we'll see exactly the same complex
exponentials over again
now what does that say what it says is
that if I consider this class of complex
exponentials
SK varies from zero
through capital N -1 we've seen
we will see all of the ones that there
are two see
there aren't any more and so in fact
if we can build excessive and
I have this linear combination then
we better be able to do it as k varies
from 0
up to and -1 because
beyond that will simply see the same
complex s
exponentials over again so for example
if k takes on the value capital and
that will be exactly the same complex
exponential
as if KZ 0
so in fact this some ranges
only over capital in above the distinct
complex exponentials
let's say for example from 0 to capital
and -1
although in fact since these complex
exponentials repeat
in K I could actually consider instead
have
from 0 to N -1 I could consider from one
and or from to too and plus one or
whatever
or said another way in this
representation
I could alternatively shoes K
outside this range thinking
0 these coefficients simply as
periodically repeating in K
because if the fact that these complex
exponentials
periodically repeating K so in fact
in place if this expression it will be
comin in writing the forty a series
expression
to write it as i've indicated here where
the implication is
that these Fourier coefficients
periodically repeated as K continues to
rip
to repeat outside the interval from 0 to
N -1
and so this notation in fact says
at what we're going to use are
is K ranging over one period
love this periodic sequence which is the
forty a series called
visions okay so
the expression that we have been for the
forty a series
I've repeated here and the implication
now is that
the AC K's are periodic they
periodically repeat because of course
these exponentials periodically repeated
this indicates there we only use them
over one period
and now we can inquire as to how
we determine the coefficients aces K
well we can formally go through this
much as we did in
the continuous-time case in and 0
we do in fact do that in the text which
involves substituting some
sums in a change in yours summation
cetera
but let me a draw your attention to the
fact that
this in fact can be thought I love
as capital in equations in capital and
unknowns
in other words we know x7 over a period
and so we know what the left hand side
if this is for capital and bad news
and we'd like to determine these
constant sese K
well it turns out that their is a nice
convening in closed form expression for
that
and in fact if we evaluate the
closed-form expression
through any variety of algebraic
manipulations
we end up then with the
analysis equation and the analysis
equation
which tells us how to get the
coefficients AC K
from excessive and is what I've
indicated here and
so this tells us how for Maxim and
to get the AC K's and of course the
first equation
tells us how x7 is built up by the VA's
K's notice incidently that
there is a strong to our the between
these two equations
and that's a duality that will return to
actually toward the end of the next
lecture now
there is a real difference between the
way those equations look
and the way the continuous-time forty a
series look
in a continuous-time case let me remind
you
that it required
an infinite number of coefficients to
build up this continuous-time
function and so this was not simply a
matter
of identifying how to invert capital and
were a finite number of equations in a
finite number upon owns
and the analysis equation was
and integration as opposed to the
synthesis equation
which is a summation so
their is a real difference there between
the continuous-time and discrete-time
cases and a difference
arises to a large extent because
all this notion that in discrete-time
the complex exponentials
are periodic in
their frequency so we have been to
summarize
the synthesis equation and the analysis
equation
for the discrete-time for a series
again x7 are original signals periodic
and of course the complex exponentials
involve the periodic their periodic
obviously in an
by it in contrast the continuous-time
these repeat
in K in other words as k Omega 0
goes outside arrange that covers a 25
interval
and because if that we're imposing
in a sense the interpretation that the
AC Kesar likewise the periodic sequence
and in fact we look at the analysis
equation
as we let K very
outside the range from 0 to N -1
what you can easily verified by
substitution in here
is that this sequence will in fact
periodically repeat
so to underscore the difference between
the continuous-time and discrete-time
cases
we have this periodicity in the time
domain
and that's a periodicity dad is of
course true in discrete-time
and it's also true in continuous-time
if we replace the integer variable
by the discrete-time time variable
and we also indiscreet I'm have this
periodicity
in krak Omega 0 and correspondingly
a periodicity in the four EA
coefficients
and bad is center properties
dat does not happen
in continuous-time and is bad
there essentially leads to all of the
important differences between
discrete-time Fourier representations
and in continuous-time
Korea representation
now just quickly let me draw your
attention to the issue
love convergence and when a sequence can
and can't be represented at cetera
a recall that in the continuous-time
case
we focused on convergence in the context
either
conditions which are referred to as
where the group believe the
or another set of conditions which were
the the Ridgeway conditions
and there was this issue about when the
signal doesn't doesn't convergent
discontinuities
center let me just simply draw your
attention to the fact
there in the discrete-time case
what we have is the representation of
the periodic signal
as Assam all a finite number
turns this represents capital and
equations in capital and unknowns
if we consider the partial some namely
taking
a smaller number turns then simply what
happens
is as the number of turns increases
to the finite number required to
represent
ex-dividend we simply end up with
the partial some representing the fun
and Lightsey
were all that boils down to is the
statement
that in discrete-time there really are
no convergence issues as they were in
continues time
okay well let's look at an example love
the four EA
series representation for a particular
signal
and the one that I think here is a
simple one
namely a constant a
are signed term and a cosine term
now for this particular example we can
expand this out
directly in terms of complex
exponentials
and essentially recognize this as a
somewhat complex exponentials
its examined in more detail
in example 5.2 in attacks
and if we looked at the for a series
coefficients we can either look
at it in terms of real and imaginary
parts are magnitude and angle
on the left side here I have the real
part of the 48 coefficients
and let me draw your attention to the
fact
their I've drawn yes
to specifically illuminate the
periodicity
other for a series coefficients in with
a period of capital and so here are the
Fourier coefficients
are and in fact its this line that
represents the DCR constant term
and these two lines represent the
co-signed term and of course this
these are the three turns that are
required or equivalent leave this one
this one
and this one and then because the period
this city
the for a series coefficients this
simply periodically repeats
so here is the real part and below it I
show
the imaginary part and
in the imaginary part incidently let me
draw your attention to the fact dead its
this term and this term
there represent in the imaginary part
that represent the sinusoid
whereas its the symmetric turns the real
part
the represent the cosine okay let's
in look at another example
this is another example from the tax and
one
that will be making frequent reference
to
in this particular lecture
and what it is is
a square wave and
I've express the for a series
coefficients which are out algebraically
developed in attacks
I've expressed the for a series
coefficients as
samples all an envelope
function and so I've expressed that as
samples if this
particular function which is referred to
as a sign
enacts over sin x function and let me
just compare it
to a continuous-time example which is
the
continuous-time square wave
where with the continuous times square
wave
the form or the for a series
coefficients
was as samples love what we refer to
as a sin x over expunge
now the sin NX
over sin x function which is the
envelope for the for a series
coefficients
for the discrete-time periodic square
wave
plays the role and we'll see it very
often in discrete-time
that sin x over exercise in
continuous-time
and in fact we should understand right
from the beginning
that the sin x over extend below
couldn't possibly be
the envelope the discrete-time for a
series coefficients
and one obvious reason is dead
it is not periodic what we require of
course
from the discussion I just going through
is periodicity
are the coefficients and consequently
also periodicity of the envelope
in the discrete-time case so once again
if we look back
at the algebraic expression that I have
it samples about the sign an X over sin
x
function dead represent the for a series
coefficients
love this periodic square way
now in the representation in
the continuous-time case we
essentially head use the concept of an
envelope
to represent the for a series
coefficients
and the notion that the for a series
coefficients were samples
up an envelope and that is said the same
notion
there will be using in discrete-time so
again for this square wave example
then what we have is an envelope
function the sign acts
over sin x envelope function for
a particular value of the period here
indicated with a period
love 10 samples these
samples at this envelope function with
then
represent the for a series coefficients
if we increased
the period then
we would simply have a finer spacing
on the samples are the envelope function
to get the 40 a series coefficients and
in likewise if we increase the period
still further
what we would have is an even finer
space
so actually as the period increases
recall we use this in the in
continuous-time also
as the period increases we can view the
for a series coefficients
samples of an envelope and as the period
increases
the sample spacing gets finer and finer
and in fact as the period goes
of essentially to infinity the samples
of the envelope
in effect become the anvil and recall
also
that this was essentially the trip that
we use
in continuous-time to allow us
to develop or utilize the 48 series
to provide a representation %uh a
periodic signals
as a linear combination of complex
exponentials
in particular what we did in
the continuous-time case
when we head and a periodic signal
was to consider constructing a periodic
signal
for which be a periodic signal was one
period
and then we developed the notion there
since
the periodic signal has a forty eight
series
and since as the period
the periodic signal increases n goes to
infinity
the periodic signal represents the a
periodic signal
then essentially the 48 series
provides us with the representation now
we can do exactly the same thing in the
discrete-time case
the statement is exactly the same except
dead in a discrete-time case
instead of see as the independent
variable
we simply make exactly the same
statement
but with are discrete-time variable
and so the basic notion then in
representing
a discrete-time a periodic signal
is to first construct
a periodic signal here we have the
a periodic signal reconstruct a periodic
signal
by simply periodically replicating the a
periodic signal
the periodic signal in the a periodic
signal are identical
for one period and as
the period goes off to infinity
it's the forty a series representation
of the periodic signal
that provides a representation all
the a periodic signal again
to returned to the example
that we
have been kinda working through this
lecture namely the periodic square wave
if we have in a periodic signal which is
a rectangle
and reconstruct the periodic signal
and now we consider letting this period
increase to infinity
we would first have this set of samples
of the envelope
as the period increases we would
decrease the sample spacing to this set
of samples
as the period increases further it would
be
this set of samples and as the period
goes off to infinity
its every point on the envelope in fact
what the representation up the a
periodic signal
is is the anvil
okay well so that's the basic notion
it's no different than what we did
in the continuous-time case and
mathematically it develops in
very much the same way as in the
continuous-time
case specifically
here is our representation
through the forty a series all the
here here's a representation through the
envelope function
and this is the 48 series synthesis
equation where
equation the equation below tells us
how we'd get these for EA coefficients
or the envelope from accident
now extolled event is the periodic
signal and we know that
over one period which is the only
interval over which we use it
in fact this is identical to the a
periodic signal
its own fact we can rewrite this
equation
simply by substituting instead effect
told The
the original a periodic signal and now
we can use infinite limits on this some
and
what we would want to examine
mathematically is
what happens to the top equation
as to the top equation as we let the
period
go off to infinity and what happens is
exactly identical mathematically to
continuous-time
I won't the labor the details
essentially
its this some that goes to an integral
Omega 0 which is the fundamental
frequency is going
toward zero in fact becomes the
differential in the integral
and in the second equation of course
this then becomes excessive Omega
and as n goes to infinity then
what the for a series becomes is the 48
transform
as summarized by the bottom to
equations so although
there are is a little bit mathematical
trickery year but I called trickery but
subtlety
to be tracked through in detail the
important conceptual thing to think
about
is this notion dead
we take the a periodic signal for
periodic signal let the period go off to
infinity
which case the forty a series
coefficients became these
envelope function and incidently
mathematically
one of the sons ends up going to an
integral
so what we have then is
the discrete-time for EA transform
which is a representation all
and a periodic signal and we have
the synthesis equation which I show as
the top equation honest
transparency and this
is the integral that the four East
series
synthesis equation went to as the period
when off to infinity
and we have the corresponding analysis
equation
which is shown below where this tells us
the 48 transform
in effect the envelope all the for a
series coefficients
love that periodic signal in and here
represented interns love the a periodic
signal
okay so we have the analysis equation
synthesis equation
there are a number of things to focus
on as you look at this and we'll talk
about so its properties
actually in the next lecture by it sold
them the
points the I'd like you to think about a
focus on
the fact that now there
is somewhat have an imbalance or lack of
duality between the time-domain and
frequency-domain
x seven witches are a periodic signal is
a course
discrete its Fourier transform
Xserve Omega is a function love a
continuous variable
Omega is a continuous variable that that
and that is essentially what represents
the envelope
also in the time domain x7 is
a periodic its not a periodic function
however in the frequency domain remember
that the for a series coefficients were
always periodic
well this envelope function then is also
periodic
with a period in omega up to par i
what's again the reason for the
periodicity it all stems back to the
fact
there when we talk about complex
exponentials
and recall back to the early lectures in
discrete-time
as the frequency variable covers a range
all to parlay when you proceed past that
range
you simply see the same complex
exponentials over and over again
and so obviously anything that we do
with them would have to be periodic
in that frequency variable alright
notation Lee
and will again represent the
discrete-time Fourier transform here as
i indicate here
and sense is a complex function of
frequency
may on occasion want to either
represented
in rectangular form as i indicated this
equation
or in polar for as i indicate in this
all right let's and look at an example
and of course one example that
we can look at is the one that has kind
of been tracking this
through this lecture which is the
example
love a rectangle now
the rectangle if we refer back to our
argument love how we get a for a
representation for a periodic signal
we would form a periodic signal where
this is repeated
and thats are square wave example as the
period goes to infinity
the forty a transformer this is
represented by the envelope
all those for a series coefficients and
that was
are sign an X over sin x function
which in this particular case for these
particular numbers
is sin 5 Omega over to
divided by sign Omega over to
and notice of course as we would expect
that notice that this is a
periodic function all the frequency
variable Omega
repeating of course with a period up to
par
whereas in the time domain the function
was not
a periodic function it's a period
now let's look at another example
in let's look at example
which is another signal that has
kinda popped its head up from time to
time as the lectures have gone along
signal which is another a periodic
signal which is a decaying exponential
of this form with the
factor a chosen between 0&1
and you can workout the algebra
at your leisure basically if we
substituted to the four EA
transform analysis equation its
this summer we evaluate because we have
a unit step here
which shots this of for and less than
zero
we can change the limits on the some
this then corresponds
to the some over an infinite number
turns
geometric series and that as we've seen
before
is one divided by one minus a
you to the minus jail make so
let's look at what that looks like
here him then we have again
the expression in the time domain
and the expression in the frequency
domain
and lets in particular focus I N what
the magnitude of the Fourier transform
looks like
its as we show here
and for the particular values
Ave that I picked namely between 0&1
its larger at the origin then it is upon
I
and then of course it is periodic
and the periodicity is inherent in the
Fourier transform in discrete-time
so we really might only need to look at
this either from minus
fired upon by or from 0 to 2pi
the periodicity of course would imply
what the rest at this is for other
values have or make it
let me also draw your attention at war
on it
the fact dead observed at if
a were in fact negative then
this value would be less than this value
and in fact for a negative
the magnitude the frequency response
would look like this except shifted
by an amount in omega equal the pie
and this example will come up
and play an important role in our
discussion next time
so try to keep it in mind in fact work
it out more carefully between
now and next time and also if you have a
chance
focus on this issue love how it looks
with a positive is compared with a
negative
okay now we developed the 48 transform
by beginning with the forty a series we
did that in continuous time also
but I'd like to do now just as we did in
continuous-time
is now absorb the forty a series
within the broader framework above the
40 a transport
and there are two relationships between
the forty a series the Fourier transform
which are identical to relationships
that we had
in the continuous-time case
let me remind you dead in
continuous-time we head
the statement there if we have a
periodic signal
that in fact the forty a series
coefficients that periodic signal
is proportional to
the two samples of the Fourier transform
all one period well
in fact thats let me remind you flows
easily from all other things that we've
built up
so far because of the fact that the for
a transformer sexually
by definition love the way we developed
it
is what we get as
the forty-a series coefficients
as we focus on one period and then let
the period go off to infinity
well thats looking at one period before
a transformer that then
is the envelope above the 40 a series
coefficients
and so in continuous-time we have
this relationship and in discrete-time
we have precisely the same relationship
except that here we're talking about
an integer variable and as opposed to
the continuous variable and a period of
capital and
as opposed to a period
love t0 okay so
once again if we returned to
our example
if or Fri return to a periodic signal
we have a periodic signal and we
consider
the for EA transform love
one period the for a series coefficients
this periodic signal are in fact
samples as stated
mathematically in the bottom equation
samples
love the four EA transform all
one period so XO makers the for a
transformer one period
a suitcase at a4e series coefficients at
the periodic signal
and this relationship simply says their
related except for a scale factor
through samples along the frequency axis
and and the chorus we saw this
in the context all our
square wave example in a square wave
example we have a periodic signal
which is a periodic square wave
and the for EA transform
a one period in fact represents
the on below and here we have the
envelope function
represents the envelope or the forty a
series coefficients
and the for a series coefficients are
samples
so what we have been is
a relationship back to before a series
coefficients from the Fourier transform
that tells us that for periodic signal
now
the periodic signal the for a series
coefficients
are related are samples of the Fourier
transform
one period now
finally to kinda bring things back in a
circle
and exactly identical to what we did it
in the continuous-time
case we can finally absorber
the 48 series indiscreet
time we can absorb it into the framework
all the four EA transport now
remember or recall how we did at when
re tried to do a similar sort of thing
in continuous-time in continuous-time
what we essentially did is
to develop that more less by definition
we have occurred we have a periodic
signal
the periodic signal is represented
through 48 series
in forty a series coefficients
essentially
when I pointed out at that time was that
if we define
and take it as a definition before a
transformer the periodic signal
as an impulse train where the amplitudes
at the impulses are proportional
to the forty a series coefficients
if we take an impulse train
representation
and simply plug it in
to the for EA
transform synthesis equation what we end
up with
is the for you see recent this equation
so in continuous-time
we bad done
we had used this definition I love
the discrete-time up the continuous-time
for EA transform other periodic signal
and again in discrete-time it's simply a
matter
love using exactly the same expression
and using instead the appropriate
variables related to discrete-time
rather than the variables related to
continuous-time
so in discrete-time if we have a
periodic signal
the Fourier transform that periodic
signal
is defined as an impulse train where the
amplitudes up the impulses
are proportional to the forty a series
coefficients
if this expression is substituted into
the synthesis equation
for the 48 transform we will simply that
will simply then reduced to
this synthesis equation for the forty a
series
so wants more returning to
our example which is the square wave
example that we carry through these
lectures
or through this lecture we can see that
really what we're talking about really
is a notational change
here is the four EA here is the periodic
signal
and below it are the forty a series
coefficients where I've removed the
envelope function just indicate
the airport to the coefficients index of
course on the coefficient number
and so this represents a bar graph and
if instead of talking about the for a
series coefficients
what I want to talk about are the
is the four EA transform the Fourier
transform
in essence corresponds to simply
redrawing mad
using impulses and using
an axis that is essentially
index on the fundamental frequency Omega
rather than on the four EA series
coefficient number
K
okay in so
to summarize what we've done
is to pretty much parallel
are somewhat more quickly the kind of
development that we went through
for continuous-time representation
through complex exponentials
parallel that for the discrete-time case
and pretty much the conceptual
underpinnings that the development are
identical
in discrete-time and in continuous time
we saw there'd their are
some major differences are important
differences between continuous-time and
discrete-time
I'm and the difference essentially
relates to two aspect one aspect is the
fact that
in discrete-time we have a discrete
representation in the time domain
whereas the independent variable in the
frequency domain
is a continuous variable whereas in
continuous-time
for the Fourier transform we had duality
between the time-domain and
frequency-domain
the other very important difference tied
back to the difference between complex
exponentials continuous-time and
discrete-time
in continuous-time complex exponentials
as you very the frequency
generate distinct
time functions in discrete-time as you
very the frequency
once you've covered a frequency interval
to pie
then you've seen all the ones there are
two see there are no more
in this in a fact imposes a periodicity
on the 48 domain representation of
discrete-time signals
and those so those differences and of
course lots the similarities
will surface both as we use this
representation
and as we develop for the property
in the next lecture what will do is
to focus and again on the Fourier
transform the discrete-time Fourier
transform
develop or eliminate so love the
property serv the trip or a transform
and then see how these properties can be
used
for a number of things for example how
the properties as they were in
continuous-time
can be used to efficiently
generate the solution and analyze when
your constant coefficient difference
equations
and then beyond that the concepts of
filtering and modulation and
the both the properties and
interpretation which will very strongly
parallel
the kinds of developments along those
lines that we did in the last night
thank you